<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The speeches and prayers of Major General Harison, Octob. 13. Mr. John Carew, Octob. 15. Mr. Justice Cooke, Mr. Hugh Peters, Octob. 16. Mr. Tho. Scott, Mr. Gregory Clement, Col. Adrian Scroop, Col. John Jones, Octob. 17. Col. Daniel Axtell, &amp; Col. Fran. Hacker, Oct. 19 the times of their death. Together with severall occasionall speeches and passages in their imprisonment till they came to the place of execution. Faithfully and impartially collected for further satisfaction.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 240 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93635</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4874A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4874B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1053_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202958</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863078</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863078</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115260</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93635)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115260)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 156:E1053[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The speeches and prayers of Major General Harison, Octob. 13. Mr. John Carew, Octob. 15. Mr. Justice Cooke, Mr. Hugh Peters, Octob. 16. Mr. Tho. Scott, Mr. Gregory Clement, Col. Adrian Scroop, Col. John Jones, Octob. 17. Col. Daniel Axtell, &amp; Col. Fran. Hacker, Oct. 19 the times of their death. Together with severall occasionall speeches and passages in their imprisonment till they came to the place of execution. Faithfully and impartially collected for further satisfaction.</title>
                  <author>Harrison, Thomas, 1606-1660, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 64, 57-76, 81-96, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Simon Dover and Thomas Creeke],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno Dom. 1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The words "Mr. Tho. Scott, .. Jones," are bracketed together on title page.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page quotation from Hebrews. Variant (Wing S4874B): lacking the quotation.</note>
                  <note>With final errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>The speeches and prayers are spurious. Cf. 'Notes and queries', ser. 11, v.7 (1913), p. 301-2, whence also the printers' names.</note>
                  <note>Originally published the same year as: The speeches and prayers of some of the late King's judges.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Oct: 1st.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the originals in the British Library and the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Regicides --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Executions and executioners --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Last words --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Restoration, 1660-1688 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115260:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SPEECHES AND PRAYERS OF Major General <hi>Hariſon,</hi> Octob. 13. Mr. <hi>John Carew,</hi> Octob. 15. Mr. Juſtice <hi>Cooke,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hugh Peters,</hi> Octob. 16. Mr. <hi>Tho. Scott,</hi> Mr. <hi>Gregory Clement</hi> Octob. 17. Col. <hi>Adrian Scroop,</hi> Col. <hi>John Jones,</hi> Octob. 17. Col. <hi>Daniel Axtell,</hi> &amp; Col. <hi>Fran. Hacker,</hi> Oct. 19 The times of their Death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together with</hi> Severall occaſionall <hi>Speeches</hi> and <hi>Paſſages</hi> in their Impriſonment till they came to the place of Execution.</p>
            <p>Faithfully and impartially collected for further ſatisfaction</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Heb. 11.4</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And by it he being dead, yet ſpeaketh.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115260:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115260:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>REader,</hi> the intent of this Epiſtle is not to ſet forth (in a commendatory way) any thing concerning the perſons, or their ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, though much might be ſpoken deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly in that matter, but only to preſent unto thee the words of dying men, ſome part whereof was occaſionall Diſcourſes (betwixt them and ſome friends that viſited them) in the Priſon, yea in the Dungeon; unto every particular there are ſufficient Witneſſes in this City, unto whom we can appeale, that there is nothing patronized upon theſe ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers but what was ſpoken by them, though it is not all that was ſpoked by them, for that would have ſwelled into too large a volume: What thou haſt here therefore are but ſome ſmall mites, carefully taken out of their great treaſury. Here are alſo extracts of ſeverall
<pb facs="tcp:115260:3"/>
Letters coppied from their own hand wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings; the reſt is their Speeches and Prayers (at the time and places of Execution) taken by exact ſhort-writers, and divers of the beſt coppies have been compared, and the worke (with much care and induſtry) hath been brought to this perfection. There hath ſome ſpeciall reaſons moved us to undertake this matter: as firſt, to prevent that wrong which might be done to the deceaſed, and more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to the name of God, by falſe and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect coppies. Secondly, to ſatisfie thoſe many in City and Countrey who have much deſired it. Thirdly, to let all ſee the riches of grace magnified in thoſe ſervants of Chriſt. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that men may ſee what it is to have an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in Chriſt, in a dying houre, and to be faithfull to his cauſe. And laſtly, that all men may conſider and know, that every mans judgement ſhall be from the Lord. <hi>Prov. 29.26.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="documents">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115260:3"/>
            <head>Some occaſionall Speeches, and Memorable paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of <hi>Major Generall Harriſon</hi>'s, after his coming to <hi>Newgate.</hi> With his Speech upon the Ladder.</head>
            <p>THe day of his coming to <hi>Newgate</hi> from the <hi>Tower,</hi> at night he ſent his Wife word that that day was to him as his Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding day.</p>
            <p>When the ſentence was pronounced, he ſaid, whom men have Judged God doth not condemne, <hi>bleſſed be the name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as he was carried away from the Court through the croud, the people ſhouted, <hi>And he cryed good is the Lord for all this;</hi> I have no cauſe to be aſhamed of the cauſe that I have been inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in. Some Friends askt him how he did, he Anſwered, very well; and cannot be in a better condition if I had the deſires of my Heart; we muſt be willing to receive hard things from the hands of our Father, as well as eaſie things: when he came to Newgate there was Chaines put upon his Feet; And he ſaid Wellcome, Wellcome<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Oh this is nothing to what Chriſt hath un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergone for me; this is out of his great loving kindneſſe and faithfulneſſe, and my God is All ſufficient in all Conditions. And alſo ſoon after his coming into the Dungion in order to his Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, a Woman belonging to the Goal, who was ſent to make clean the Room, and to make a Fire for him, was askt when ſhe came out by divers people (whereof ſome were ſcoffers) how the Major General behaved himſelf and what he ſaid. To which ſhe anſwered, ſhe knew not what he had done to deſerve to be there, but ſure ſhe was that he was a good man, and that never ſuch a man was there before, for he was full of God, there was nothing but God in his mouth; ſo that it would have done any one good to have been neer him, or with him; And his diſcourſe and frame of heart would melt the hardeſt of their hearts.</p>
            <p>Some time after he was put into the Hold, Three Miniſters of the City were ſent by the Sheriffe to diſcourſe with him.</p>
            <p>And their diſcourſes was to endeavour to convince him.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Of being Guilty of the Kings Blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Of Mr. Love's Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:115260:4"/>Thirdly, <hi>Of breaking the Old Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Of being looſe in Family duties, and the Obſervation of the Lords day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>Of the juſtneſſe of this thing that was upon him by reaſon of his iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which he anſwered, As to the Blood of the King, I have not in the leaſt any Guilt lying upon me; for I have many a time ſought the Lord with Tears to know if I have done amiſſe in it, but was rather confirmed that the thing was more of God then of men; And beſides what I did, I did by Authority of Parliament, which was then the onely lawful Authority, for God owned it by pleading their Cauſe, and Fighting their Battels for them; the Lords people owned it by rejoycing in it, and praying for it; the Generality of people both in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> owned it by yeilding Obedience to it; Forreign Princes owned it by ſending their Embaſſadours, therefore it was rather the act of the Parliament, then ours that were there ſervants. He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared that he was very tender of the King, inſomuch that the King himſelf did confeſſe that he found him not ſuch a perſon as he was repreſented to him (when he was brought out of the <hi>Iſle of Weight</hi>) and that he had ſome skill in Faces, ſo that if he had but ſeen his Face before, he ſhould not have harbored ſuch hard thoughts of him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As to Mr. <hi>Love</hi>'s Death, I was in <hi>Scotland</hi> when he was Condemned and had no hand in it in the leaſt. They deſired to know if he did not ſay then, <hi>That if a Godly man ſo tranſgreſs as to being himſelf under the Condemnation of the law, it were not a juſt thing for him to ſuffer for his ſin;</hi> he told them he did not remember that he did ſay ſo, <hi>But then</hi> ſaid, <hi>if a godly man did ſo tranſgreſſe a righteous law, he ought to ſuffer as another man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, The breaking of the Parliament was the Act and Deſigne of General <hi>Cromwell,</hi> for I did know nothing of it; that morning before it was done he called me to go along with him to the houſe, and after he had brought all into diſorder, I went to the Speaker and told him; Sir ſeeing things are brought to this paſſe it is not requiſite for you to ſtay there he anſwered he would not come down unleſſe he was pulled out; Sir ſaid I, I will lend you my hand, and he putting his hand into mine came down
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115260:4"/>
without any pulling, ſo that I did not pull him; Indeed after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards I was glad the thing was done, for I did ſee they did intend to perpetuate themſelves without doing thoſe deſirable things which were expected and longed for by the Lords people; and apprehending that God had done his work by them, and that he had ſome more worthy perſons to come upon the ſtage; the Lord is my witneſſe, that I had no ſelf-end in that Action, but it was out of the Integrity of my heart as to the Lord. Afterwards when <hi>Cromwell</hi> and his party did ſet up themſelves in their room, I abhorred them and their wayes, and ſuffered impriſonment by reaſon I would not joyne with them in that iniquity and go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my conſcience; there is nothing of this alſo that lyes as Guilt upon me.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Concerning Family-duties and the Obſervation of the Lord's Day, there ſtands my Servant let him ſpeak to it; for he hath lived with me about this Eight years.</p>
            <p>The Servant anſwered, <hi>That thoſe reports were very falſe; for his Maſter was a man in a manner wholly devoted to religious Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, very frequent in prayer, and diligent in expounding the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, to the great comfort and conſolation of his whole Family, and that he was very zealous in obſerving the Lord's day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, He ſaid that the Lord's Spirit did witneſſe with his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, That all his ſins were done away by Jeſus Chriſt, and that he had peace with God, and was aſſured that this was not come upon him for his iniquity.</p>
            <p>They diſcourſed of many other things, but theſe were the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, ſo far as one then preſent could afterwards remember. He parted very ſweetly and lovingly with the ſaid Miniſters, and they told him that they came then by the deſire of the Sheriffe; But that they would willingly come again upon a Chriſtian ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
            <p>Many Friends came to viſit him whilſt he was in that place, and found him full of the joy of the Lord; ſo that ſome apprehended he was cloathed with the Spirit of the Lord.</p>
            <p>The Sheriff came that morning that he was to die, and told him that in half an hour he muſt be gone; He anſwered that he was ready and would not have him ſtay at all on his account. But the Sheriff left him to ſtay a little longer, and in the mean time,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115260:5"/>
he was longing for the Sheriffs coming, and as his Friends judged he was in haſt to be gone, and ſaid, he was going about a great work for the Lord that day, and that his ſupport was, that his ſufferings was upon the account of Jehovah the Lord of Hoſts: he ſaid, he looked upon this as a clear anſwer of his prayers; for many a time ſaid he, have I begged of the Lord, That if he had any hard thing, any reproachfull work, or contemptible ſervice to be done by his people, That I ſhould be imployed in it; <hi>And now bleſſed be the Name of God, who accounteth me worthy to be put upon this ſervice for my Lord Chriſt: Oh, this is nothing to what Chriſt hath ſuffered for me!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He parted with his wife and friends with great joy and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe as he did uſe to doe when going ſome journey or about ſome ſervice for the Lord; He told his wife he had nothing to leave her but his Bible; but that he was aſſured that God would make up all her loſſes in due time, and deſired that thoſe that did love him ſhould manifeſt their love in being loving and tender to his dear wife.</p>
            <p>Some paſſages at the Dungeon dore as he came forth, The She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe commanding the Keeper to acquaint <hi>Mr. Harriſon</hi> he muſt go to ſuffer; the Keeper came forth and returned anſwer, that he was ready when he pleaſed: Then the Sheriff commanded the Keeper to fetch him forth; ſo he came forth immediately, ſooner then was expected; (running down the Stairs with a ſmiling countenance) by reaſon of his ſudden coming, the doore (that he was to go up a pair of Stairs at) was not opened, which occaſioned his ſtay in the Hall till the Keeper could be found; and there one Mrs. <hi>M.</hi> took him by the hand, and ſaid, with a loud voice, <hi>Bleſſed be the great God of Hoſts, that hath enabled you and called you forth to bear your teſtimony, the God of all grace and peace be with you, and keep you faithfull to the death, That you may receive a crown of life.</hi> With that one of the Officers pulled the woman away by the ſhoulder, ſaying, Away with this woman ſhe ſtands prating here. But the Maj. General replied, Be not offended with her, ſhe ſpeaks Scripture-language: So they thruſt her away from him, and would not permit any to ſpeak more to him in that place. Then he ſpake, ſaying, <hi>I bleſſe the Lord that hath called me forth, and hath inabled we in the power of his ſtrength, to offer my
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115260:5"/>
life with ſatisfaction and cheerfulneſs in obedience to the will of God. I bleſs the Lord I am full of the manifeſtation of his love in the Lord Jeſus; It's a day of joy to my ſoul. I ſay God hath enabled me, to whom all the powers of the world are but as the drop of a bucket;</hi> &amp; ſaid he, I <hi>do find ſo much of the joy of the Lord coming in, that he was carried far above the fear of death being going to receive that glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and incorruptible crown which Chriſt hath prepared for him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then he was carried into a Room where the common Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners were, and told them what a ſad thing it was to be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to die, and to want the love and favour of God: But it's not ſo with me; for though I die, yet I know I ſhall live with Chriſt to all eternity, and this is out of the exceeding riches of the grace of God; for he it is that maketh the difference; For as I am in my ſelf, I am a baſe, vile, and nothing-creature; but compleat in him who is the Head of all Principalities and Powers. Poor men! I wiſh you all as well as I doe my own Soul. Oh that you did but know Chriſt! his bowells earns towards the greateſt of ſinners; his bloud is ſufficient to doe away the deepeſt iniquity; he waiteth to be gracious and is willing to receive all that come unto him: Oh therefore labour to come to Chriſt; your time in this world is ſhort and uncertain; you are walking upon the brink of eternity, and are ready to drop in every moment, if you die without the fear of our God you will be miſerable for ever &amp; ever; but if you come to know Chriſt to be yours, it will be your joy and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs world without end. He then put his hands into his pocket and gave them ſome money, and wiſhed them to take heed of ſinning againſt the Lord. And from thence was carried upon the Leads on the top of <hi>New gate,</hi> ſo that he could ſee the greateſt part of the City, he then ſaid, <hi>The earth is the Lords and the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thereof, and there is nothing hid from his eyes.</hi> From thence he was carried down two paire of ſtaires, where he was tied about the back, breaſt, and ſhoulders; he took the rope in his hand and ſaid, <hi>friends take notice that God gives me power to receive this with thanksgiving</hi> and he helped the Sarjeant to put on the rope. Then a friend came weeping to him to take her leave of him, he ſaid, <hi>hinder me not, for I am going about a work for my maſter.</hi> Then looking about him ſaid, <hi>Sirs,</hi> Its eaſie to follow God when
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115260:6"/>
he makes a hedge about us, and makes liberall proviſion for us: but its hard for moſt to follow him in ſuch a diſpenſation as this; and yet my Lord and Maſter is as ſweet and glorious to me now as he was in the time of my greateſt proſperity.</p>
            <p>He alſo ſaid, this I can ſay for my ſelf, <hi>That according to the light that God hath given me, I have ſerved him and my Countrey with integrity and uprightneſſe of heart, not willingly, nor wittingly wronging any;</hi> But this have I done with much infirmity and weakneſſe. One telling him, that he did not know how to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the mind of God in ſuch a diſpenſation as this, He ſaid, <hi>wait upon the Lord; for you know not what the Lord is leading to, and what the end of the Lord will be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this, addreſſing himſelf to a Gentleman, he ſaid, <hi>I dare not nor cannot be a pleaſer of men:</hi> a friend anſwered, it appeared ſo by your declining <hi>Cromwell</hi>'s Intereſt; which words he aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to, and further ſaid, the manner of my ſpeaking before the Court may ſeem ſtrange to ſome; but my Deſign was not to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove my ſelf before Men but God; and what I ſaid, was accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my conſcience. And as the Rope was tying on he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s words to <hi>Abraham, Father, here is the wood, but where is the Sacrifice?</hi> and alſo ſaid, <hi>if the Lord ſee good, he can provide another ſacrifice, he can deliver thoſe that are appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to die; but his will be done, Death is not terrible to me; yea, it is no more to me then a Ruſh, I have learnt to die long ago.</hi> And was often heard to ſay, concerning the Lord's diſpenſation to him and his people, <hi>Shall not the Lord do with his own what it pleaſeth him?</hi> And ſo parting with his Friend, went down ſtairs to the Sledge, and askt which my muſt I ſit, for I am not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with this: <hi>Good is the Lord in all his waies.</hi> Then he was carried away in the Sledge, having a ſweet ſmiling Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, with his eyes and hands lifted up to Heaven, his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance never changing in all the way as he went to he place of Execution, but was mighty cheerful to the aſtoniſhment of many. He called ſeveral times in the way, and ſpoke aloud, <hi>I go to ſuffer upon the account of the moſt glorious Cauſe that ever was in the world.</hi> As he was going to ſuffer, one in a Deriſion called to him and ſaid, Where is your <hi>Good Old Cauſe?</hi> He with a cheerful ſmile clapt his hand on his Breſt, and ſaid, <hi>Here it is, and I am
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115260:6"/>
going to ſeal it with my bloud.</hi> And when he came to the ſight of the Gallows he was tranſported with joy, and his ſervant askt him how he did, he anſwered, never better in my life: his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant told him, Sir, there is a Crown of glory ready prepared for you, Oh yes ſaid he! I ſee it; when he was taken off the Sledge, the Hangman deſired him to forgive him, I doe forgive thee ſaid he with all my Heart as it is a ſin againſt me; and told him he wiſh't him all happineſſe. And further ſaid alas poor man thou doſt it ignorantly; the Lord grant that this ſin may not be laid to thy charge: and putting his hand into his pocket, gave him all the money he had; and ſo parting with his Servant, hugging of him in his arms, and went up the Ladder with an undaunted countenance.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <head>M. Gen. <hi>Harriſon's</hi> Speech upon the Ladder.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I did not expect to have ſpoken a word to you at this time, but ſeeing there is ſilence commanded, I will ſpeak ſomething of the work God had in hand in our dayes.</p>
            <p>Many of you have bean Witneſſes of the Finger of God that hath been ſeen amongſt us of late years in the deliverance of his people from their Oppreſſors, and in bringing to Judgement thoſe that were guilty of the precious bloud of the dear ſervants of the Lord, And how God did witneſs thereto by many wonderful and evident teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, as it were immediatly from Heaven; inſomuch that many of our Enemies, who were perſons of no mean quality, were forc'd to confeſs, <hi>That God was with us, And if God did but ſtand newter they ſhould not value us;</hi> And therefore ſeeing the Finger of God hath been pleading this Cauſe, I ſhall not need to ſpeak much to it: In which work I with others were engaged; for the which I do from my ſoul bleſſe the name of God, who out of the exceeding riches of his grace accounted me worthy to be inſtrumentall in ſo glorious a work, and though I am wrongfully charged with murder and bloudſhed, yet I muſt tell you I have kept a good conſcience both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, and towards man; I never had malice againſt any man, neither did I act malitiouſly towards any perſon, but as I Judged them to be Enemies to God and his people; And the Lord is my
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115260:7"/>
witneſſe that I have done what I did out of the ſincerity of my heart to the Lord, I bleſſe God I have no Guilt upon my conſcience, but the ſpirit of God beareth witneſſe that my Actions are acceptable to the Lord through Jeſus Chriſt; though I have been compaſſed about with manifold Infirmities, Failings and Imperfections in my Holieſt duties; but in this I have comfort and conſolation, that I have pace with God, and do ſee all my ſins waſh't away in the blood of my dear Saviour. And I doe declare as before the Lord, that I would not be guilty wittingly, nor willingly of the blood of the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſon, no not for ten thouſand Worlds, much leſſe of the blood of ſuch as I am charged with.</p>
            <p>I have again and again beſought the Lord with Tears to make known his will and mind unto we concerning it, and to this day he hath rather confirmed me in the juſtice of it, and therefore I leave it to him, and to him I commit my wayes; but ſome that were emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in the work, did wickedly turn aſide themſelves, and to ſet up their Neſts on High which cauſed great diſhonour to the name of God and the profeſſion they had made, And the Lord knows I could have ſuffered more then this rather then have fallen in with them in that iniquity, though I was offered what I would if I would have joyned with them, my Aime in all my proceedings was the glory of God, and the good of his people, and the wellfare of the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth.</p>
            <p>The people obſerving him to tremble in his hands and leggs, he taking notice of it ſaid,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> By reaſon of ſome ſcoffing that I do hear <hi>I</hi> Judge that ſome do think I am afraid to dye by the ſhaking I have in my hands and knees, I tell you no, but it is by reaſon of much blood I have lo<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t in the Wars, and many wounds I have recceived in my body, which cauſed this ſhaking and weakneſse in my Nerves, <hi>I</hi> have had it this twelve year, <hi>I</hi> ſpeak this to the praiſe and glory of God; he hath carryed me above the fear of death: and <hi>I</hi> value not my life becauſe <hi>I</hi> go to my Father and am aſſured <hi>I</hi> ſhall take it up again.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> Take notice that for being inſtrumentall in that cauſe and intereſt of the ſon of God which hath been pleaded amongſt us, and which God hath witneſſed to by Appeals and VVonderfull Victories; <hi>I</hi> am brought to this place to ſuffer death this day, and if <hi>I</hi> had ten thouſand lives, <hi>I</hi> could freely and cheerfully lay them down all to witneſſe to this matter.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:115260:7"/>Oh what am <hi>I</hi> poor worm that <hi>I</hi> ſhould be accounted worthy to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any thing for the ſake of my Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>I</hi> have gone joyfully and willingly many a time to lay down my life upon the account of Chriſt, but never with ſo much joy and freedome as at this time; <hi>I</hi> do not lay down my life by conſtraint but willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for if <hi>I</hi> had been minded to have run away, <hi>I</hi> might have had many opportunities, but being ſo clear in the thing <hi>I</hi> durſt not turn my back nor ſtep a foot out of the way by reaſon <hi>I</hi> had been engaged in the ſervice of ſo glorious and great a God; however men preſume to call it by hard Names, Yet <hi>I</hi> believe ere it be long the Lord will make it known from Heaven that there was more of God in it then men are now aware of: <hi>All the Gods of the Nations are but Idols, they have Eyes but ſee not, and Mouths but ſpeak not, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſave thoſe that truſt in them. But my God is the King of Kings and Lord of Lords, before whom all you here, and all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are but as a drop of a Bucket. And he will never leave thoſe that truly truſt in him, unto whoſe Glory I ſhall ſurely go, and ſhall ſit on the right hand of Chriſt in Heaven, it may be to Judge thoſe that have Unjuſtly Judged me,</hi> Matth. <hi>25.33, 34. 1</hi> Cor. <hi>6.2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Sheriffe minding him of the ſhortneſſe of time, it he had any thing to ſay to the people he might.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He ſaid <hi>I</hi> do deſire as from my own ſoul, that they and every one may fear the Lord, that they may conſider their latter end, and ſo it may be well with them; and even for the worſt of thoſe that have been moſt malitious again<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t me, from my ſoul <hi>I</hi> would forgive them all ſo far as any thing concerns me, and ſo far as it concerns the cauſe and glory of God <hi>I</hi> leave it for him to plead; and as for the cauſe of God <hi>I</hi> am willing to juſtifie it by my ſufferings according to the good pleaſure of his will.</p>
            <p>I have been this morning, before <hi>I</hi> came hither, ſo hurried up and down Stairs (the meaning whereof <hi>I</hi> knew not,) that my ſpirits are almoſt ſpent; therefore you may not expect much from me.</p>
            <p>Oh the greatneſſe of the love of God to ſuch a poor, vile, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing creature as <hi>I</hi> am! what am <hi>I</hi> that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> ſhould ſhed his hearts Bloud for me that <hi>I</hi> might be happy to all Eternity, that <hi>I</hi> might be made a ſon of God, and an heir of Heaven! Oh, that Chriſt ſhould undergo ſo great ſufferings and reproaches for me, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115260:8"/>
ſhould not <hi>I</hi> be willing to lay down my life and ſuffer reproaches for him that hath ſo loved me! Bleſſed be the Name of God that <hi>I</hi> have a life to loſe upon ſo glorious, and ſo honourable an account: then praying to himſelf, with tears; and having ended, the Hang-man pull'd down his Cap; but he thruſt it up again, ſaying, <hi>I</hi> have one word more to the Lords people that deſire to ſerue him with an up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right heart: Let them not think hardly of any of the good wayes of God for all this; for <hi>I</hi> have been near this ſeven years a ſuffering perſon, and have found the way of God to be a perfect way, his Word a tried Word, a Buckler to them that truſt in him, and will make known his glorious Arm in the ſight of all Nations. And though we may ſuffer hard things, yet he hath a gracious end, and will make for his own glory and the good end of his people; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be cheerfull in the Lord your God, hold faſt that which you have, and be not afraid of ſuffering; for God will make hard and bitter things ſweet and eaſie to all thoſe that truſt in him: keep cloſe to the good Confeſſion you have made of Jeſus Chriſt, and look to the recompence of reward; be not diſcouraged by reaſon of the cloud that now is upon you; for the Son will ſhine, and God will give a teſtimony unto what he hath been a doing in a ſhort time.</p>
            <p>And now <hi>I</hi> deſire to commit my Concernments into the hands of my Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he that hath delivered himſelf for the chief of ſinners; he that came into the world, was made fleſh, and was crucified, that hath loved me, and waſhed me from my ſins in his own bloud, and is riſen again, ſitting at the right Hand of God making interceſſion for me.</p>
            <p>And as for me, Oh, who am <hi>I?</hi> poor, baſe, vile worm, that God ſhould deal thus by me; for this will make me come the ſooner into his glory, and to inherit the Kingdome, and that Crown prepared for me! Oh, <hi>I</hi> have ſerved a good Lord and Maſter which hath hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped me from my beginning to this day, and hath carried me through many difficulties, trialls, ſtraits, and temptations, and hath alwayes been a very preſent help in time of trouble; he hath covered my head many times in the day of Battle: By God <hi>I</hi> have leaped over a Wall, by God <hi>I</hi> have run'd through a Troop, and by my God <hi>I</hi> will go through this death, and he will make it eaſie to me. <hi>Now into thy Hands, O Lord Jeſus, I commit my ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="documents">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:115260:8"/>
            <head>Some Occaſionall Speeches, and Memorable paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges before Execution of Mr. <hi>John Carew.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHen the firſt tidings of the Adverſaries intentions to ſeize and apprehend him (being then in <hi>Cornwall</hi>) came to his knowledge, he uttered theſe words or to this effect. That he had committed both his life and eſtate to the Lord; to ſave or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, as he thought meet; and therefore he would not by any means go out of the way, though provoked thereunto by ſeveral Friends.</p>
            <p>After he was ſeized upon in the Countrey, and coming up to <hi>London,</hi> he had a gratious preſence of the Lord with him: ſweetly ſupporting him in the ſenſe of the love of Chriſt to his ſoul; and being perſwaded, that the cauſe of his ſuffering from man was ſuch, as he had no cauſe to be aſhamed of; otherwiſe, the many reproaches and hard uſage in the way to <hi>London</hi> had been ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to have troubled his ſpirit. In moſt Towns where he came, the Generality of the people Reviling him, with ſuch words as theſe: hang him Rogue, piſtol him, ſaid others, hang him up ſaid ſome (at <hi>Salisbury</hi>) at the next ſign-poſt without any further trouble Look ſaid others how he doth not alter his Countenance; but we believe he wil tremble when he comes to the Ladder. This is the Rogue will have no King but Jeſus. Indeed, the rage of the people all the way was ſuch, that had he not been indued with ſtrength from on High, he could not have under-gone the wicked and Barbarous Deportment and Carriage of the Giddy multitude which he was ſubjected to.</p>
            <p>After he came to <hi>London,</hi> and had many opportunities of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape, if he had thought it meet (before he was ſent to the <hi>Tower</hi>) yet he would not, knowing how much the Name and Glory of God was concerned in his faithful witneſſe to the cauſe of Chriſt for which he was in Bonds. And the truth is, his joy in the Lord was ſuch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that when many came drooping in ſpirit to him (by reaſon of the Gloomineſſe of this preſent diſpenſation) they went away refreſhed and comforted by thoſe many Gracious words that came out of his mouth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:115260:9"/>When word was brought him that Maj. General <hi>Harriſon</hi> was dead, he ſaid well, my turn will be next, and as we have gone a long in our Lives, ſo muſt we be one in our Death. The Lord God grant, that I may have ſtrength from himſelf to follow coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly to the laſt breath; and that I may much honour and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God, whom I have made profeſſion of; I can do nothing of my ſelf, but my ſtrength is in the Lord of Hoſts, who hath help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me from my beginning to this day, and will help me to the end. The night before he ſuffered, ſome of his Natural Relation came to take their leave of him, and when they were parting, they ſhed ſome tears, but when he perceived it ſaid, O my friends, if you did know and feel what joy I have, and what a Glorious Crown I ſhall receive from the hand of Chriſt (for this work) you would not Mourn, but Rejoice, that I am counted worthy to be a witneſſe to this Cauſe, and ſaid further, <hi>The Lord preſerve you all from the portion of this Generation;</hi> for aſſuredly, There is great wrath from the Lord that will reach them to their deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. When Mr. L. came to take his leave of him, he asked this Queſtion (<hi>viz.</hi>) how it was with him? he Anſwered, very well I bleſs my God; as to my intereſt in him I have not the leaſt doubt, but do know aſſuredly, that when my ſoul ſhall be ſeparated from this body, I <hi>ſhall be taken into his preſence where is fullneſs of joy,</hi> &amp;c. And by Jeſus Chriſt be preſented to my Father, without ſpot and blame, in his own compleat and perfect righteouſneſſe which is free, and not for any of mine own works: for I am a poor ſinful and wretched creature, and compaſſed about with many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities. And when it was asked him, if he had any thing of conviction upon him as to what he was to ſuffer for? he anſwered no, not in the leaſt, for ſaid he, Though man have Condemned, yet the Lord hath and doth juſtifie; he added, the Lord had ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifyed it in the Field once already in this Nation (but that is now accounted as a thing of Nought) but he will again do it with a Witneſſe, and prayed that the Lord would deliver him (<hi>viz.</hi>) Mr. <hi>L.</hi> from that Judgement that was at hand by which he would do it. To this effect ſpake he alſo to many that did quere with him about this matter—being told that his Nephew and ſome others were doing their utmoſt for his Reprieve, he replyed, that there is nothing to be done: For the Sheriffe hath brought me
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115260:9"/>
word (juſt now) that I muſt Dye to morrow, and that there was ſome that deſired I might not be Quartered, but it would not be granted. But Death is nothing to me, let them Quarter my body never ſo much, God will bring all thoſe pieces together again. It was asked him if he had aſſurance of the love of God? he ſaid, yea, yea, he had Fought a good Fight and had overcome, and he was ready to ſuffer the will of God. One asked him if he thought there would be a Reſurrection of the Cauſe? he Anſwered, he Dyed in the Faith of that, as much as he did that his body ſhould riſe again &amp; if he did not believe that, he ſhould not be ſo cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full at the Sentence of death, he ſaid alſo he had not the leaſt regret or diſturbance on his ſpirit about that for which he was to die, for what he did was of the Lord, &amp; if it were to be done again he wold do it. And the way they took to ſuppreſſe and deſtroy thoſe that did not think the Kings perſon Sacred, their blood will make many hundreds more perſwaded of the truth of it: it was grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous to him, to hear how at his Tryal they blaſphemed God and his people; but he was reſolved he would own the Lord among them, which they could not bear, Therefore they were ſo violent againſt him: he ſaid the Goſpell was going from <hi>London,</hi> &amp; Popery and Superſtition, &amp;c. was coming in, and it would be a rare thing to find a profeſſor of religion in <hi>London</hi> ſhortly; he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged thoſe about him, to keep cloſe to the Lord in this evil day Oh! ſaid he, who would have thought ſome yeers ſince, that Poper<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Formality ſhould have been let in again to theſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? he ſaid, they were ſo Barbacus, they would not allow him ſome ſmall time to take a little Reſt before he was to ſuffer; which was all he needed or deſired of them; For he was much tired with ſpeaking to company which came continually in: He deſired to be remembred to ſome Friends, and tell them, <hi>That this was the laſt Beaſt, and his Rage was great, becauſe his time was ſhort.</hi> Some more Expreſſions he uttered to this effect. But in all his words and manner of ſpeaking, he manifeſted the higheſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Magnanimity and holy Greatneſſe of mind, and ſuch a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of joy and glory reſted upon him, even to aſtoniſhment. It was asked if he apprehended his confidence would contniue to the death? he ſaid, he was not ſtrong in his own ſtrength, but in the Lord's ſtrength, which he ſtill relied upon. And he ſaid to one
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115260:10"/>
by him, will you not ſee how God will carry me through next day? and deſired prayers for him. One asked him, what he thought of this ſevere hand of God? He ſaid, that which was hid ſecret in the boſome of the Father, ſhould be manifeſted in due time: Oh! ſaid he, it grieves me to think how Popery is coming upon us like a flood in this poor Nation, and the great judgement that will follow. But the Lord will be a hiding place for his poor people untill the indignation be overpaſt: let not our enemies think to break the Spirit by putting us to death; for I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, That God will give his Spirit ſeven-fold unto thoſe that are left; but the enemy, the Lord hath ſet their feet in ſlippery places, ſo that when they come to their meaſure, they muſt be caſt down: Therefore 'tis the the duty of the Lord's people to wait patiently <hi>and he that ſhall come, will come, and will not tarry.</hi> 'Tis a trying time, and none but thoſe that are endued with power from on High, will be able to hold out. One asking him, where his Chain was? he ſaid, here it is; and though I have worn it ſo long, that it hath entred into my fleſh, yet it was not as <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s, it had not entred into his ſoul. He was highly rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up in admiring the grace of God, That he ſhould be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted worthy to wear a Chain for Chriſt, ſaying, They have been bleſſed Chains to me; adding, that the Lord had crowned him beyond many of his Brethren, being counted worthy to ſeal Gods work with his bloud; admiring that God ſhould accept of ſuch a craſie body: much of his ſtrength being already ſpent; yet, That God ſhould ſo honour it in the end; he much admired the depths of the love of God to ſuch an unworthy worme. The Lord will bring my bloud (ſaith he) to cry with the reſt of the Martyrs, <hi>How long, O Lord, Holy and True,</hi> &amp;c. As for death, or the fears of it, I am got above them, in and through the behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the glory of our God, into which I am entring: which glory ſhall be ſhortly for the reviving of the ſpirits of his Saints, and deſtroying his Enemies. A friend ſpeaking to him (the night before he died) of this diſpenſation he ſaid, he was perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, That their bloud would be of much advantage to the <hi>Cauſe</hi> in Foraign Nations. Two Friends that came to viſit him, being (as he thought) under ſome trouble of ſpirit, he directed his ſpeech to them, as follows; Be not troubled, there is nothing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115260:10"/>
ſtands between me and the Father; for I go with all clearneſſe and freedome, and, I know, That Jeſus Chriſt is my compleat Righteouſneſſe; and this is my crown of Rejoycing, <hi>That I die not in the Lord onely, but for the Lord;</hi> And think not that this bleſſed <hi>Cauſe</hi> ſhall be loſt; for it ſhall reach to the end of the Earth. Think not your prayers loſt; for your prayers and tears with our bloud, ſhall come down ſhortly upon <hi>Babylon,</hi> although they think to heale her, yet they ſhall give her a greater blow then ever we could have given her in our perſons. Thoſe who have been pleading for ſuffering, who ſo ready to run away from it? While the Lord hath given us a little of the ſpirit of Rejoycing, that hath made us willing to be giving up our ſelves unto him. And, although the Enemy think to Conquer us, they ſhall never do it; for we are got above them in the Spirit of the Kingdome; we trample upon them, and they are under our feet; and this bloud that now ſhed, ſhall warm the bloud that hath bin ſhed before; and ſhall come down and doe notable Execution upon the Enemy. The Lord hath (in much wiſdome) hid this death from us, and hath alured into it; but he hath fitted us for it, and be not troubled that he hath taken away two or three drops of the ſpirit; for he will in the room thereof pour it out upon you.</p>
            <p>The day he ſuffered and the hour being come, The Rope be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tyed about him, he rejoyced exceedingly, ſaying, Oh! what am I, that I ſhould be bound for the Cauſe and Intereſt of the Son of God? And when he was coming down <hi>Newgate</hi>-ſtairs to go into the Sledge, in a very ſmiling, cheerful manner, his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance ſhining with great glory, uttered words to this effect; My Lord Jeſus, for the joy that was ſet before him, endured the Croſſe, and deſpiſed the ſhame and is now ſet down on the right hand of God; whoſe ſteps deſire to follow. It was alſo obſerv'd that the cheerfulneſs of his countenance all the way as he went to the Gibber, remained, to the encouragement of the Faithfull, and admiration of enemies, uttering by the way many chearfull expreſſions ſetting forth his joy in the Lord.</p>
            <p>When he was brought to the gibbet, before he went up the lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der (his hands being bound) he exhorted ſeverall friends ſtanding by, to be faithfull unto death; and not to be aſhamed of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115260:11"/>
cauſe for which they ſuffered, and they ſhould receive a Crown of life. And further ſaid to a friend that ſtood by, That he hoped the Truths of the Kingdom which he had preached up and down would not be the leſſe eſteemed, for that he now came to ſeale it with his blood.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <head>Mr. <hi>Carew's</hi> Speech upon the Ladder.</head>
            <p>TRuly, it is not words, nor that which I have to ſpeake in mine own ſpirit, will glorifie God; or give any advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to your ſoules, or unto me: but it is, if I may ſpeak a few words in the Spirit of the Lord, and in the power of his might, and from an unfeigned love unto Jeſus Chriſt: that would indeed give me an open entrance, and make my paſſage very ſweet; and a bleſſing may be left behind, even upon you. The firſt thing (indeed) that hath been very weighty (and I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to leave it upon all, upon Saints as well as upon thoſe that are not acquainted with Jeſus Chriſt) that Eternity, Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, and Eternall life, it is a wonderfull thing; the thoughts and apprehenſions of it are able to ſwallow up a poor ſoul: we little think what it is; he that knows moſt of God, and moſt of Chriſt, and hath the greateſt meaſure of the anoynting, he little, little knows what it is to appeare before the holy, the moſt glorious, the moſt righteous God of Heaven and Earth: to ſtand before his judgement ſeat, before Jeſus Chriſt that is at his right hand: and where all the holy Angels are ſo aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med (becauſe of the glory of God) that they fall down and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their faces, and cry <hi>Holy, holy, Lord God Almighty, which art, and waſt, and art to come.</hi> And therefore if ſuch glorious creatures, if ſuch excellent Spirits as theſe Seraphins and Cherubins be, if they do fall down before the glory and Majeſty of this moſt excellent and wonderfull God, how ſhould duſt and aſhes doe? and how ſhould they feare and tremble to appeare before him? And therefore, I ſay, think of this, and of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115260:11"/>
the righteouſneſs of God, as well as of his glory and Majeſty, and of his juſtice; that when for one ſinne he threw down the Angels (thoſe glorious Spirits) into hell, and he would take no ranſome or redemption for them; and though he hath mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy on the ſons of men (according to his own election and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and according to that that he hath purchaſed for himſelf in Chriſt Jeſus before the foundations of the World was laid) yet in time he made his Sonne a Sacrifice before men, and Angels to bring his choſen ones to glory. That he ſhould take pleaſure to ſend his own Sonne out of his boſome, who was the delight of his ſoule, and bruiſe him for our ſinnes; yet it pleaſed the Father to bruiſe him. The moſt holy and righteous God, that had but one Sonne, one onely begotten Sonne (that was the delight of his ſoule) and ſhould take pleaſure to bruiſe him, that we might be healed, and laid ſtripes upon him that we might be healed. oh! the height and depth, oh! the length and bredth of the love of God in Chriſt Jeſus unto poor ſouls. Oh! this is that the Angels do deſire to ſtoope down and looke into, and to know more of this great myſtery of the love of God in Chriſt: and that God ſhould take upon him the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man, and put him into that glorious union with his own Sonne; and that he ſhould leave the Angels, though Chriſt was made a little lower then they for ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering death for us: yet now, becauſe the nature of man is united to the Godhead by vertue of that marriage and un<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on, we become the ſonnes of God, and heirs of glory. Thoſe that are adopted by Jeſus Chriſt are brought neer to the Throne of glory, are in a high and glorious communion and fellowſhip with the Father and Spirit, owned of all the holy Angels. And therefore they doe ſtand without the Throne (as in ſeverall places of the <hi>Revelations</hi>) <hi>and round about the Elders, and round about thoſe that were given to the Lambe</hi> (as in the fifth of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> and many other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures)
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115260:12"/>
they ſtand without, but there is another company with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in which is the <hi>24</hi> Elders, and four living creatures, they fall down and worſhip God, they are neerer then the Angels; Oh! who hath credited, who hath believed this report, and to whom is the arm of the Lord revealed? Oh! how many profeſſors are there in this day, in this Nation, that call upon the name of Chriſt, and that ſay they ſhall be ſaved by Chriſt, and doe live and truſt moſt in their awn works and righteouſneſs; and never come to the knowledge and underſtanding of this great myſtery of the love of God in Chriſt? who never recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved thoſe teachings from the Anointing, and according to the new covenant, where it is promiſed that they ſhall be all taught of God, all the children of God ſhall be taught of him, and there is no one can teach theſe but the Father, none can draw them to the Sonne but the Father; and no man can come to the Father but through the Sonne: and this great myſterie is both by the light and opperation of the holy Spirit, who makes the new creature in the ſoule: o that God would poure out of his holy Spirit; that God would poure out the Spirit of the new Covenant, and the ſpirit of the Goſpel, and the ſpirit that can declare the myſtery of Gods word in the Spirit, and that he hath made manifeſt through Jeſus Chriſt. oh! there is much talking and ſpeaking in the name of Chriſt, and how many men ſpend little time in getting evidences in the power and demonſtration of the Spirit, and come to apprehend God in Chriſt, that ſpeake of him? Oh! time are few of theſe the Lord knows. O that the annoynting may be poured out more now, according to this faith, in the way of this grace, and in this love of God, even in the electing love of the Father; and in the redeeming blood of Jeſus Chriſt, according to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed poſſeſſion that he hath obtained through his own righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, wherein God hath been juſt alſo, in juſtifying the ungoldy; and among them, ſuch a poore ſimple piece of duſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115260:12"/>
and aſhes as I have been, and have to this day little glorified my father; and yet I can call him father, through ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his ſpirit, and father according to the ſpirit of adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to; and can ſay the Lord Jeſus hath given himſelfe for me, and I take the Lord Jeſus Chriſt as the great gift of the Father, deſiring to bear witneſſe of that love, and of that won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull grace and glory, that he hath made me partaker of in and through him. Oh! bleſſed be the God and Father of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, who hath called me to this hope, and who hath made me partaker of this glory, that the Saints an enlightned in. And now I long to ſee the face of this father, and of his Sonne, though I have ſuch a number of ſinnes in me; and though I have an intereſt in him, and can call him Father at any time without doubt, and in full aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of faith in the holy Spirit, yet if Jeſus Chriſt were not there, to preſent me faultleſſe before the preſence of God, I ſhould be afraid to appear e before him; but he is able to doe it, and therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Now unto him that is able to ſave you, and to preſent you faultleſſe before the preſence of his glory with exceeding joy, &amp;c.</hi> I am a poore ſinfull piece, full of iniquity, laden with many burdens, that have a body of death that I carry about me, and I am now about to lay it down, and my ſoule ſhall enter into eternall life, and be made perfect in a moment, through the mighty power of God that hath wrought that glorious work of raiſing Chriſt from the dead. Oh! all my ſtrength, and all my joy, and all my life is in Chriſt, and in him alone; and I have a righteouſneſſe already of his working, according to his owne grace, and according to his own mighty power, and according to his own mercy, that he hath been pleaſed to worke in me; and ſo hath been pleaſed to keep me in a very wicked and in a very evill day, by the power of his grace. And I deſire to glorifie my father, and many years have I been in that worke,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115260:13"/>
that hath been of late in this Nation; few and evill have been the daies of my pilgrimage, but I have deſired to ſerve the Lord with faithfulneſſe, and in the integrity of my ſoule, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prejudice againſt any creature; and it hath been the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of my ſoule to approue my ſelfe faithfull towards God, and towards man: and what I have done I have done it in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Lord; that I had in my eye, and in my heart. There are many things laid upon many of thoſe that profeſſe the Kingdome and glorious appearane of Jeſus Chriſt, as if they were enemies to Magiſtracy and Miniſtery; and, as if ſo be we were for the deſtruction of the Lawes and properties of mankind, therefore ſhall I ſpeak a few words unto that. And if indeed we were ſuch, we were fit to be turned out of the World; as ſome now think they ſhould doe God good ſervice in ſending ſuch poore creatures quickly from hence. There is no ſuch thing; I deſire to beare witneſſe to the true Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy, that Majeſtracy that is in the Word of the Lord. And that true Miniſtery, which Miniſtery is a Miniſtery from the annoynting; that doth beare witneſs to the Lord Jeſus, and hath his holy Spirit. That teſtimony I deſire to beare; and that teſtimony I deſire to ſtand faithfull in, with integrity to the Lord Jeſus, as King of Saints, and King of Nations. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is, I ſay, to have a Majeſtracy as at the firſt, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors as at the beginning, men fearing God and hating cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs. And that Miniſtery as doth preach the everlaſting Goſpell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Here Mr. Sheriffe interrupted him ſaying,</hi> 'tis deſired that you ſpend the reſt of your time in preparing your ſelfe. <hi>Another ſaid,</hi> you ſpend your ſelf, Sir, in this diſcourſe. <hi>Another ſaid,</hi> it raines. <hi>Then Mr.</hi> Carew <hi>ſaid,</hi> I will pray,</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:115260:13"/>
            <head>Mr. <hi>Carew,</hi> his Prayer.</head>
            <p>O moſt holy, and moſt glorious and bleſſed God, the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Father of all Glory; The God of the ſpirits of all Fleſh; unto thee, unto thee doth my ſoule deſire to come through the new and living way, even through Chriſt my Righteouſneſſe: And in him and through him to be offered up by the Eternall ſpirit, a living and acceptable Sacrifice, in which thy ſoul delighteth. O Lord, thou knoweſt my frame, and thou knoweſt my life, and what a paſſage this is; and what a wonderfull thing it is, to enter into Glory. And what a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thing it is to ſtand before thee, and to ſtand in thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. O Father, father, let my ſoul be filled with thy joy, and with peace in Believing; O Let my heart be in heaven while my body is here; and O Let me be joyned unto the Lord, through thine own ſpirit before this ſeparation be—O Lord, thou on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly art able to take hold of my Heart and Spirit; poor Creatures may ſpeak words to thee, but Oh! it is thine own power, and it is thine own ſpirit, that muſt take hold of the heart; it is thine own ſpirit that muſt carry through all, and it hath heen thy ſpirit (Ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſed be thy Name) that hath carryed me through many Tryals, and many Temptations, and many Difficulties, that thy poor Worme hath met with in this Pilgrimage for many Years. O Bleſſed by thy Name for all the Goodneſſe, and for all thy Grace, and for all thy preſence that hath been with thy poor Creature far and neer. Oh! Bleſſed be thy Name that thou haſt kept me in any meaſure faithful to <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>to thee, and made me willing to lay down my life for thy <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ous Work and Cauſe, Oh Bleſſed be thy Name, that the Lord and Chriſt (that is at thy right hand) hath bought me with his own moſt precious bloud. He hath Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed me indeed. Therefore it is but my reaſonable ſervice
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115260:14"/>
that I ſhould be offered up a ſacrifice to him, my joy is in him, and my confidence is in him, that I ſhall be preſented by him to my heavenly father. O father, when thy ſervant is to be preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before thee, let him know what it is to finde mercy. Let him know what it is to have Jeſus Chriſt an Advocate; and what it is to be preſented before thee by ſuch a Redeemer. O that Jeſus Chriſt might bid me welcome into the preſence; and may ſay to my ſoule, <hi>Well done good and faithfull ſervant, enter thou into the joy of thy Lord.</hi> O bleſſed Father, it is not that I doe expect any thing from thee upon any account below the account of the Lord Jeſus: and wherein ſoever thou haſt been glorified by thy poor ſervant, it hath been by thine own power and thine own working. O nothing unto thy poore creature is due, but unto thy holy name be praiſe and glory. O holy father, behold thy work in the Kingdomes, and behold the cauſe and intereſt of all thy people. O doe thou revive it in thine own appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted time; O doe thou ſtrengthen the starts of thy poor Saints: O ſcatter all clouds, ſpeak comfortably to their ſoules, that they may be able to ſtand under all ſtorms, faithfull into the death, and receive a Crown of life and glory. O bleſſe the poor Saints in the City, and bleſſe thy Saints in the Country: and bleſſe thy Saints in the Weſt: O bleſſe thy ſonnes and thy daughters; O bleſſe all the meetings of thy people, let the bleſſing of the Lord appear unto them, let the glory of the Lord make haſte; let the glory of the Lord be upon theſe Nations. O remember thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to thy ancient people the Jewes; O let thy people be taught of thee, O let theſe drie bones live, O let the Spirit of life breath upon them. O dear father let the fulneſſe of the Jewes and of the Gentiles be brought in. Let multitudes be gathered out of every Kindred, and Tongue, and Nation, unto the Kingdome of Jeſus Chriſt. O Father, Father, advance thy Sonne; ſet him as King upon the mountaine of thy holineſſe; give him all glory, and power and dominion over the whole Heavens, that thou haſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed according to thy word and covenant to give unto him: that he may raigne in thine own word and law, through his own Spirit for ever and ever. Lord, lord I deſire thou wouldſt ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther up my ſoul, O gather up my ſoule O Lord, make this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage ſweet, O make it comfortable. Lord Jeſus thou haſt taken
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115260:14"/>
away the ſting of death, and born the burden of all this ſhame, and of all this reproach. And thou haſt given thy poor ſervant ſomething of thy preſence, through the riches of thy grace this day. O Lord, now receive, O open thine everlaſting armes: O now let me enjoy thy preſence O God, which I have deſired to behold and ſee, and to behold thy face in Jeſus Chriſt, O, and now let me enjoy what thou haſt prepared for me: and fill me with the joyes that are at thy right hand, and thoſe pleaſures that are in thy preſence for ever more. O thou lamb of God lead me to the everlaſting Fountain, that living fountain that is able to ſupply all our wants. O Lord bleſſe, bleſſe thy poor people; O comfort them in this day. Poure out ſevenfold of thy Spirit for what thou doſt take away in any of thy ſervants, for thy holy Names ſake. O let the cauſe and kingdome of Chriſt be deare and precious in thy ſight, and live alwaies. Lord little doe theſe (poor creatures) know, or theſe Nations know, what a contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie thou haſt with them. O that thou wouldeſt be pleaſed gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly to ſpare this people, ſpare thy people however; and let them that love <hi>Zion,</hi> and favour thy righteous cauſe, be glad for ever and ever. O now Father be neer to me doe thou receive my ſpirit, take me into thine own glory, take me into thine own glory; let me know it is my portion, let me know there is a Crown in the hand of Chriſt prepared for my ſoul. O bleſſed Lord, thou haſt honoured thy poore creature, and brought him hitherto, O reward all the labours of love in any to him, in bonds or death; and give them a double reward into their own boſomes. Reward it ſo to them and theirs. Bleſſed be thy name that thou haſt brought thy poor own hither to ſuffer in thy cauſe. And O Lord, let thy ſpirit be powred forth upon the Nations, until the whole Earth be filled with the knowledge of thy Glory. And that Chriſt Jeſus may have all the Honour, and Praiſe, and Glory, and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion for Ever, and Ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am ſo exceeding Dry that my Tongue is ready to ſtick to my Mouth. But I would fain ſpeak a little more. Oh bleſſed be God! oh! how many are the Refreſhments I have had from the preſence of my God and Father, ſweet, and ſecret
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115260:15"/>
Communion betw'xt him and my ſoul to day. And for that my ſoul hath ſeen of his Riches and Kindneſſe. O that I might be more like Chriſt! for I have been very unlike to Jeſus Chriſt, very unlike to my Father. But I ſhall leave all that is unlike Chriſt behind; And all his own Work manſhip he will purifie and perfect through this paſſage into Glory. O my Dear Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, receive my ſoul, O! make this paſſage ſweet, for now I am coming to thee; Lord Help, Lord Spirit me, fill me with thy Spirit, let me be ever with thee, let me know what it is to have thee at my Right Hand, that I may not be moved; that in my ſoul going out of the Fleſh, I may be let into the preſence of God, and into the Arm of Jeſus Chriſt. Oh! That my ſoul may be breathed forth into the Arms of God, into the Boſome of Jeſus Chriſt, through the Anointing of the Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Friend that ſtood by ſaid, it is expected you ſhould ſpeak ſomething to the matter of your ſuffering; The under Sheriff ſaid 'tis not to be ſuffered, What are you? that you put on men to ſpeak, What are you Sir?</p>
            <p>Mr. Carew <hi>ſaid, Farewell my dear Friends, Farewell; the Lord keep you faithfull.</hi> The Friend ſaid, we part with you, with much Joy in our Souls.</p>
            <p>Mr. Carew <hi>ſaid to the Executioner, ſtay a while, I will ſpeak one word, and then ſaid very ſolemnly and with a loud voyce,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lord Jeſus receive my Soul, Lord Jeſus into thy Armes I Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my Spirit.</p>
            <p>And ſo fell a Aſleep.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="documents">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:115260:15"/>
            <head>Some occaſionall Speeches, and Memorable paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of <hi>Mr.</hi> Juſtice <hi>Cooke,</hi> during his Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the <hi>Tower</hi> and <hi>Newgate.</hi> With his Speeches and prayer upon the Ladder.</head>
            <p>HIS Wife coming to viſit him in the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> but not having Admittance to him, he ſaw her forth of his Window, and ſaid to home to thy Friends my Dear Lamb I am well, <hi>Bleſſed be God they cannot keep the Comforter from me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His wife asking the Gentleman Jaylor to ſee him (another time) He anſwered, ſhe might ſee him ſuddenly in <hi>Newgate,</hi> her Husband hearing of this, ſaid, <hi>If the way to the new Jeruſalem be thorough Newgate, bleſſed be God for Newgate, the King of Glory will ſet open his Everlaſting Gates to receive me ſhortly, and then I ſhall for ever be with the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="note">
                        <head>A Note ſent by him from the <hi>Tower.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>My <hi>D. L.</hi> chear-up, Heaven will make amends for all, bleſſed be God I am full of ſpiritual Joy, and do muſt God to make what bargain for me he pleaſeth, for he knoweth the appointed time of my Compoſition and Diſſolution, <hi>let us look to Jeſus Heb.</hi> 12.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>After Mr. <hi>Cooke</hi> was brought to <hi>Newgate</hi> diſcourſing with ſome Friends there, he ſaid, I am now going to my Tryal, wherein the Lord ſtrengthen me. If I be attainted yet my Eſtate in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is not thereby Forfeited without an Act of Parliament to that purpoſe, and indeed it is much ſet upon my heart, that if my ſmall Eſtate be taken away from my poor Wife and Child, it will prove as poyſon to thoſe that enjoy it, and Conſumptive to the reſt of their great Eſtates, for I bleſſe God I never Acted Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litiouſly, or Covetouſly, but in a ſpirit of Simplicity and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, however the good will of the Lord be done.</p>
            <p>I commit and commend my Dear, Loving and Faithful Wife and Child to their bleſſed Husband and Father, with three ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures eſpecially for their portion. <hi>The Widdows cruſe and barrel of meal,</hi> 1 King. 17. Iſa. 54. ver. 5. to 10. Jer 49.11. <hi>Earneſtly deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115260:16"/>
that my Child may be Religiouſsy Educated in the fear of the Lord.</hi> Thus if God hath appointed it, I ſhall go from the Croſs to the Crown.</p>
            <p>Speaking to ſome in priſon, for the clearing of himſelf from falſe Aſpertions, ſaid, whereas ſome ſay I have done them wrong, they do much wrong me in ſo ſaying, I have relieved many ſo far as by law I could, knowing that the worſt of men ought to have Juſtice; I bleſſe God I durſt not wrong any man, for I know that I ſhall meet them at the laſt day before the Bar of Chriſts Judgement, where I can with boldneſſe look all men in the Face as to matter of Juſtice, for which I have great cauſe to bleſſe the Lord, <hi>Holy be his Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some in the priſon ſpeaking of the Differences in Religion, Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> ſaid, pray talk not of controverſies now, we have but a little time to live and cannot ſpend it in ſuch diſcourſes.</p>
            <p>Whereupon,</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Cooke</hi> ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed be God brother Peters we are going to Heaven, where the Saints are all of one mind, which my ſoul hath long deſired to ſee, it rejoyceth my heart to think what a perfect hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe I ſhall have there; the beſt condition here is but mixed, but in Heaven there is no ſorrow nor trouble, neither have I one drame of trouble upon my ſpirit at this time, bleſſed be God he hath wiped away all tears, and I could with Paul and Silas ſing in priſon for Joy,</hi> Bleſſed be the Comforter.</p>
            <p>Diſcourſing after he came into the Dungion, he ſaid, when a poor Creature comes about ſo Solemne a work as to Dye, what a bleſſed thing is it to have a Helper, and what can help but the holy ſpirit; bleſſed be the Comforter for I am full of ſpiritual Conſolation; if one of you was to have a Thouſand pounds a year after the death of an Old man Conſumptive, that would not live three dayes, how would you rejoyce; this is my Condition through Grace, I muſt in a little time put off the Old man, and enter into the poſſeſſion of Heavenly Glory. Let no good people fear a priſon, for it is the only place, wanting other books to ſtudy the book of ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Friend going about to comfort Mr.</hi> Cooke <hi>from the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the brevity and uncertainty of mans life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> uſing ſome expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of love,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:115260:16"/>Mr. <hi>Cooke</hi> replyes, what doſt thou ſpeak thus for, if I were ſick of a <hi>Feavour</hi> this might be a ſutable diſcourſe, but we muſt talk at a higher rate then this now; were I to chuſe, I would rather chuſe this death then to Dye of a <hi>Feavour,</hi> for there is much pains and ſometimes diſtractions, but here a man is well when he goes upon the Ladder and out of all pains in a quarter of an hour; And ſpeaking to a Friend ſaid, I am now going to Heaven and ſhall leave you in the ſtorm.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Mr. Cook to ſome Friends in priſon</head>
               <p>Friends I beſeech you rejoyce with me, O let us bleſſe the Lord that he counts us worthy to be ſacrifices to follow his ſteps, was not the Captain of our Salvation made perfect through ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, and ſhall not I, Oh I long to be at home, out of the body with the Lord, though I go through a ſea of Bloud to him; truly I think every Hour Ten; little doe my Enemies think what a Friendly part they do me, to haſten me to my Fathers Kingdom, to my Crown and Glory; I had rather go to my Dear Jeſus with my Chain and Croſſe, then to ſit down with an Earthly King on his Throne and wear a Crown of Gold.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Some disaffected to him being preſent ſaid, the Jeſuits ſuffered chearfully and confidently.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Cooke</hi> replyes, I bleſſe God my juſtification is not built upon the merits of Works, but alone upon Grace in the bloud of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſaid perſon compared him and his fellow priſoners to</hi> Corah, Darhan <hi>and</hi> Abiram.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well friends ſaid he, it matters not who condemnes, when God juſtifies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. Cooke <hi>(ſaid they) do not juſtifie your ſelf, but confeſs your ſins, your haynous crime againſt the Lord and his Anointed, and Reſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Cooke</hi> replyes, I muſt needs tell you that if Repentance was now to doe, I was in a ſad condition, but I bleſſe my God he hath inabled me to confeſſe my ſin, and hath ſealed my pardon in the bloud of his Dear Son, and given ſuch peace as none can give or take away. I have no Guilt nor Trouble upon my ſpirit touching what is done, but ſuch ſweet peace in God as I cannot expreſſe, and I ſhall leave all with God who judgeth righteouſly, who will decide all things.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:115260:17"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Mr. Cooke</hi> to <hi>Mr. Peters</hi> in the Dungion ſaid</head>
               <p>Brother <hi>Peters</hi> we ſhall be in Heaven to morrow in bliſſe and Glory, what a bleſſed thing is that, my very heart leaps within me for joy, I am now juſt as I was in the <note n="*" place="margin">See his Relation of his paſſage by Sea to <hi>Ireland,</hi> and his dream.</note> ſtorm, almoſt in ſight of Heaven, read me the <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.9.10. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.10.11. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.14.</p>
               <p>Then looking upon his bed, ſaid, that ſhall be my laſt Pillow, I will lay me down and ſleep awhile, and he ſlept about an hour and half, and then awoke, ſaying, now farewel ſleep, no more ſleep in this World, and farewel Darkneſſe and Night, I am go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing where there ſhall be no Night there, neither need of a Candle, nor of the Sun, for the Lord will give us light, <hi>yea the Lord will be our Everlaſting light and our God will be our Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And welcome every thing that gives notice the hour is at hand, welcome the Cock that crowes, welcome ſweet death my good Friend that will bring me ſo near Eternity. O bleſſed be God, bleſſed be his Name, Oh this Chriſt is a bleſſed Chriſt, he anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth all things, and within few hours we ſhall be crowned with Glory and Victory; bleſſed be our Lord Jeſus that hath given us the Victory over Sin and Death. Welcome Mr. <hi>Loman</hi> my keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, welcome Angels, that will within few hours take the Office and Guard me into Eternity.</p>
               <p>At midnight he prayed very fervently, and the common pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners heard him, and ſeemed very ſorrowful by their expreſſions ſaying, Sir the Lord be with you, O that our ſouls might go where your ſoul goes.</p>
               <p>About the Morning ſpeaking to Mris. <hi>Cooke</hi> ſaid, Lamb do not diſhonour my laſt Wedding day by any trouble for me; For if all my Judges did but know, what Glory I ſhall be in before Twelve of the Clock they would deſire to be with me.</p>
               <p>And let the Executioner make what haſt he can I ſhall be <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> hand with him, for before he can ſay here is the Head of a Traytor, I ſhall be in Heaven. <hi>Come Lord Jeſus come quickly, my ſoul longeth for thee, and I wait to hear thy voyce ſaying, come up hither, and immediately, I ſhall be in the Sprit;</hi> and then ſhall I for ever be with the Lord. At and midnight there was a cry
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115260:17"/>
heard the Bridegroome cometh, and they that were ready went into the Marriage; <hi>This day I ſhall enter into the joy of my Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Come brother <hi>Peters</hi> let us knook at Heaven Gates this morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, God will open the dores of Eternity to us before Twelve of the Clock, and let us in to that innumerable company of Saints and Angels <hi>and to the ſouls of juſt men made perfect,</hi> and then we ſhall never part more, but be with the Lord for Ever, and Ever, Singing praiſes, Singing praiſes to our Lord and Everlaſting King to all Eternity; he ſaid further, O what a good maſter have I ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that ſtands by me now, and ſupports me, with his Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Arme he bears me up; (then ſaid) <hi>come away my beloved make haſt, and be thou like unto a young Roe, or a young Hart upon the Mountaines of Spices,</hi> Behold I come Lord Jeſus, I come full ſayle to thee I come upon the wing of Faith, Lord Jeſus receive me; and going to lye down upon his bed he ſaid, it is no more to go to dye to morrow then it is to go to ſleep to night. I bleſs the Lord I am free from trouble, and my poor heart is as full of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual eomfort as ever it can hold, <hi>And this joy can no man take from me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The dores of the priſon being opened in the morning, he ſpent that little time he had left in prayer and heavenly diſcourſe with Friends that came to viſit him, preparing himſelf, for his ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, with ſuch a cheerfulneſſe, as was an Aſtoniſhment to the ſpectators.</p>
               <p>Then ſpeaking to his Wife ſaid, farewel my Dear Lamb, I am now going to the ſoules under the Alter, That cry how long O Lord holy and true; doſt thou not Judge and Avenge our bloud on them that dwell on the Earth, and when I am gone my bloud wil cry and doe them more hurt then if I had lived. But I am now going to eternity, bleſſed be God, be not troubled for me, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, becauſe I goe to my father and your father, to my God and your God. And after ſome time ſpent in prayer, he deſired his wife not to withhold him by an unwillingneſs to part with him now when God called for him, to be offered up as a ſacrifice for his name and cauſe.</p>
               <p>After a little pauſe ſhe freely gave him up to the Lord; to which he replied, Now all the work is done, and ſaid, I reſign thee up to Jeſus Chriſt, to be thy husband, to whom alſo I am going to be married in glory this day.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:115260:18"/>His wife ſhedding tears, he ſaid, Why weepeſt thou? let them weep who part and ſhall never meet again; but I am confident we ſhall have a glorious meet in heaven; here our comforts have been mixt with chequer work of troubles, but in heaven all tears ſhall be wiped from our eyes.</p>
               <p>He asked ſeverall times if the Sheriffe was not come, ſaying, why ſtaieth the wheeles of his chariot? why doe they drive ſo heavily? I am ready bleſſed be God, I have nothing to due but to die;</p>
               <p>Word being brought that the Sheriffe was come, he makes haſt to be gone, and his wife ſtepping after him tooke him by the arme, whereupon he ſaid, <hi>O doe not hinder me from going to Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And then with a chearfull countenance, taking leave of his friends, he went to the ſledge that carried him, whereon was alſo carried the head of Major Gen. <hi>Tho. Harriſon,</hi> with the face bare towards him; and notwithſtanding that diſmall ſight he paſſed rejoycingly through the ſtreets, as one born up by that Spirit which man could not caſt down. Being come to the place of exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, when he was taken out of the ſledge, he ſaid, <hi>this is the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieſt chariot that ever I rid in in all my life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being come upon the ladder, and the rope put about his neck he rejoyced, ſaying, <hi>Bleſſed be the name of God, that</hi> I <hi>am bound for the ſake of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then his work was to addreſſe himſelf to God, and to that end ſaid, if you pleaſe I ſhall ſpeak a few words to God in prayer.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="prayer">
                           <head>Mr. <hi>Cookes</hi> prayer before his ſpeech.</head>
                           <p>Moſt glorious Majeſty, this day is a repreſentation of that great day when all thy poore people ſhall meet together, multitudes, multitudes in the valley of deriſion, Thy poor poor ſervant is now come to pay the debt which he oweth to nature, bleſſed be thy name that thou haſt prepared him for it, bleſſed be thy name ſweet Jeſus, bleſſed be thy name. O that all thy poor people that are here if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible may feel ſomething of that divine power and aſſiſtance of God, that thy poore ſervant now feels at this time; bleſſed be thy name. <hi>I</hi> am a poor creature, a poor ſinner, and the Lord might juſtly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115260:18"/>
from me, and leave me to horrour and fearedneſs, if he ſhould deale with me in juſtice. But this hath not been his method (bleſſed be his name) to leave and forſake his poor ſervant. Lord let thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing be upon us at this time, and let thy bleſſing be upon England, and let thy bleſſing be upon all theſe Nations, and let thy bleſſing be upon all that are here; Aſſiſt O Lord, by thy divine power; give us to ſee much of thy power, and let not this meeting be in vain, but let every one here receive benefit thereby, to the praiſe and glory of thy great name, and the everlaſting ſalvation of all our ſoules (if it be thy bleſſed will) through Jeſus Chriſt our Lords</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Having ended his firſt prayer, he applies himſelfe to the Shie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe and ſpectators in this following ſpeech:</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="speech">
                           <opener>
                              <salute>Mr. Shieriffe and Gentlemen,</salute>
                           </opener>
                           <p>The moſt glorious ſight that ever was ſeen in the world was our Lord Jeſus Chriſt upon the Croſſe; and the moſt glorious ſight next to that, is to ſee any poor creature ſuffer for him in his cauſe.</p>
                           <p>I deſire to ſpeake a few words, briefly to let you underſtand what a glorious worke the Lord hath been pleaſed to accompliſh upon my ſpirit. I bleſſe the Lord, I have ranſacked into every corner of my heart, and I have ſearched into all my ſinnes, actual and original, ſecret and open, known and unknown, ſo farre as the Lord hath diſcovered them to me; and I have confeſſed them all with a penitentiall bleeding heart, and contrite ſpirit; bleſſed be his name he hath been pleaſed to come in abundant manner, and hath been pleaſed to ſhew me that the onely remedy is the blood of Chriſt; and I have, bleſſed be the Lord, applied that precious blood to my poor ſoul, and have laid hold upon a Chriſt, by a true and lively faith; and there is a ſweet calme and ſerenity in my ſoul, and conſcience, bleſſed be thy name. I deſire to glorifie God, and to give him the glory of all, and to take ſhame unto my ſelfe for any ſinnes that I have ever committed, that I know to be ſinne. and therefore I deſire to rejoyce in the God of my ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as, <hi>Iſai</hi> 61, 10. <hi>I will greatly rejoyce in the Lord, my ſoul ſhall be joyfull in my God, for he hath cloathed me with the garment of ſalvation; he hath covered me with the robe of righteouſneſs, as a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115260:19"/>
Bridegroom decketh himſelf with ornaments: and as a Bride ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth her ſelf with Jewels: Even ſo the Lord delighteth in me. And as the earth bringeth forth her buds, and as the garden cauſeth the things that are ſown in it to ſpring forth: ſo the Lord will cauſe righteouſneſs and praiſe to ſpring forth before all Nations.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>And <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 43.9, 10. <hi>Ye are my witneſſes, ſaith the Lord,</hi> I doe deſire to bear a teſtimony unto God, and to Jeſus Chriſt, for ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and truth, and righteouſneſs and holineſſe.</p>
                           <p>The Lord knows I have no malice upon my heart againſt any man or woman living upon the face of the earth; neither againſt Jury that found me guilty, nor Court that paſſed ſentence; <hi>I</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire freely to forgive every one from the bottom of my heart. And as concerning this great diſpenſation you may (it may be) deſire to hear ſomething of it. Truly, <hi>I</hi> ſay, as to the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, <hi>I</hi> have not any hard thoughts concerning him: my prayer ſhall be for him that his Throne may be upheld by truth, and by mercy; for <hi>by mercy,</hi> as <hi>Prov.</hi> 23. <hi>the Throne is upheld.</hi> But <hi>I</hi> muſt needs ſay, that poore we have been bought and ſold by our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> was.</p>
                           <p>Brother hath betrayed brother to death; and that Scripture is in a great meaſure fulfilled, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.21. <hi>The father againſt the ſonne, and the ſonne againſt uhe father; and brother ſhall deliver up brother to death. I</hi> deſire for my own part to kiſſe the rod; and <hi>I</hi> doe deſire (if it may pleaſe the Kings Majeſty) that no more blood may be ſhed after miae: it may be the Lord wil put it into his own breaſt.</p>
                           <p>Here is a poor brother comming, <hi>I</hi> am afraid that he is not fit to die at this time; I could wiſh that his Majeſty might ſhew ſome mercy.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>The Shieriffe interrupted in words to this effect: <hi>let that alone, for the Kings Majeſty hath clemency enough for all but his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers murtherers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Cooke</hi> replied, then <hi>I</hi> ſhall proceed to ſpeak ſomething con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning my profeſſion and faith, which <hi>I</hi> bleſs the Lord, is founded upon the rock Chriſt Jeſus. <hi>I</hi> doe not expect ſalvation for any thing <hi>I</hi> have ever done, but onely lay hold upon Chriſt as a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Chriſt, and there to bottome my ſoule.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> can ſay to the praiſe and glory of God, that <hi>I</hi> have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vored
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115260:19"/>
in my place and to my power, to doe that which might be to Gods glory, according to the beſt of my underſtanding. I have ſtood for a Goſpel Magiſtracy and Miniſtry, and that many delays in the law might be removed, (and that thing I have much ſuffered for) I ſay its good both for King and people, that many delays in matter of juſtice ſhould be removed, and that publique juſtice might be ſpeedily and cheaply adminiſtred.</p>
               <p>And as for my profeſſion, I am of the Congregational way, I deſire to own it, and am for liberty of conſcience, and all that walk humbly and holily before the Lord; and deſire to walk in the fear of the Lord; and I believe it is a truth, and there can be nothing ſaid againſt it. I doe confeſs I am not convinced of any thing I have done amiſſe, as to that I have been charged with, I am not indeed; neither did I underſtand the plea of the Court, that if the Lords and Commons had brought the King to the Bar, and ſet him over them again, their bringing him to the barr had been treaſon.</p>
               <p>I deſire never to repent of any thing therein I have done; but I deſire to own the cauſe of God and of Chriſt; and am here to beare witneſs to it, and ſo far as I know any thing of my ſelfe I can freely confeſs it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here the Sheriffe interrupted him again, deſiring him to forbeare any ſuch expreſſions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Cooke</hi> replied, it hath not been the manner of Engliſh men to inſult over a dying man, nor in other countries among Turks or Galliaſſes.</p>
               <p>The Lord bleſs every one of us, and help us that we may look more to the honour and glory of God then the concernments of our own lives: for alaſs what is a poor miſerable life to us, but that therein we might give honour and glory to the God of all our mercies.</p>
               <p>And if there be any here of that Congregation to which I was related in the time that I lived here, I would commend to them that Scripture, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.17, 18. <hi>Yea and if I be offered up upon the ſacrifice and ſervice of the faith, I joy and rejoyce with you all, for the ſame cauſe alſo doe ye joy and rejoyce with me.</hi> And <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.11. <hi>The Lord God of your Fathers make you a thouſand times more then you are, and bleſſe you as be hath promiſed.</hi> The Lord be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115260:20"/>
to ſpeake comfort to them, and to all them that feare the Lord.</p>
               <p>The Lord keepe <hi>England</hi> from popery, and from ſuperſtition, and keep it from prophaneneſs, and that there may not be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undation of Antichriſt in the land. And that is all the harm I wiſh unto it.</p>
               <p>The Lord hath forgiven me many thouſand talents, and therefore I may wel forgive thoſe few pence that are owing unto me. I bleſs the lord I have nothing lying upon my conſcience, but I can unboſome my ſelfe to every one, and to the throne of free grace, in the ſimplicity of my ſpirit, I have endeavoured to doe nothing but with a good conſcience, and through the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity of my heart though accompanied with many frailties.</p>
               <p>I deſire to bleſſe the Lord, my lot was rather in <hi>Ireland</hi> then here, here <hi>I</hi> have been more known where I have given the Offence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Sheriffe again interrupted him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr. Cooke</hi> replyes, Sir I pray take notice of it, I think I am the firſt man that ever was Hanged for demanding of Juſtice, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I hope you will not interrupt me.</p>
               <p>I ſuppoſe yon were there, and doe bear me witneſſe in your conſcience, that there was not any thing then, that I did not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate to the Court that I now ſpeak upon the Ladder.</p>
               <p>If you will believe the words of a dying man, I ſay as I muſt give an account, I have nothing lyeth upon my conſcience. We muſt all meet together at the great day of the Lord to give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all our Actions, (and then it will appear) the Lord grant we may meet with Joy and Comfort.</p>
               <p>I have a poor Wife and Child and ſome Friends left, I deſire you that came along with me, to commend to them, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 54.4.5. and 10. ver.</p>
               <p>I hope the King and Parliament will conſider our poor Friends as to their Eſtates, you know that thoſe Lords that formerly ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffered under the Parliament, did not looſe all their Eſtates; I hope there will be ſome conſideration as to Juſtice, (leaſt that our ſmall Eſtates prove a poyſon amongſt their great deal) and my poor Wife and Relations ſuffer.</p>
               <p>The Lord grant that mercy may be ſhewed, that mercy and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115260:20"/>
righteouſneſſe may magnifie and exalt it ſelf above Juſtice. I ſhall not hold you long; I ſhall deſire in the fear of the Lord to give my ſelf (as in the 12 <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.) <hi>A living Sacrifice, Holy and Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table unto God, which is but a reaſonable ſervice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo doe intreat that I may have a little time to call upon the Lord, unleſſe there be any thing more deſired, or any one to would ask me a queſtion.</p>
               <p>Truly I forgive all from my heart, I have nothing upon my heart to accuſe any of them withal. I bleſſe the Lord I have a cleare Conſcience, I ſay it in the integrity and ſimplicity of my heart, (I doe now appeale to the great God, to whom I muſt give an account of what I have done) knowing that all my Guilt is waſhed away in the blood of Jeſus Chriſt, (and before him I hope to appear,) and have nothing elſe to plead any thing at all for me.</p>
               <p>And ſo I hope that I have declared my ſelf with ſimplicity and integrity, in a few words that you may underſtand my mind.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I ſhall ſpeak a few words to the lord in prayer, and ſhall not trouble you further.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Mr. Cookes Prayer.</head>
               <p>MOſt Glorious Majeſty, I beſeech thee, ſo to warm my Heart, and fill it ſo full of the love of Jeſus Chriſt, that it may never be cool any more; Oh that the Lord would now appear Graciouſly to ſhew himſelf a wonder working God, in bearing up the Heart and Spirit of thy poor creature, it is no matter how bitter the Cup is, if the Lord give ſtrength to drink it, and no matter how heavy the Burden be, if the Lord be at one End, and uphold the other, and bear the burden himſelf, or lay no more upon his poor Children then they are able to bear; the Lord give ſtrength to all that are to bear this bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; the Lord be with all that are yet to ſuffer in this cauſe, and double and treble ſeven-fold of thy Spirit upon us, let us not ſtand it out againſt our Reaſons and Judgements and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences. If any did purſue power and intereſt, and did not
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115260:21"/>
look after the good of Gods poor People, and the good of the Nations, the Lord forgive them. The Lord knows the Simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of the Hearts of his poor Servants that are gone before, and of thoſe that are to come after; I deſire that all thine may have hearts willing to ſuffer for thee, to make confeſſion of Faith in Chriſt Jeſus, I know is nothing, I know it is not enough onely to confeſſe in Words, to confeſſe in Doctrinall E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelicall Truths, and to confeſſe by a holy life and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation; and if the Lord call any of his poor Children to ſeale the truth with their blood, yea their precious blood, it is their duty alſo; if the Lord Jeſus had come down from the Croſſe, and had not ſhed his moſt precious blood, and had not by that blood gone to heaven our Salvation had not been. Lord let it be well with England, the Lord hear me for my poor Friends and Relations, for my poor Wife and Child; unto thee Lord I commend the cauſe of God, and of Jeſus Chriſt, And re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member poor Ireland wherein I had a lot and intereſt, the Lord remember them all, and help thy poor Children to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue Faithfull unto Death, that ſo we may receive a Crown of life, for the ſake of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: and ſo I come Lord Jeſus, Oh receive my ſoul! Send down a Guard of Angells to convey my ſoul into Abrahams Boſome; Receive my ſoul, O Lord, into thy hands I commend my Spirit. And I deſire to appeal to thee O lord, thou art the great God of Heaven and Earth before whom all controverſies muſt come.</p>
               <p>I believe there is not a man in the world what ever he be, but hath ſome reverentiall feare of death; but for any ſinfull vitious fear; I bleſs the Lord I have not the hundredth part of a dram upon my conſcience; if it were my wedding day I could not more rejoyce in the Lord, becauſe it is a conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of that bleſſed marriage that my Lord Jeſus hath made up with me. Bleſſed be thy name, me thinks I doe ſee with <hi>Stephen,</hi> even by the eye of faith, Heaven open, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115260:21"/>
the Lord Jeſus ready to receive my poor ſoule. And oh that I may with <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſee the glory of God; and ſee, with <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> the Lord ſitting on his Throne of glory. And oh that the love of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the Spirit may warme my heart, and carry me up from the beginning of this paſſage to the end and cloſe of it. Lord Jeſus come and receive my ſpirit, and ſweeten this cup, and let me ſay, <hi>The cup which my Father hath given me, ſhall I not drink of it?</hi> And I leave all into the hands of the Lord, that if it be the Lords will every one that belongs to the election of grace my meet with comfort at the great day, and that we may ſhake hands together, where no office of love ſhall be unrewarded, nor any unkindneſs ſhewed to the people of God.</p>
               <p>But within a few hours I ſhall be in the harbour; I am juſt now entring into it, I would not goe backe againe for all the world.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed be the Lord I deſpiſe the ſhame, and am willing to endure the croſſe, for Chriſts ſake; becauſe the Lord Jeſus, who is the author and finiſher of my ſalvation, did it for me. The Lord pitty thoſe that follow, and bear up their hearts.</p>
               <p>The Lord helpe his poore people that finde any thing upon their ſoul; that they ſhould ſtand faſt unto the truths of Jeſus. Alas, we ſhall be but a few daies here, and Heaven will make amends for all, and we ſhall glorifie God in eternity, where we ſhall enter into a ſinleſſe, timeleſſe, and temptationleſs eſtate, and never meet with ſorrow or troubles any more; but the Lord will receive us to himſelfe, and then the innocency of thy poor ſervants ſhall be vindicated, and we ſhall be ever with the Lord, bleſſing and praiſing his holy name.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Elijah</hi> was taken away, the ſpirit of <hi>Elijah</hi> reſted on <hi>Eliſha,</hi> who ſtood up in his ſtead. And when <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt was cut off, the Lord had his Apoſtles to ſupply that office. The Lord will have profit in the Death of his Children. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115260:22"/>
that an Army of Martyrs would willingly come from Heaven to ſuffer in ſuch a cauſe at this that I come here to ſuffer for.</p>
               <p>I deſire to bewaile that I have not had ſo much love to the Glory of God therein as I ought. But as to the thing I come to ſuffer for, I have not had any thing or act come to my mind with leſſe regret, and greater comfort then this.</p>
               <p>And as for thoſe that brought me hither, I do forgive them, I have not one hard thought concerning them, the bleſſing of the Father Son and Spirit be with them.</p>
               <p>Oh that the Lord would grant that no more might ſuffer; and ſo Dear and Bleſſed Father I come into the boſome of thy love, and deſire (to enter into that Glory which is Endleſſe and Boundleſſe) through Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Letter written from the <hi>Tower</hi> to a Chriſtian friend, by Mr. Juſtice <hi>Cooke.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>NOw in anſwer to your loving inquiry how it fares with my better part, I bleſſe God I never found ſo much internall ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſolice, and unmixt joy and comfort, as <hi>I</hi> have experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in theſe five moneths indurance, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.3, 4, 5. Let never any Chriſtian fear a priſon, it being the onely place where (wanting other books) a man may beſt ſtuddy the book of the knowledge of himſelfe, having a long vacation from all buſineſs; but praying unto, and praiſing God in Chriſt, by the ſpirits aſſiſtance. I cannot take <hi>Marthas</hi> part, for none muſt come to me; nor <hi>Marys</hi> part to wait upon the ordinances, which my ſoul thirſts after; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my chamber is like the <hi>ſanctum ſanctorum,</hi> where wittingly none may enter but the high Prieſt of our profeſſion the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. <hi>I</hi> did not think that there had been ſo much ignorance, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potence, impatience, ingratitude, pride, inordinate affection to creature comforts, revenge, diffidence of God, ſelf-love, and ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of all ſorts in me, as I finde there is; who am not onely a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115260:22"/>
poor ſinner, but ſin it ſelfe, a very maſſe of ſin. I find it very hard to rely nakedly on Gods goodneſs, not to feel the heat of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, nor to be carefull when all is taken away. <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.17 <hi>Lo,</hi> ſo this darkneſs and filthineſs of ſpirit is onely diſcovered by the light of Chriſt, by whoſe lowlineſs in waſhing the Apoſtles feet, I ſee my loftineſs and want of condeſcention when I had power; by his patience my many paſſions and heart-riſings againſt inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; by his obedience to the death, my reluctancies; by his faithfulneſs my former backſlidings; by his fruitfulneſs, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.38. my barrenneſs &amp; the little good I did when I had opportunity; and by his liberality, my penuriouſneſs; whereby I adore and acknowledge his juſtice that he hath moſt righteouſly deprived me of my liberty &amp; eſtate: all which drives me neerer to Chriſt, and makes me take faſter hold of his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs. I now underſtand (through grace) how precious he is; 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7. if it were not for Chriſt what a miſerable condition were I now in? that might ſuddenly be ſent to contend with the wrath of God in everlaſting burnings; and this makes me love Chriſt the more, having forgiven me more then others: and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had ten thouſand talents forgiven me, I would forgive any wrong doers; and this keeps me humble and from cenſoriouſneſs. I bleſs God I have ranſackt into every corner of my ſoule, I have with <hi>David, Job, Eſay,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> bewailed my hereditary diſeaſe and heart-corruption. I feel it is as a rotten tooth that akes, would fain be rid of it, have condemned my ſelfe for it, cried out aginſt it, as the raviſhed damſel, <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.26. The like for ſins done in my inclination, which by preventing grace are ſecret and onely known to God; and I haue mourned over my ſecret ſinnes, onely known to God and my ſelfe; over the ſinnes of my youth, which were committed faſter then can be named; for thoſe which <hi>I</hi> did not know to be ſin, and thoſe that <hi>I</hi> have forgotten? and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for my actually known ſins committed againſt love and light, promiſes and covenants. I have confeſt them all with a heavy bleeding broken and contrite ſpirit, and O that I had all ſin, as ſin, in a greater execration; my griefe is for having offended ſo gracious a father<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that wil not damn me for it; if there were no hell nor judge I would rather dye then willingly offend him any more, and I cannot ſatisfie divine juſtice for one vain thought<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:115260:23"/>
therefore I flie to Chriſt, and cloſe with him upon a free promiſe as a poor penitent ſinner; no merits but the merits of my Saviour; I take in whole Chriſt, and not one drop of my pudled water ſhall be mingled with the ocean of his pure and perfect righteouſneſs; &amp; I give up my ſelf wholly to him, as by a deed of gift, to be at his diſpoſe; and I know he hath received me, <hi>I am my beloveds, and my beloved is mine,</hi> and all is mine, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22. death it ſelfe; I have a ſweet certificate from Heaven of the pardon of ſin, juſtification, reconciliation, and adoption. I know Gods heart and his eyes are upon me perpetually, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 2.15. that no tender father or mother can have ſo ſpecial a care of any ſick impriſoned child, as he hath of me. I believe that God who hath given a property to the needle to keep fixt though the ſhip overturn, wil keep me faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the death, and that I ſhal receive the crown of life, and ſtand with as much confidence at the great day, as if: had never ſinned; and herein I am confirmed by the teſtimony of the ſpirt, and Scripture evidences.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed be God I doe love the Saints, every one that ſuffers in this cauſe is at deare to me as my own ſoule, my ſighs have been many, and my heart faint, ſince I came hither, not for my own condition (for it is happy) but for the afflictions of <hi>Joſeph;</hi> ſcarce a poor Saint permitted to breathe in Iriſh ayre; thoſe that wil not ſweare and be drunke, or have prayer in their families, are counted Fanaticks. <hi>Eſay</hi> 50.15. I have a dear reſpect to all Gods commandements, ſpiritual joy is no ſtranger to me; I love the Word and Ordinances more then my appointed food. I deſire that all my thoughts, words, and actions may pleaſe God; and that all that he does may pleaſe me; and I doe freely forgive my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, the Lord herein encreaſe my faith, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.5. and I bleſs God I have a quiet conſcience as to the world, and which is good alſo for being juſtified by Chriſt, apprehended by faith, I have peace with God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1. and ſo I deſcend to the cauſe for which I am in bonds, which is as good as ever it was; and I believe there is not a Saint that hath engaged with us, but wil wiſh at the laſt day that he had ſealed to the truth of it with his blood, if thereunto called: for I am ſatisfied that it is the moſt noble and glorious cauſe that has been agitated for God and Chriſt ſince the Apoſtolical times; being for truth, holineſs, and righteouſneſs,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115260:23"/>
for our liberties as men and as Chriſtians, for removing of all yokes and oppreſſions, for a goſpel Magiſtracy and Miniſtery and not onely for the Prieſtly and Prophetical offices of Chriſt Jeſus, but for his Kingly alſo: the peculiar light and worke of this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration being to diſcover and oppoſe the Civil and Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal tyrannies intended upon the Nations, by the Popes <hi>Leger de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main,</hi> to exalt Chriſt as Lord and King over mens conſciences, to magnifie and make the law of God honourable, and authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique every where, and to give juſtice and mercy the upper hand. As I hear nothing what they intend to doe with me, ſo I am not much ſollicitous about it; I doe freely truſt God to make what bargain for me he pleaſes. I believe they are as angry with me as any man in the nations, becauſe <hi>litera ſcripta manet,</hi> but their cauſe requires rather ſilence then eloquence; as for that againſt Monarchy unaccountable they will be aſhamed to oppoſe it, that which nettles them, is the ſtating the Caſe for which I had Vou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and Warrants for every word, but now they plow with our Heffer; yet great is the truth and that will prevail, as for Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning there is not any. I cannot confeſſe any guilt, it is ſuch a Cauſe that the Martyrs would gladly come again from Heaven to ſuffer for, if they might, though too many object againſt me, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.15. <hi>Let none of you ſuffer as a Murtherer:</hi> I look upon it as the moſt noble and high Act of juſtice that our Story can parallel; and ſo far as I had a hand in it, never any one action in all my life comes to my mind with leſſe regret, or trouble of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, then that does; for the bloud muſt lie upon Him, or the Parliament; and I am ſure I had no more malice in my heart, then when I was in my Cradle: all that I can be ſorry for, is, that I had not ſuch pure, and unbyaſt Aims, at the glory of God &amp; exaltation of Chriſt therin, as I ſhould have had; I neither ſaid nor did any thing <hi>dubitante,</hi> or <hi>reluctante conſcientiae</hi> I was ſo far from a rainſaying conſcience in any thing I acted, that I never ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled in the leaſt, and the generality of the people have ſince owned it: <hi>I</hi> was in mercy a poor Advocate for Chriſt, and the people of <hi>England,</hi> and if by my bloud their cauſe may be watered, I ſay (as <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.17, 18.) to you and the reſt of the Church of Chriſt, if I be offered upon the ſacrifice and ſervice of your faith, let us rejoyce together: it has been counted ſhamefull for Souldiers to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115260:24"/>
run from their Colours, or deſert their Maſters, and Principles, but it is more odidus for a Councellor to prevaricate and betray his Clients Cauſe: I am perſwaded that all thoſe that have had a chief hand and are now giving Judgement againſt themſelves, and all good people, in all thoſe points which they formerly conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for, againſt the King; as the lawfulneſſe of the War, which was granted both here and at <hi>Edenburgh.</hi> The Militia, Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Voyce, power to diſſolve Parliaments, conferring great Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (as King <hi>James</hi> ſaid, <hi>ſo long as I make Biſhops and Judges, I will have what Religion and Laws I pleaſe</hi>) As they are moſt abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable prevaricators of the honeſt intereſt, for they will wiſh at the laſt day, that they had been <hi>Jewes, Turks</hi> or <hi>Indians</hi> for the greater light, the greater is their Apoſtacy and ingratitude, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. and ſure they will have a peculiar Judgement by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; for they do openly proclame the cauſe of <hi>Barrabas</hi> before the cauſe of Jeſus. <hi>Peter</hi> denyed Chriſt, and <hi>Judas</hi> betrayed him, but it was before his paſſion and Aſſention, they never ſaw the wonderful works which our Eyes have beheld; but what ſhall we ſay, if the treachery of <hi>Judas</hi> help forward the work of our ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, why may we not hope, that God is whetting his Tooles, and gone back to fetch a greater blow againſt his oppreſſors, <hi>Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ac</hi> muſt not dye though the Knife be at his Throat, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.14. our caſe ſeems to be like theirs, under proud <hi>Homan</hi> the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows was erected, but the Royal ſeed preſerved. <hi>Heſt.</hi> 6.13. <hi>Numb.</hi> 23. the ſtory of <hi>Baalam</hi> is much upon my heart, the ſhout of King Jeſus to Reign in Holineſſe and Righteouſneſſe is among his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, I hope as much as ever; and there is no inchantment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Jacob</hi> therefore he muſt not be afraid; I am perſwaded we ſhall fare the better for the thouſand curſes we had between <hi>Cheſter</hi> and <hi>London,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.12.</p>
               <p>Now having endeavored to ſatisfie you that the great work is over as to my eternal ſalvation, and my opinion of the goodneſs of our Cauſe; I ſhall further entreat your patience to tell you that I am fully convinced, that next to that unſpeakable gift of Chriſt, the greateſt grace and mercy that God can beſtow upon any of us, is to call for and enable us to lay down our lives upon this account; ſuffering for Chriſt being a ſtrong Argument of his Electing love, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.15, 16. and a greater matter of rejoycing,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115260:24"/>
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 23.11. be of good cheer <hi>Paul;</hi> therefore he forbids tears for him upon that ſcore, <hi>Acts.</hi> 21.13. and I have charged my poor lamb not to wear any black for me (if ſhe have where with to buy it;) for I ſhall be in <hi>white, Revel.</hi> 6.11. the Apoſtle rejoyced to be counted worthy to ſuffer ſhame for Chriſt, and would not but ſpeak what they ſaw with the eyes of Faith, and heard with the ears of the Spirit, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.20. and the 5.41. and <hi>Paul</hi> gloried in the tribulation, rejoycing in hope of the glory of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5, 23. and took pleaſure in reproaches, neceſſity and perſecutions for Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.10. ſo <hi>Moſes, Heb.</hi> 11.26. for the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of reward which is God himſelf, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.1. and the times cannot be ſo full of terrour and diſcouragement as the Scriptures are full of comfort and incitations in this particular, to us the Lords priſoners, <hi>Mat</hi> 5.10.12. why are we ſorrowful when Chriſt bids us to be joyful, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.25.27. there is no ſafety but to be on Chriſts ſide, for the Son of man ſhall come in his glory and the Saints alſo, <hi>Mark</hi> 8.33, 38. they are not the words of a Child, but of Chriſt, not ſpoken to affright us, but for our animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; Oh this perfidious Generation! how will that word be made good to the Amazemeat of our Timerous profeſſors, <hi>John</hi> 16.21. The Axe or a Halter will be leſſe pain then the pangs of Child-birth, <hi>John</hi> 15.18, 21. we are in nothing to be terrifyed, 1 <hi>Phil.</hi> 28.29. conſtancy in ſuffering for good principles is matter of glory in the Churches, and Tribulation will be the portion of our troublers, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.4. to the end is very pretious, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.8. we live if yee ſtand faſt in the Lord: I know you, and my dear Brethren and Siſters are of <hi>Pauls</hi> mind, if I dye in my bed being a Church member, you will by the rule of Charity judge me hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py; I cannot doe you more ſervice then to bear my witneſſe in this Cauſe of Chriſt wherein you are ſo much concerned, I finde our Text appropriate to our Condition, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.23. to 27. Chriſts death was like ſowing of Corne, which ſeemed loſt, but was our life; ſo he that counts not his life dear for Chriſt, though the world count him miſerable, yet he hath two ſpecial promiſes to be where Chriſt is, and that the Father will honour him, it is a following of Chriſt in Dying for him, Actively or in Affection as appears, <hi>John</hi> 13.36, 21, 19. by a conformity to his death, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.3. ſome read which dyed for the Lord, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115260:25"/>
and 19.10. which now is counted as bad as Treaſon, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. has an ineffable ſweetneſſe in it, <hi>Ch.</hi> 11. is the little book of Martyrs, 12.1. the ſpirit ſayes follow your leaders, he is a Coward that will not follow ſuch free Examples; Chriſt and the Saints behold you and yee are witneſſes for Chriſt as they were, but muſt forſake all ſin, eſpecially your <hi>Dallilaes, Herodias</hi> and <hi>Rimmons,</hi> and ſtrive againſt it; and ye have need of patience, but ye will faint and be weary unleſſe yea look unto Jeſus and fear not, for he is as well the finiſher of your Faith as the Father of it, he deſpiſed the ſhame, what need you care if they ſay behold the Head, or the heart of a traytor, when your better part is in heaven, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves us for being too parſimonious of our blood; we muſt be prepared for ſuffering <hi>eruore ſanctorum rigatur Eccleſiae. Luther</hi> was troubled that he carried his blood to his grave, he loved the Chriſts croſſe more then the 24 Letters, and loved not half Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that were onely for doing &amp; not for ſuffering; and though our ſinne deſerve death as from the Lord, yet our enemies mind them not, they puniſh us for being judges, advocates, and ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for our Lord Jeſus, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.20.</p>
               <p>And as the ſpiritual man overcomes the Animal, ſo I am rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning my ſelf againſt ſence into a willingneſs to dye, for either the times will be better or worſe; is there not in probability a great floud of Oppreſſion and Perſecution, coming upon the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; will not the righteous ſoule of a juſt <hi>Lot,</hi> be vexed with the horrible prophaneneſſe, malignity, and contempt of Chriſts pure Ordinances that abounds every where; we have heard Juſtice and Tyranny, Truth and Falſehood, the forme and the power of Godlineſſe pleading together, and Judgement was given for God, and his people, but all ſeems to be reverſed, and what was but an <hi>injurie</hi> or <hi>neſciente</hi> before, is now a formal and material con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, and deſpight to God and Chriſt, and the ſpirit of grace in whom ſoever breathing; and what, comfort is there in a ſon, if the Ark be taken, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.20, 21. ſhe regarded it not, the bleſſing is to ſee our children with peace upon <hi>Iſrael, Pſal.</hi> 128.5, 6. it is a mercy to be taken away from the evil to come, <hi>Eſay</hi> 57.1. beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon <hi>Joſiah</hi> as a favour, being tender hearted, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 23.19. tis a rich mercy to get into our heavenly houſe, and harbour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſtorm come, 2 <hi>Cor,</hi> 5. how much more bleſſed to give our
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115260:25"/>
polluted blood for his ſake who ſhed his moſt precious blood for us; and if the times prove good, for civil or ſacred liberties; <hi>Moſes</hi> envied not thoſe that were to goe into <hi>Canaan,</hi> becauſe he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted with a better poſſeſſion, a heavenly Countrey, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.16. if there be ſuch glorious times to be expected upon earth as you and I have diſcourſed of, I am ſure there is no leſs joy in heaven; and we that are there ſhal have no cauſe to envy our millitant brethren; beſides, as for my ſelf I can expect to doe little for God, I am three parts dead, 70 being divided into four, the ſhadows of the evening are upon me, and aches and paines are inſeparable companions, if now Chriſt ſhould graciouſly accept of my poore crazy body, &amp; bring me to an honourable and an eaſie death for him, bleſſed be his name forever, 1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 29.10. <hi>to</hi> 16. The heathen could ſay, <hi>Dulce eſt pro patria mori, pro Chriſto mori dulcimum.</hi> How did the Romans glory to die for their liberties, and after for the glory of their <hi>Ceſars?</hi> and how glad are the poor Spaniards and Muſcovites that they have a life, a wiſe, or a ſonne, for their King: and how glad are the City that their feaſtings will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, A Popiſh Friar told me lately, that if he were of my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion for aſſurance of ſalvation, he would not willingly live an houre longer for all <hi>Ireland;</hi> yet Saints too much feare this grim porter death, though when executed we goe from the croſſe to the Crown, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.12. indeed it is below the profeſſion that we have made, to be now troubled; in proſperity I would be a worm, but now the Lord makes us bold as Lyons, that being called to ſuffer after ſo bleſſed an example, we may think it an honour to pledge our maſter in his own cup, and commit the keeping of our ſoules to him in wel doing as unto a faithful creator, 1 <hi>Pet,</hi> 2.21. and 4.19. for he wil never leave nor forſake us, but wil give us ſhoulders to bear what he laies upon us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. let us therefore who are the children of <hi>Zion</hi> be joyful in our King, as others (who one day wil appeare to be fanatiques indeed) rejoyce in them, for theſe preſent ſufferings are not worthy to be compared with our future glory, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18.</p>
               <p>Sir, I bleſs God I have an invincible peace and a ſecret joy ſurpaſſing my expreſſion; <hi>and I preſs towards the marke, Phil.</hi> 3.14 yet divine cordials are not conſtant, but often ſome fainting fits, and diſpondencies; the ſpirit bloweth where it liſteth; where it is
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:115260:26"/>
not comforting it is ſupporting, <hi>Eſay</hi> 40.29, &amp; 41.10. if I were not very feeble, how could Gods power appear in my weakneſs. I bleſs his name that his arrows are not within me, nor doe the terrors of death take hold upon me, as <hi>Job</hi> 6.4. for I never was better as to the frame and temper of mind, and body, then ſince my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint; and bleſſed be the comforter I am not long without him. My couſin <hi>Harriſon</hi> is very full of ſpiritual comfort (as the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman Jaylor tels me) and bids me cheere up, and indeed it wil be a mercy if thoſe who are called forth to teſtifie for Chriſt prove couragious, as <hi>Joſ.</hi> 1.9. but truly as for my part, in does not lie on that ſide, I fear leaſt <hi>I</hi> may be too much exalted with the honour of it though <hi>I</hi> know the Lord can ſoon withdraw; we live by faith and not by ſight, our happineſs is in our union rather then in communion and ſenſible guſts; and <hi>I</hi> rather fear a lingring death with ſeverity, ſome for baniſhment, <hi>Ezek,</hi> 7.16 &amp;c. but let the Lord doe with me as he pleaſeth, as <hi>Joab</hi> ſiad, 1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 19.13. <hi>Omnia co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>operatur in bonam, Rom.</hi> 8.28. So having unboſomed my heart unto you, that you and ſuch whom you judge faithful and ſecret may the better ſpread my condition before the Lord, <hi>I</hi> would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat you to beg for me more particularly, 1. That God would ſet home upon my heart, and fulfil in me with power your ſweet Scripture (for which <hi>I</hi> heartily thank you) 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.7, 8, 9, 12. that <hi>I</hi> may not be afraid of their terrors, nor troubled but may ſanctifie the Lord at that time, and be able to anſwer all oppoſers, that they may be aſhamed when we ſuffer for wel doing, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.14. to 18. 2. That <hi>I</hi> and the reſt of our brethren and companions in tribulation, and in the kingdom and patience of Jeſus Chriſt, for the word of God and his teſtimony may be ſtrengthned with all might according to Chriſts glorious power, unto all patience and long ſuffering with joyfulneſs, as <hi>Paul</hi> prayed for the Colloſſians, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.9, <hi>to</hi> 14. being filled with knowledge, wiſdome, and ſpiritual underſtanding and feeling thoſe grounds of joy as an inheritance of light, and deliverance from the power of darkneſs: that we may be <hi>teſtes</hi> and <hi>conteſtes</hi> to agree in our teſtimonies, and not diſparage ſo good a cauſe. 3. That we may be ready (not onely to be bound but to die for Chriſt, and the vindication and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of his Evangelical doctrine; we have made high profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and confeſſion of the everlaſting Goſpel, and it is a bleſſed
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115260:26"/>
thing to believe with the heart, and confeſs with our mouths, and in our lives and by active martyrdom, as <hi>Brooke, Ireton, Hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, Pickering,</hi> and others have worthily done, who are ſafely ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived expecting us, and we are yet upon the waves; but the moſt excellent, honourable, rich and fruitful confeſſion of Chriſt, whereby we can make the moſt efficacious demonſtration of our election and faith in Chriſt, and love in his glorious perſon with moſt ſupream illuſtration of Gods glory is to lay down our lives as the martyrs did to ſeal and confirm the truth of our profeſſions with our blood, for the cauſe of Chriſt, and ſafety of our brethren, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.4. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.16. as our bleſſed maſter, after he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed and preached the glory of God, and our ſalvation, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and approved all by miracles, and his moſt holy life made a good confeſſion, under <hi>Pontius pilat,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.13. without which all had been ineffectual: So I have often thought for the diſcovery of hypocrites, cementing of the Saints in more concording affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, trial of faith, exerciſing of patience, and love to Chriſt, and for many other glorious ends God would call for ſome of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens blood, which wil be the greater favour to them whom he ſhal count worthy of it, becauſe I think this wil rather be a <hi>Julian</hi> then a <hi>Heronian</hi> perſecution, alwaies provided that we be found in the doctrine of the covenant of grace, that God does not love us becauſe we live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent world, and are willing to forſake all, and looſe our lives for him.</p>
               <p>But becauſe he loves us, and has ſingled us out from the world, therefore he enables us ſo to live, and to doe ſingular things for his honour and glory, and willingly to <hi>follow the Lamb whither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he goeth, Revel.</hi> 14.4. <hi>for the love of Chriſt conſtraineth us,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. O that we had more enlarged hearts for our King Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. 4. (That you may fully hit my condition) I have ſome trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble upon me concerning the loſſe of my temporal eſtate, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for my poor, tender loving wife and child: I was a purchaſer, and had a ſtock of cattel, &amp; being wrongfully made priſoner two moneths before any ſpeech of a King I was ſurprized and could ſave nothing nor get 20 <hi>l</hi> of my eſtate ſince Michaelmas laſt They promiſed to beare my charges to <hi>London,</hi> but at <hi>Cheſter</hi> I was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to borrow money, or muſt have come a foot: therefore pray
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:115260:27"/>
be earneſt with the Lord, that we may take the ſpoyling of our goods more joyfully, knowing that we have in heaven better and an enduring ſubſtance, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10 34. and that we may not faint at theſe momentany afflictions, which work ſo wel for us (wherein riches and honours are not ſo) according to that paſſage, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4 3 laſt verſes, and be affected with eternal joyes. It is ſaid that I ſhall be put down into the hole for non-payment of great Fees: my comfort is that God will be with me, there they cannot ſhut out Gods ſpirit from me, which is an everlaſting ſpring and Jubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le; nor will that be ſo bad as <hi>Jeremiah's</hi> Dungeon, nor as <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph's</hi> Irons which entered into his ſoule, though indeed we are ſold by our brethren as <hi>Joſeph</hi> was, that the ſcripture may be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, <hi>The brother ſhall deliver up the brother to Death, Matthew</hi> 10.21.</p>
               <p>I know not how to conclude, not knowing when I may have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother opportunity to converſe with you, I am overjoyed to think they cannot reach my ſoule, and that our cauſe is invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and it will be a happineſſe if God ſee it good that none might ſuffer death, but ſuch whoſe ſouls are out of danger; but being upon the account of civil liberties as well as ſpiritual, our onely wiſe Father will order all for his own Glory, and this onely ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences all murmurings, and maſter ſave thy ſelfe, that what he pleaſes muſt needs be leaſt for us; he being Infinite, Wiſdome, Love, Power and Goodneſſe. Had the King made his way by the Sword, we might expect his ſoreſt ſtrokes; but for the men of <hi>Keilah</hi> to deliver us up for the Parliament to ſacrifice us, theſe men that ſit by a Commonwealth Writ, for whoſe priviledges we adventured our all, and who cannot condemne us but muſt give up the Cauſe, and give Judgement againſt themſelves, and all the good people in the Nation; let the <hi>Indians</hi> judge of it, if any of the Elect think hardly of us, that we do not cry <hi>peccavi,</hi> &amp; make our recantations, it will not laſt long, and it is no matter what others ſay, for they muſt receive their Judgement at the Bar of Chriſt, and we ſhall Judge our Judges; therefore let us not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine damps of diſpondencies. My rejoycing is in a good God, a good Cauſe, a good Conſcience, I have the Juſtice of Heaven on my ſide, and Gods loving kindneſſe which is better then life, if we find injuſtice and cruelty here, mens Law at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> will
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:115260:27"/>
be adjudged Treaſon in Heaven, it will not be long before all tears ſhall be wiped from our Eyes, and if our innocencies be not vindicated, and cleared up in this life, as <hi>Jobs Mordecas, Joſephs,</hi> and <hi>Daniels</hi> and <hi>Suſannas</hi> were yet at the revelation of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous judgement of God, it will appeare before men and Angels, that we are not Traytors, nor Murtherers, nor Phanatiques, but true Chriſtians, and good Commonwealths men, fixt and conſtant to the principles of ſanctity, truth, juſtice, and mercy, which the Parliament and Army declared and engaged for; and to that Noble principle of preferring the Univerſality, before Particula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that we ſought the publique good, and would have infran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſed the people, and ſecured the welfare of the whole groaning Creation, if the Nation had not more delighted in ſervitude, then in freedom. And if we now ſuffer a martyrdom of body, we ſhal be ſome of the ſouls under the Altar crying, <hi>How long O Lord holy &amp; true,</hi> and though we can patiently digeſt their Tortures, and leave all vengance to whom it belongs, yet who knows but that our blood may be their poyſon; but then after all unjuſt ſentences of men how ſweet and honourable will the Judgement of Chriſt be, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. <hi>(Euge bone ſerve)</hi> of entring into our maſter joy, when the Kings of the Earth and the chief Captaines and Dukes of <hi>Edom</hi> ſhall wiſh the Mountaines and Rocks to fall upon them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.16. I bleſſe God my poor Wife <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> much encourage me, to be faithful to the Death, and ſhe is a <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> who helps her Husband ſo to Heaven, as in a Fiery Charoit; ſhe is one who bears an unfeigned love to Chriſt and all the Saints; I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat your tender care of her and my Child, <hi>providebit Deus, Ier.</hi> 49.11. I ſhal leave her that Scripture and <hi>Eſa.</hi> 54.5. to 8. while they cannot take away by confiscation; when we were in the ſtorm we took our leaves each of the other, <note n="*" place="margin">See the relation of his paſſage by ſea from Wexſo<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d to King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſale.</note> and though we have not paid our Vowes at <hi>Pethell,</hi> yet I truſt (as was then promiſed) we ſhal be willing to go to Chriſt if he call through a Sea of bloud. But O the infinite wiſdome and love of God, and the unſearcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble riches of his Grace, that if I had been drowned the Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants would have ſaid, though he eſcaped by Land, yet Divine Vengance over took him at <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ow he ſhould vouchſafe me (poor me as <hi>Gideon</hi> ſaid, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 15. one of the meaneſt Lawyers in <hi>Weſminſter-Hall</hi>) <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of bonds and an affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:115260:28"/>
if not effectual Martyrdome for being an Advocate for my bleſſed Advocate and the good people of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have been the larger not knowing what uſe this may be of, if my mouth ſhould be ſtop't; if you hear any report of me contrary hereunto, believe it not, ſo you have my heart; and I had rather be buried alive, then my Tongue or Hand ſhould differ from it. O pray much for me, and pray again and mend your prayer, as I have great need to doe, if you know what pittiful poor ſhort and confuſed prayers I make in a day; yet Father into thy hands I commend my ſpirit is a prayer, no period better then prayer, therefore now unto him that is able to keep you (and me) from falling, and to preſent you (and me faultleſſe before the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his glory with exceeding joy: To the only wiſe God our Saviour be Glory and Majeſty, Dominion and Power now and for Ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your for ever in our Dear Redeemer,</hi> John Cooke.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Letter written by Mr. Juſtice <hi>Cooke</hi> from the <hi>Tower</hi> to his Wife.</head>
               <p>MY deare lamb, bleſſed be God for Jeſus Chriſt, and for a priſon, where I finde much of his comforting preſence; tell ſiſter <hi>Jones</hi> that ſhe keeps but two or three Sabbaths in a weeke, but in priſon every day is a Chriſtian Sabbath; not onely to ceaſe from ſinne, but to praiſe God, ſinging Hoſannaes and Hallalujahs. I can but ſmile to think that they cannot hinder me from preaching, for <hi>I</hi> preach twice every day to my ſelfe, and yeſterday, bleſſed be the Comforter, my heart was brimfull of joy and conſolation from Pſal. <hi>73.25, 26.</hi> wherein I obſerved three points, or doctrinall concluſions.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1. That a Saint ſhould love and eſteem nothing but God, and for God;</hi> all diſcourſe is vain but what aims and tends to Gods glory <hi>1 Cor. 10.31.</hi> a husband, wife, child, friends, and all creature com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts are to be loved ſo far as we ſee God in them; as the creatures doe not ſerve us but God ſuſteines us in them, and by them, ſo our affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and deſires muſt not be fixed upon them, but terminate in God; as the waters in the river never reſt till they return to the Sea, ſo our
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:115260:28"/>
loves muſt onely paſſe by the creatures, and ſettle in God; and the more wel ſee the image of God in any one, there our love is to be moſt in the Lord, and for his ſake this love is the greateſt weight of our ſoules, and transforms into the nature of the thing beloved, let us endeavour to put out more acts of love to God in Chriſt, <hi>Cant. 1.16.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> From thoſe words, <hi>my fleſh and my heart faileth me, but God is the ſtrength of my heart,</hi> the chiefe reſidence of the ſoul being in the heart, <hi>I</hi> obſerve, <hi>That there is ſomething more dear to a Saint then his own ſoule, which is the ſoule of his ſoule, and the life of his life, and that is Jeſus Chriſt, who dwelleth in our ſoules by his ſpirit,</hi> Rom. <hi>8 10, 11.</hi> for as the body is dead when the ſoul leaves it, ſo the ſoule is dead without Chriſt; which may teach us two leſſons. <hi>1.</hi> To love Chriſt more then our own lives or relations, becauſe he is the ſoul of our ſoules; this did <hi>Moſes,</hi> Exod. <hi>32.32.</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. <hi>9.3.</hi> they preferred the glory of God in the ſalvation of their brethren before their own ſoules, if it could have been, which is a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian duty, though very hard; and if divine juſtice ſhould ſay to us at the great day, <hi>the ſoul that ſins muſt die:</hi> we may ſay, why then did God puniſh our Lord Jeſus who is the ſoule of our ſoules, more dear to us then our ſouls; and if God had ſeen it good we had rather have ſuffered in our own perſons to have ſaved him; but we not being able to undergoe the wrath of God, that innocent and immaculate lambe was put to death, who is the heart of our hearts, the ſoule of our ſoules, and the ſpirit of our ſpirits; for juſtice is more then abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſatisfied, much more then if our wils, ſoules, and bodies had ſuffered, and the debt was all paid together which had alwaies been paying if we had gone to hell, for as to Chriſt our ſalvation is all pure ſtrict juſtice, who felt nothing but extremity, the father would not ſpare him, <hi>Rom. 8.32.</hi> but as to us it is all mercy that his ſatisfaction ſhould be accepted for us, and that thee and me, and deare Da<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>; and ſweet love I truſt ſhould be veſſels of that mercy and free grace, O bleſſed be his glorious name for ever.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> My meditations were principally carried out from the joyes of heaven and from thoſe words, <hi>Whom have I in heaven but thee? and thou art my portion forever,</hi> I was raviſhed with this conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, <hi>that the joyes of Heaven are eternal:</hi> or thus, <hi>The Saints pleaſures have a beginning, but no ending.</hi> No doubt but this is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:115260:29"/>
matter of joy to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and all the Saints in heaven, to think that they ſhall continue in their joy and glory, not <hi>100.</hi> or <hi>10000</hi> millions of years onely, but for ever, that when they have been there <hi>100000</hi> millions of millions of years, as to what remaines it wil not be a minuit, but then we begin our felicity, therfore Chriſt cals it <hi>a life eternal,</hi> Matth. <hi>25</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Therefore if a man could live here <hi>1000000</hi> millions of years and enjoy his hearts deſire, and all the variety of pleaſures which <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> world can afford, and afterwards be deprived of Paradiſe, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> damned, what a ſad bargain would that be; for the S<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>its <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> that while in heaven, and ſhall be there for ever: and <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> might <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> its <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ounger and live here for ever if ſuch a <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> poſſibl<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> not that content him, becauſe he is capa<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of go<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the choice of an illuminate Chriſti<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> whether to <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>000</hi> years in health, wealth, and all the <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to be in heaven but one day, he ought to chooſe the lat<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>40.</hi> ſo one minuits being in heaven is to be preferred before a perpetuity of all worldly pleaſures, for to be abſent from the Lord is more grievous then all humane de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights can be comfortable, if it were but a pretty good condition, if men were ſure alwaies ſo to continue it would be comfortable: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to think of an everlaſting crown of Glory, is a ſoul-melting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration. If then this life be not a minuit in compariſon of the perpetual life of the bleſſed ſoules in heaven; how greatly are they to be blamed that for a little vain honour flattering pleaſure or the momentany ſinfull delights of this evil world, ſquander away their precious ſoules, <hi>2</hi> As the joyes of Heaven are eternal, ſo they are exceeding great: If the men of the world which have their portion here, <hi>Pſa. 17.14.</hi> have ſuch ſtately horſes and pleaſant palaces and delights, ſhall we not think that God hath provided ineſtimable trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and pleaſures in the world to come for his children<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for whom doe earthly parents treaſure up, but for their children; but if we could hut apprehend what they are, they are not the joyes of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, for <hi>no heart can conceive what God has prepared for them that love him, 1 Cor. 29.</hi> the eye hath ſeen much, and the eare heard more, and the heart may conceive much more, but eternal pleaſures are inconceivable, yet the ſpiritual eye hath ſome glamps of it: a poor Saint findes more ſolid and zeal joy in a crucified Chriſt, poore and naked and deſpiſed in the world, then all the Dukes of Edome in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:115260:29"/>
their rich and glorious pomp and magnificence; but all the Saints living here have not ſo much joy and ſplendour as the leaſt Saint hath in heaven. The Scripture mentions three heavens, <hi>where the Fowles are, the ſtarry Heaven, and the Heaven of heavens, 1</hi> Kings <hi>8.27.</hi> the ſun is conceived to be <hi>300</hi> times bigger then the Earth, and every ſtarre bigger then this lower world, and that all the earth it but as mote and not ſo big as a flee in compariſon of the Emperiall coeleſtiall Heavens where the ſouls of the Saints are with God and Chriſt; and by the largeneſs of the place we may gueſs at the greatneſs of the joys &amp; pleaſures, that the Elect are but few in compariſon of thoſe who ſhal be turned into hell, <hi>Pſa. 9.17.</hi> as it were thruſt into a hole together, <hi>Matth. 25.23.</hi> our Lords joy can be no little joy, and it is too big to enter into us, we muſt enter into it. Next I conſider wherein the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and eſſence of heavenly joyes does properly conſiſt by <hi>1 Cor. 13.12.</hi> it ſeems much to be in ſight and knowledge.</p>
               <p n="1">1 For ſight to ſee God face to face, to ſee the beautifull perſon of our deare Lord Jeſus, to ſee all the bleſſed ſaints and Angels, and to be one of them, how joyfull is the thought of it; for if the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (between whom and the ſaints there is a great gulph fixed, <hi>Luk. 16.26.</hi>) ſhall ſee <hi>Abraham and the prophets in the Kingdome of God,</hi> Luke <hi>13.28.</hi> when themſelves are thruſt out (poor ſaint-haters that now perſecute the heirs of glory, &amp; ſcorn their companies would then fein crowd into heaven with them) much more the Elect them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; but the difficulty is, how we can ſee ſpirits with bodily eyes, and bodies with ſpiritual eyes. <hi>I</hi> rather think that <hi>Job 19.25, 27.</hi> is to be underſtood of Jeſus Chriſt, whom <hi>Job</hi> ſhall ſee with the Eyes of his hody, and by the Eyes of our ſoules we ſhall ſee God the Father and the bleſſed ſpirits; and our comfort is that we ſhall for ever be with the Lord. But here the Scripture has no Tongue to ſpeak, we muſt not too curiouſly inquire for knowledge, it is a wonderful ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, we ſhall know even as we are known, God knows us perfectly and what ſhall be our laſt thoughts, <hi>Pſal. 139.1, 2.</hi> All the ſaints up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth do not know ſo much as one ſaint in Heaven, where faith is turned into Viſion, and hope into Fruition; then ſhall we know the love of Chriſt which paſſeth all knowledge here below, <hi>Eph. 3.19.</hi> how all the love that ever God vouchſafed to the world, is but as a ſpark to the Oven red hot in compariſon of giving Chriſt; but I believe we ſhal never know God comprehenſively [but apprehenſively] that is ſo much
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:115260:30"/>
of his glory as we ſhall never know more, for there will he new ſprings and freſh diſcoveries of his infinite Grace, Glory, Goodneſſe and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections ſtreaming forth continually to us, that will be as everlaſting fountaines of joy and glorious rejoycing to our ſoules and bodies; as one at ſea ſees a great way but not to the end or bottome of the ſea, for we ſhall know as much of God as our heads can hold, and love God as much as our hearts can containe; and no doubt but there are different degrees of Glory in Heaven, as the Saints know more or leſs of God, here as when Veſſels of ſeveral ſizes are caſt into the ſea, they are all full, but ſome hold more then others, <hi>2 Cor. 5.4</hi> God works upon our Hearts as ingravers upon Gold or Marble, and the more of his image he ſtamps upon us in this life, the liker ſhall we be to him in Glory, but every ſaint ſhall have his own fulneſſe of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> I think that heavenly joy does much conſiſt in the will, in the transformation of our wills into the will of God; for as we heard an excellent ſermon from <hi>1 Cor. 6.17.</hi> at <hi>Northampton,</hi> he that is joyned unto the Lord is one ſpirit; for I believe that miſtical oneneſſe which our dear Lord ſo ſweetly prayed for, <hi>Joh. 17.11, 21, 22.</hi> is meant of oneneſſe in will and affections, when the ſoul ſhall have all that it can deſire and nothing but what it does deſire, and ſhall will nothing but what God wills, and not onely to be ſatisfyed with the wil of God, but but to taſte a ſweet complecency and delight in it, that it is infinitely beſt to be there.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4.</hi> This transforming of the will proceeds from the apprehenſion of divine love, where the ſoul finds that God has loved it from all Eternity, that his eye and his heart are perpetually upon it for good, and knows that it is a free, pure, unchangeable, and eternal love, this cauſes an eternity of joy; &amp; a love is the ſweeteſt grace in the heart (the very ſugar of the ſoul) that makes a Heaven upon Earth, where it is without diſſimulation and ſpiritual, ſo heavenly joy will conſiſt much in love, which muſt needs flow from ſight and knowledge, for as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaies, <hi>1 Cor. 2.8.</hi> it is onely ignorance of God that makes ſo many to oppoſe the way of truth and holineſs; ſo the ſight of divine glorious beauty, and the knowledge of infinite wiſdome, power, love, and goodneſs in Chriſt, cauſes the ſoul to love God, and Chriſt, and the Spirit, much better then it ſelf: for if the Spouſe be ſick of love here, <hi>Cant. 5.8.</hi> and if the fire of love conſtrain militant Saints
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:115260:30"/>
not to live to themſelves, <hi>2 Cor. 5.14.</hi> ingenuity being the great prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of the Goſpell not to work for life, but from life, and to doe all from a ſpirit of love, much more the Saints triumphant: but the more I think of this bleſſed ſtate of glorification, the more I am at a loſſe in it, <hi>Pſal. 16.11. in Gods preſence there is fullneſſe of joy, and at his right hand there are pleaſures for evermore:</hi> and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſaies, Pſal. <hi>123. that they that be wiſe ſhall ſhine as the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Firmament, and as the Stars for ever and ever: but one Star differeth from another in glory; and</hi> Matth. <hi>13.43. the righteous ſhall ſhine as the Son in the Kingdome of their Father,</hi> And our Lord ſaies, <hi>in my Fathers Houſe are many manſions,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> calls it, <hi>a far more exceeding and eternal weight of glory, 2</hi> Cor. <hi>4.17. and a building of God a Houſe not made with hands eternal in the Heavens, where we ſhall be ſo ſoon as the ſoul parts from the body, 2</hi> Cor. <hi>5.1, 8.</hi> and that it is an inheritance in light, all light and no darkneſſe, <hi>1 Coloſſ 12.</hi> and that the Saints ſhall judge the world, and when Chriſt ſhall appear, we ſhall be like him; for we ſhall ſee him as he is, <hi>1 John 3.2.</hi> the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> there ſhall be no ſorrow, no crying, no pain, <hi>Rev. 21.4.</hi> and the gates of the City are pearls, and the ſtreet is pure gold, <hi>ver. 21</hi> the glory of God lightens it and the Lamb is the light thereof, <hi>v. 22.</hi> in it there is a pure river of water of life and a tree of life, which bears fruit every month, <hi>Rev. 22.1, 2.</hi> and there ſhall be no Curſes there, and there ſhall be no night, and we ſhall reign for ever and ever, <hi>ver. 5.</hi> All theſe are ſoul raviſhing conſiderations, and I have ſuckt much comfort from, <hi>Pſal. 17.15.</hi> I ſhall be ſatisfied when I awake with thy likeneſſe; and <hi>1 Theſſ. 5.10.</hi> who died for us, that whether we wake or ſleep we ſhould live together with him; therefore let us comfort our ſelves and edifie one another with theſe words, and Mr. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>'s Text, <hi>Heb. 12.22, 23.</hi> it is ſweet alſo to conſider of the glory of the body, <hi>1 Cor. 15.42, 43.</hi> it ſhall be an incorruptible, glorious, powerfull, ſpiritual body, there will be charity, agility, penetrability, impoſſibility, no hunger, no cold, it ſhall be faſhioned like unto Chriſts glorious Body, <hi>Phil. 3.20.</hi> What a comfort is it to thee as me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that have ſuch crazy bodies! ulcerous <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſhall be as ſound as a Fiſh, and we ſhall have an everlaſting ſpring of health and ſtrength which ſhall never decay.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Uſe.</hi> Let this teach us more to mind eternity, to ſtudy the joyes of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:115260:31"/>
Heaven, that we may receive a full reward, <hi>2 Epheſ.</hi> to <hi>8.</hi> as Mr. <hi>Whitfield</hi> once exhorted <hi>Oliver</hi> in every thing to mind and eye eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; for they are the brave men and women that will be ſo at that day: the pleaſures of this world are ſo far from ſatisfying the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and will, which are capable of God, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſatisfie any one ſence; never any Muſick ſo ſweet, but a man will deſire to hear better, no object ſo beautiful, no meat ſo pleaſant, but a man will covet to ſee that which is more lovely and taſts ſweeter, <hi>Eccleſ. 1.8.</hi> ſtudy that Book and Canticles well, that the ſpirit may convince us of the vanity and vexation of all creature-delights, and of the fullneſſe and excellency that is in Jeſus Chriſt the beſt condition in this life is but a bitter-ſweeting, all our comforts are impure mixt with Wormwood, no Roſe without thorn, and the bitter is more then the ſweet, but in Heaven all our delights are pure and unmixed, there is perfect joy without any grief, ſollid comforts and no afflictive mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, no Envy, no Emulation which abounds here; for every Saint has what his heart can deſire, it is a Sinleſſe, Sorrowleſſe, Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſse, Oppreſſionleſſe, Sickleſſe, Timeleſſe and Endleſſe eſtate, where being once Arrived we ſhall never fear parting any more, therefore (my dear ſweeting) let us wait patiently and chearfully for that bleſſed tranſlation from Earth to Heaven; we muſt begin our Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven here, the more prepared to dye, the fitter we are to live, ſo let us live, ſo let us dye, that we way live Eternally. If thee likeſt ſuch poor breathings &amp; broken Meditations, thee may'ſt command more of them, I leave thee and me and my dear child and our Chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations with thee in his Armes who is in Heaven at the right hand of the Father, therefore we need not fear what man can do unto us, <hi>Eſa. 51.12.</hi> To him I am, thine for ever,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Thy loving Husband during this Life,</hi> John Cooke.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:115260:31"/>
               <head>Another <hi>Letter</hi> from Mr. <hi>Cooke</hi> to a Friend af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Condemnation.</head>
               <p>DEar Brother, beloved in the Lord, <hi>condemnatus ſum ad vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam,</hi> and this is my Cordial Farewel to you and all Saints, from my <hi>Jeremiahs</hi> priſon; to morrow I ſhall be in eternal glory, in the boſom of Chriſt, where our father <hi>Abraham</hi> is, and a guard of Angels wil convey my ſoul thither. Never let Gods people fear a priſon any more, for the Lords ſupporting or comforting ſpirit hath not been abſent from me ſince my indictment. I writ a letter to you formerly, acquainting you with my ſpiritual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, to which I refer you; and fearing leſt wrong may be done to the cauſe when I am in heaven, I think fit to leave a few words with my deareſt love to all Chriſtian friends.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Upon my triall it came to this, that the Judges ſaid, <hi>that all have been treaſon ſince</hi> 1642, ſo that the Lords and Commons are not to meddle with the King. I ſaid, <hi>that I acted obedientially by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from the houſe of Commons, and the Commons being the repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives of the people cannot commit treaſon, for there can be no trial of all the people. And as for any force upon the Houſe in</hi> 1648. <hi>they were the onely judges of it and no inferiour Court can judge of the lawfulneſs or unlawfulneſs of their acts or orders.</hi> But they ſaid, all our Acts and Orders are treaſon. So that now it is brought to that it was in 1642.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I intend by Gods aſſiſtance upon the Ladder to beare my teſtimony for Jeſus Chriſt to all his Offices, and for a Goſpel Magiſtracy and Miniſtry, and to ſpeak ſomething ſo farre as God ſhall enable, and wil be permitted, for <hi>the good Old cauſe,</hi> or righteouſneſs and holineſs. I can at preſent onely leave my dear love and reſpects for you and my dear ſiſter, beſeeching God, and not doubting but that we ſhall ſhortly meet in eternal glory. Company ſo ſpends me that I can write no more; I ſhall ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enter into the joy of the Lord, O bleſſed be his name, bleſſed be the Comforter, my ſoul is full of conſolation Farewel, fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel, <hi>Renede in Paradiſo.</hi> Yours forever,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>John Cooke,</signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For my dear brother</hi> F.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon_notes">
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:115260:32"/>
            <head>Some Notes taken of a Sermon Preached by Mr. <hi>Hugh</hi> Peters, the <hi>14<hi rend="sup">th.</hi>
               </hi> of <hi>October</hi> 1660. (after his Condemnation) in the priſon of <hi>Newgate,</hi> wherein he was much interrupted, by the coming in, and going forth, of ſtrangers that came to ſee him, and the other priſoners, in the Room with him, and ſo was conſtrained to break off the ſooner; And though they are but briefe Heads, yet it's thought conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient here to inſert them, for the better ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of any, touching the frame of Mr. <hi>Hugh Peters</hi> at that time. The diſcourſe was from,</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 42. ver. 11.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Why art thou caſt down O my ſoule? and why art thou diſquieted within me? Hope thou in God, for I ſhall yet praiſe him, who is the health of my Countenance and my God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AFter Analyſing the Pſalme, he Obſerved this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
            <p>Doctrine, <hi>That the beſt of Gods people are apt to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was the Mans caſe in the whole 88 <hi>Pſal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Davids</hi> caſe, when he complained of the breaking of his Bones, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was Chriſts caſe himſelfe, when he cryed out
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:115260:32"/>
               <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Reaſons why the beſt of Gods people, are apt to diſpondencies, are,</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>When ſomething falls out from God more then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, when God put's weight in Sorrow and Affliction, that makes it ſinking; Although that Afflictions are heavy of themſelves many times, yet it's the weight that God puts in Sorrow, that makes it ſink us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2ly, Over-valuing our comforts, puting too much upon Wife, Children, Eſtate, or Life it ſelf, a man is apt to be caſt down when he thinks of parting with them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Our unpreparedneſſe for ſufferings, and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that makes us diſpond. Alas I thought not of it ſay ſome, it's come unexpectedly upon me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>We are apt to diſpond when our Afflictions are many, when they are multitudes, when all is ſtruck at together, Name, Eſtate, Relations and Life it ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>VVhen Afflictions are of long continuance, a man can bear that Burthen a while, that he cannot ſtand under long.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>VVhen afflictions fall upon the nobleſt part of man, which is his ſoule; then are diſpondencies apt to come in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seventhly, <hi>VVhen we have more Senſe then Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now it ſhould not be ſo, Gods people ought not to diſpond.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Becauſe it diſcovers impatiency.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Becauſe it diſcovers want of Faith, they leane not upon the Rock that will not faile them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>It diſcovers want of Wiſdome,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>VVe ſhould not be thus, becauſe it gratifies the Enemy, who in ſuch a caſe is ready to upbraide us, and ſay, where is now their God? what is become of their God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now what cure and remedies are there for diſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:115260:33"/>This Eleventh verſe gives you two.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Hope in God, <hi>Hope thou in God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Faith is ſet on work, <hi>I ſhall yet praiſe him,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But more particularly take theſe directions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Be carefull of exerciſing faith, for no condition of man ſuperceeds his Faith, do all in Faith, pray in Faith, and hear in Faith,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Now what is the exerciſe of Faith but rouling upon Chriſt, and ſtaying on him, here I'le ſtick, if I periſh I periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The miſcarriages of Chriſtians, is either becauſe they have no faith, or elſe, becauſe, if they have faith, they give it not food to live upon; faith muſt go to Chriſt, as the Liver Vaine, and fetch bloud and life thence. We quarrel that we have not Love, and Patience, and meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but the defect lyes in our faith, if we had more faith, we ſhould have more of all other Graces.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now what is the food of Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Faith will not feed upon every Diſh, not on a ſtalled Ox or fatted Calfe; proſperity is not faiths food. But it will Eat a word, live upon promiſes, theſe nouriſh faith, <hi>I will never leave thee, nor forſake thee, all things ſhall work together for good,</hi> and the like promiſes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Be marvellouſly carefull of things below, meaſure things not by ſence, or by a day, but by faith, and Eternity; we are troubled at the loſſe of this and tother Creature, and comfort, but what's the value of them, the over valluing things is our miſchiefe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Go and tell the Lord Chriſt I have a defiled conſcience, and if thou doeſt not waſh me, I am undone for Ever. See the neceſſity and worth of Chriſt; there muſt be ſomething better to look at then what we looſe for the preſent, ſomething above Eſtate, and Life, and Relations, and Name. See the worth of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:115260:33"/>
Chriſts bloud, it's worth all the world, becauſe what the bloud of Bulls and Goats could not doe, his bloud doth cleanſe from all ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Keep cloſe to the uſe of Ordinances much of our miſchief hath come from neglects of this kind; the ſafety of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian lyes in the enjoyment of Church Communion, Pſal.</hi> 27.4, 5 <hi>and</hi> 6 <hi>Verſes,</hi> One thing I have deſired of the Lord, and that will I ſeeke after, that I may dwell in the houſe of the Lord all the dayes of my life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for in the time of trouble he ſhall hide me in his Pavillion, in the ſecret of his Tabernacle, ſhall he hide me, he ſhall ſet me upon a Rock; and now ſhall my head be lifted up above mine Enemies round about me, &amp;c. <hi>The greateſt fears are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled there—you ſhall find before troubles paſſe over (for you expect ſome) it will be a hard matter to break Churches, they are ſo faſt chayned together, and yet there hath been mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous miſcarriages amongſt Saints in their Church Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> Finis.</p>
            <p>He alſo during his impriſonment in the <hi>Tower,</hi> wrote ſome ſheets of paper to his Daughter, leaving them with her as his laſt Legacy, containing in it very much ſound and wholeſome advice as to her ſoules health. It carries with it ſuch a ſavour as denotes it proceeds from a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that hath learned experience in Chriſts ſchoole, and hath been aquainted ſometimes with ſunſhine as well as foul weather, it's too long here to be incerted, but if it be made publick by it ſelfe, doubtleſſe the Experienced Reader will be no looſer by peruſing this legacy.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="documents">
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:115260:34"/>
            <head>Some Memorable paſſages of Mr. <hi>Hugh Peters,</hi> in his Impriſonment at <hi>Newgate,</hi> and at the time of his Execution at <hi>Charing-croſſe</hi> October <hi>16 1660.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Peters,</hi> as is well known, was exerciſed under a great conflict in his own ſpirit, during the time of his Impriſonment, fearing (as he would often ſay) that he ſhould not go through his ſufferings with courage and comfort, and ſaid to friends, that he was ſomewhat un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prepared for death, and therefore unwilling to dye; ſomething he ſaid he had committed, and other things omitted, which troubled him, but though it was a clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and dark day with him for a ſeaſon; yet the light of Gods grace and favour would break forth at laſt.</p>
            <p>And ſurely the favour of God did at the laſt appeare, for a little before he went forth to Execution (as many can teſtify) he was well compoſed in his Spirit, and chearfully ſaid, I thank God now I can dye, I can looke death in the face and not be afraid.</p>
            <p>As for that ſlanderous report which was too much received by good people as well as bad, to wit, that he was guilty of Uncleanneſſe. A Friend coming to him in priſon, put that queſtion ſeriouſly and ſoberly to his ſoule, to which he replyed, that he bleſſed the Lord, he was wholy clear in that matter, and that he never knew any woman but his own Wife.</p>
            <p>A night or two before he ſuffered, two of the Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Cleargy, who as ſome report were the Kings Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains, came to give him a viſit; they endeavoured to make advantage of the preſent temptations wherewith
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:115260:34"/>
he was then aſſaulted, and to perſwade him to a Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Recantation of his former Activity in the Parliament cauſe, which they endeavoured to enforce upon him by a promiſe of pardon from the King, in caſe he would therein hearken to them, But though he was then much afflicted in his ſpirit, yet the Lord did help him to beare up with much courage againſt the inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of that ſort of men, and told them he had no cauſe in the leaſt to repent of his Adhering to that intereſt; but rather, that he had in the proſecution thereof done no more for God and his people, in theſe Nations, and with civility diſmiſſing thoſe Viſitants, he applyed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to ſome other Miniſters then preſent, whome he judged more able to ſpeake a word in ſeaſon to him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe great Tryals, wherewith the Lord was then pleaſed to exerciſe him.</p>
            <p>Being carried upon the ſledge to Execution, and made to ſit therein within the Railes at <hi>Charing-Croſſe,</hi> to behold the Execution of Mr. <hi>Cooke.</hi> One comes to him, and upbraided him with the Death of the King, bidding him (with opprobrious language) to repent: he replyed, Friend, you do not well to trample upon a Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing man, you are greatly miſtaken, I had nothing to do in the death of the King.</p>
            <p>When Mr. <hi>Cooke</hi> was cut down, and brought to be quartered, one they called Coll. <hi>Turner,</hi> called to the Sheriffs men, to bring Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> neer, that he might ſee it, And by and by the Hangman came to him, all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmered in bloud, &amp; rubbing his bloudy hands together, he (tauntingly) asked, come, how do you like this Mr. <hi>Peters,</hi> how do you like this work? to whom he replyed, I am not (I thank God) terrifyed at it, you may do your worſt:</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:115260:35"/>When he was going to his execution, he lookt about and eſpied a man, to whom he gave a piece of gold (having bowed it firſt) and deſired him to goe to the place where his daughter lodged, and to carry that to her as a token from him, and to let her know <hi>that his heart was as full of comfort as it could he; and that before that piece ſhould come to her hands, he ſhould be with God in glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being upon the Ladder he ſpake to the Shieriffe, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Sir, you have here ſlain one of the ſervants of God before mine eyes, and have made me to behold it, on purpoſe to terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and diſcourage me, But God hath made it an Ordinance to me for my ſtrengthning and encouragement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When he was going to die, he ſaid, <hi>What fleſh, art thou unwilling to go to God through the fire and jawes of death? Oh</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>this is a good day, he is come that I have long loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for, and I ſhall be with him in glory,</hi> and ſo ſmiled when he went away.</p>
            <p>What Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> ſaid further at his Execution, either in his Speech or Prayer, it could not be taken, in regard his voyce was low at that time, and the people uncivill.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="documents">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:115260:35"/>
            <head>Some Paſſages and occaſional Speeches of Mr. <hi>Scot's</hi> before he came to Execution.</head>
            <p>VVHen he was in the Tower, a Relation ſent to know how he did; To which he returned this anſwer, That he had been very ill all night, and had ſome Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions that it might be unto death. But, ſaid he, I was not at all diſpleaſed; for if it be the Will of God, that I may not live his Servant, I would dye his Sacrifice.</p>
            <p>The firſt day that he came to New-gate, ſome friends came to ſee him, and asked him how it was with him; he told them, he was well; but he waited and much longed for a word of Peace from God: But (ſaid he) I Bleſs God (though it is ſomewhat dark with me at preſent, and I know I have a very naughty heart) yet I have not one Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to deſert <hi>that good Cauſe,</hi> which God hath ſo ſignally (ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a time) owned.</p>
            <p>The next day, which was the day Maj. Gen. <hi>Harriſon</hi> was Condemned, ſome of his Relations came to him, and told him, They ſuppoſed he had heard what diſmal Sentence was paſſed on him; And, O Sir, ſaid one of them, my heart fails me to think how you will bear it. Why, ſaid he, fleſh and blood will recoil; But, bleſſed be God, I am not troubled at that; A fit of an Ague would coſt a man more, I believe.</p>
            <p>The day after he was Condemned himſelf, his Wife and other Relations and Friends came to him: O Sir, ſaid ſome, how is it now? Why, ſaid he, Bleſſed, O bleſſed Chains! I would not be without theſe Chains. Indeed, it was a very dark, diſmal, cloudy morning, I was brought to be content to periſh. Truly, I thought I could not plead at all, my ſoul was ſo ſad, becauſe God hid his face: But I was reſolved, ſaid he, if I could have ſaid no more, to tell the Court, <hi>That the Cauſe was the Lords;</hi> and the fault was not in the Lord, but my great perſonal unworthineſs, that I could not aſſert it; And that though I did ſink into the Bottomleſs Pit immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet I durſt not, no not for a World, but own that Cauſe,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:115260:36"/>
which God had often honoured. But, ſaid he, the Lord for your ſakes did help me to ſay ſomewhat; but, truly it was but pitiful. I thought if I might have been ſuffered, (although I have not ſlept, to ſpeak of, theſe two nights) I could have ſpoken three or four hours longer. And now, ſaid he, as dark as it was in the morning, 'tis ſo bright, ſo quiet and calm, that truly I think, if I were to be executed to morrow, I could ſleep all night as well as ever. But (lifting up his eyes) Lord, ſaid he, I would not be too confident: O pardon thy ſervant. But, being in a very chearful frame, his Friends and Relations left him at that time, and, becauſe of ilneſs, could not viſit him next day.</p>
            <p>But on the next firſt-day of the week, being with him, he told them he found an increaſed ſtrength. That day about noon; the Warrant for Execution was ſigned; at which time, he was deſirous to have a Repreeve gained, if poſſible: not (ſaid he) that I expect Life; but methinks my Wedding Garment is not quite ready: a little more time, that I may, as a Bride, be ready trimmed. That evening it was told him, that Sir <hi>O. B.</hi> would ſpeak with him the next morning; and ſome told him, it may be that would prove an hour of Temptation. Truly (ſaid he) I bleſſe God, I am at a point, I cannot, no, I cannot deſert the CAUSE.</p>
            <p>The next morning they two were together, the matter of their diſcourſe I know not, but I remember when his Wife deſired to go to <hi>O. B.</hi> that evening, to ſee if he would be her dear Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands (or rather her) Mediator to his Majeſty for his Life. It may be (ſaid he) Sir <hi>O. B.</hi> may ſay, That I ſhould confeſs guilt, and do the King ſome ſervice. Prethee tell him, I would engage to live quietly; but for owning <hi>Guilt,</hi> that I cannot do: For to this day I am not convinced of any, as to <hi>the Death of the King,</hi> and that I went but too far, in asking the benefit of the <hi>Proclamation;</hi> and I cannot go any further, no not to ſave a Thouſand Lives.</p>
            <p>That evening came in two Miniſters: one, or both of them, (after they had talked with him a good while) I heard them ask, <hi>Whether he did acknowledge his Guilt?</hi> for they believed his owning of that, would be the moſt likely (if not a moſt certain) means, to prolong his Life. To which he anſwered, That al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:115260:36"/>
he had often, and that with many tears (and he thought with ſome brokenneſs of heart) ſought the Lord to convince him of it, if he had any <hi>Guilt</hi> in him, as to that particular Action, (for which he was then in Chains, and under Condemnation) for, ſaid he, I would not for a World die with one Sin unrepented of: But, ſaid he<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Really, to this day I have no ſuch Conviction. But, ſaid the Doctor, <hi>Sir, If any ſuch do come in, will you tell us?</hi> Yes, ſaid he, I profeſs I will, if it come in at the laſt moment, even at the Gibbet, I will tell the World of it. And it is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable, that ſome of his laſt words were, <hi>That God had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged him in a CA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE, not to be Repented of,</hi> I ſay, <hi>Not to be Repented of</hi> —</p>
            <p>The night before Execution, when he was in the Dungeon, he was (as he had been that day) ſome ſadder than at other times; And one asked him, if any particular thing lay on him? He ſaid, No, But the Lord was pleaſed to ſuſpend his Comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſence: but, ſaid he (with an humble boldneſs I would ſpeak it) The Lord ſhall not put me off with any thing beſides Himſelf. After, having ſpent ſome hours in Prayer, as at other times, about midnight we left him, and his Fellows, that they might get a little reſt, for the ſupport of their natural ſpirits; and in three or four hours his Wife, Children, and many other friends returned. When we came, we found them praying: Aſſoon as Col. <hi>Scroop</hi> had ended, Mr. <hi>Scot</hi> turned about, and opening his arms, he imbraced his Wife, and one of his Daughters: Ah, ſaid he, my dear ones, <hi>God is good, he is come, he is come! I am full, I am full. O bleſſe the Lord for me, and with me; O my ſoul, and all that is within me, magnifie the Lord.</hi> By and by he went to prayer himſelf; and one would have thought he had been (as it were) in Heaven, his ſoul was ſo enlarged in bleſſing, praiſing and magnifying the God of his Salvation. O! ſaid he to his Wife, <hi>I would not change this dark Room for the beſt Star-Chamber under Heaven.</hi> He deſired his Friends and Relations would not be ſolicitous for his Body; but let them do what they pleaſed, and exerciſe what Cruelty they would; ſaying, it was meet it ſhould be ſo: And that the dead Bodies of the Witneſſes muſt be unburied, that the Scriptures might be fulfilled.</p>
            <p>Some part of his prayer was, to bleſſe the Lord, That (as the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:115260:37"/>
Pſalmiſt ſaid) though he came in there weeping, and fearing that he had not yet been bearing precious feed, yet now they were returning rejoycing and triumphing, and carrying their ſheaves with them. Call us not (ſaid he) <hi>Marahs</hi> (as ſhe once ſaid) but call us <hi>Naomies:</hi> for we came in hither (ſome of us) <hi>empty;</hi> but we are going out <hi>full:</hi> The Lord hath not writ <hi>bitter</hi> things, but <hi>good</hi> of us; for this is glorious Grace, <hi>That We are counted worthy to ſuffer for GOD and His CA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE.</hi> Oh! what ſhall we render to the Lord? Wee will <hi>take the Cup of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and call upon the Name of the Lord.</hi> Oh our ſouls, bleſſe the Lord! And we do with our ſouls bleſſe Thee, that we have an Eternity to bleſſe Thee in; for no leſſe will ſatisfie our ſouls, And now, O bleſſed and glorious God, ſhall we be among thy Worthies?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Meaning</hi> N. G. H. Mr. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rew, <hi>and</hi> Mr. Cook.</note> if Poſſible, let us attain to the firſt Three; but if we attain not to ſo glorious a Teſtimony as that, yet O Lord, let us be among thy Worthies. We deſire to glorifie thy great and bleſſed Name, that Thou haſt in any meaſure enabled us to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage our hearts in the Lord our God, at ſuch a time as this, when Eighty is (as it were) in the flames; and the people ſpeak of worſe than ſtoning us. When ſome ſpake of the Reproaches of the people, he ſaid, he accounted that his honour.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <head>Mr. <hi>Scot's</hi> Speech upon the Ladder.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>GENTLEMEN,</hi> I ſtand here a Spectacle to GOD, to Angels, and Men: To GOD and Angels, to whom I hope I am ſhortly a going. And now to you I owe it; to God, and the Nation, and my ſelf, to ſay ſomething concerning each. For my ſelf, I think it may become me to tell you how and why I came hither: and ſomething in the general, concerning my ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity. In the beginning of theſe Troubles I was (as many others were) unſatisfied: I ſaw Liberties and Religion in the Nation, in great danger, to my beſt apprehenſion; I ſaw the approaches of Popery in a great meaſure, coming in upon us: I ſaw —</p>
            <p>Upon which the <hi>Sheriff</hi> interrupted him in theſe words:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If you will betake your ſelf to prayers, you may.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Scot</hi> replied, I ſhall not ſpeak to reproach any —</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:115260:37"/>The <hi>Sheriff</hi> interrupted him again, ſaying, <hi>You have but a little time, Mr.</hi> Scot, <hi>Therefore betake that little time to prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Scot</hi> replied, I ſhall ſpeak —.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sheriff</hi> interrupted him again, ſaying, <hi>I beſeech you Sir, betake your ſelf to prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Scot</hi> ſaid, It may become me to give account of my ſelf, becauſe —</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sheriff</hi> interrupted him again, ſaying, <hi>It doth not become you to ſpeak any ſuch thing here; Therefore I beſeech you betake your ſelf to prayer; it is but a little time you have to live: you know, Mr.</hi> Scot, <hi>that is the moſt needful thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Scot</hi> replied, 'Tis ſo.—</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sheriff</hi> interrupts again, ſaying, <hi>Sir, But when you came upon the Stage, you deprived your ſelf very much.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then ſaid Mr. <hi>Scot,</hi> I thought to tell you how I came hither— Here the <hi>Sheriff</hi> interrupted again (or elſe ſome one beſides the <hi>Sheriff</hi>) and ſpake to this effect. <hi>Every body knows, that</hi>—</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Scot</hi> ſaid, Sir, 'tis hard that an Engliſh man hath not li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to ſpeak —</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sheriff</hi> interrupted again, ſaying, <hi>I cannot ſuffer you to ſpeak any ſuch thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Scot</hi> ſaid, I ſhall ſay no more but this, That it is a very mean and bad Cauſe that will nor bear the words of a dying-man: it is not ordinarily denied to people in this condition —</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sheriff</hi> interrupted again, ſaying, <hi>Sir, you had a fair Tryal, and you were found guilty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Scot</hi> replied, 'Tis according to my mind to ſpeak what may be ſaid—</p>
            <p>Hear the Under-Sheriff interrupted, ſaying, <hi>It hath been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed unto your Predeceſſors, and will be denyed unto you.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>Then he Prayed as followeth.</head>
            <p>HOly Lord God, the great and glorious God of Heaven and Earth; King of Nations, and King of Saints: in both which capacities, thy poor and unworthy Creature comes now to bear his Witneſs in this great ſpectacle, before Thee, Angels and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:115260:38"/>
Men. O Lord, were it not for Sin, none of theſe things had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallen this Nation, nor my unworthy ſelf: We have all tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and gone aſtray from thee by a perpetual back-ſliding; even all, of a ſorts, conditions, ranks and orders of men: And among them none, none more than thy poor unworthy Creature, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth the ſame here before Thee, in the face of Heaven, and in Thy Preſence, to which he is very ſhortly a going. That glorious Grace, which thou haſt been pleaſed to afford unto his ſoul in it. Thou art gone to the higheſt extent of mercy that ever was ſhewed to any of the ſons of men. Thy poor ſervant doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge himſelf to be the greateſt of tranſgreſſors. And thy glorious Grace is magnified above all thy Name, in what Thou haſt done for thy poor Creature. But Lord, ſo it is, becauſe ſuch is thy good pleaſure, ſuch was thy deſign from Eternity; through or in the great Tranſactions that was between Thee, and Chriſt thy bleſſed Son, and our bleſſed Saviour; that Thou ſhouldeſt in thy dispenſation, in the governing of thy Church in the World: That thou ſhouldeſt glorifie thy Free-grace in pardoning of the Sins, and in the Salvation of ſome of loſt Man-kind, which was the great Maſter-piece of thy Love, that thou ſhouldeſt chuſe out of poor loſt Man-kind one or other, it is of admirable and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible mercy: And that thou ſhouldeſt chuſe thy poor Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as one in the number, is matter of Adoration, Admiration, is matter of Eternal Extaſie, and is matter of Thankſgiving for ever: And this is the comfort of his poor ſoul, that he ſhall have an Eternity with thy ſelf; Thou haſt ſo aſſured him, that he ſhall be bleſſing, honouring and magnifying of Thee among a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Saints and Angels, and the ſouls of juſt men made perfect. O bleſſed Lord, thou haſt called him forth as a publick Spectacle to ſome, in a condition of Shame and Reproach; to others, of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; and to thy Bleſſed Self, as one that is a Witneſs for Thee, that hath ſerved Thee with all faithfulneſs in his truſt and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick capacity and imployment. O Lord, thy Dispenſation to thy poor Creature hath been wonderful gracious, and merciful; and he muſt ſay, to the praiſe of thy Free-grace—</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Here the</hi> Hangman <hi>ſtooping down to take Drink, which was reached up to him upon the Ladder, interrupted him; Upon which Mr.</hi> Scot <hi>ſaid, prethee let me alone, I have not done; and then proceeded in Prayer as followeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:115260:38"/>— That this very Condition to which he is now brought, he acknowledgeth, is the anſwer of his Prayer before his going out of <hi>England.</hi> Thou knoweſt Lord, he did many times in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and tears ſeek thy bleſſed Majeſty, for Counſel and for Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; whether it were his duty to ſtay and ſuffer, or to ſhelter him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf abroad: And if it were thy will to take more honour to thy ſelf, by his Suffering than his Living; thou wouldeſt be pleaſed to Remand him back again, and bring him hither. And he hath obſerved thy Providence checking of his way, and in preſerving him all along until he came to this. O bleſſed Lord, thy poor Creature doth acknowledge, that thy ways to his poor Soul, have been of wonderful grace and mercy. It was a great mercy to him, that having had (by reaſon of many ſinful temptations, and many incumbrances, and many inceſſant Buſineſſes in the World, whereof he hath been a perpetual drudge) many years paſt; and he hath not had the conveniency, though his duty: The Lord knowes he had not the conveniency, nor the heart, ſo to improve and keep his own vineyard, while he had been look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after, or keeping others vineyard: Thou didſt therefore all along (while he was abroad) give ſweet opportunities, and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſeaſons, (while he was abroad, of ſeeking thy face, and ſtudy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Souls good concerning Eternity, and the Eternnal pleaſure of thy holy will: And he bleſſeth thy name, that thou haſt been pleaſed to open to him, both the Scripture and his underſtanding; and ſo to anſwer the one by the other, as that he is (through the grace of God) comfortably perſwaded, that his eternal eſtate is out of hazard. But O Lord, thou haſt been pleaſed, all the while that his condition hath been doubtful, to make his Comforts to his poor ſoul doubtful alſo; ſometimes fear, and ſometimes hope, have been mixed: Again, and again wanting thoſe Conſolations that might ſupport his ſoul to ſuch an iſſue. But bleſſed be thy glorious Name, the great God of Heaven and Earth, he hath been pleaſed to bear him witneſs to himſelf, to Angels, and to all that hear me this day, this very day, thy poor Servant that now ſtands to ſuffer, had joy and much Conſolation from God, and from his <hi>Cauſe,</hi> more than ever he had before: I ſay again, to the praiſe of the Free-Grace of God, I bleſs his Name, he hath engaged me in a <hi>Cauſe not to be repented of;</hi> I ſay, in a <hi>Cauſe not to be repented of</hi>—</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:115260:39"/>
               <hi>Here the Sheriff interrupted him, ſaying, Is this your Prayers Mr.</hi> Scot? <hi>deſiring him to forbear thoſe kind of Expreſſions, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo told him, that he contradicted himſelf, and ſpoke Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then Mr.</hi> Scot <hi>ſaid,</hi> I ſhall ſay no more but this; The Lord I do acknowledge, that this very morning in the <hi>Dark Chamber,</hi> I had very much of the preſence of God; and from thence I take Conſolation to my ſelf, that his Spirit is with me, and that he hath ſealed unto my ſoul the Decrees of Heaven, at leaſt perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded my ſoul, that it will be well with me, and that I am out of all danger as to my Eternal Condition; and that I ſhall live and reign with him there, where all ſin ſhall be done away, which is the growing glory of my ſoul, and all tears wipt away alſo; In the mean time I pray thee O Lord, that thou wouldeſt remember <hi>England,</hi> and remember thy <hi>Cauſe</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> and remember me with the joyes of thy Salvation in the inſtant of my departure; O Lord, it is an narrow entrance, it is a ſtrait paſſage, it is an entrance into Eternity. O Lord thou haſt once to day ſhewed me ſomething beyond it, ſomething of the glory of God; I pray thee forſake me not while I am here and ſenſible, or afterwards in the paſſage of my ſoul; to thee I leave it, and to thy Providence, and do acknowledge thy goodneſs to my ſoul, in fitting me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that good which thou in thy infinite pleaſure, doſt think fit for me; And therefore O Lord, into thy hands I commend my Spirit. Lord I deſire to have ſome more teſtimony of thy Love, if it be thy bleſſed will: It is enough that I live upon what I had to day; but if it be agreeable to thy holy will, I would ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and eternally bleſs thee, if thou wouldſt be pleaſed to ſhine upon me, with ſome more particular immediate diſcoveries of thy preſence; but not my will but thy will be done. The Lord be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſettle the Nation in peace, and in the power and purity of Religion, and thy Ordinances in purity: And Lord, for thy Son, that is the darling of thy Soul; Be thou pleaſed to give him a glorious entertainment in the world; and let the Kingdoms of the world, become the Kingdoms of Jeſus Chriſt. Lord thou haſt a <hi>Cauſe</hi> in the world, dear unto thee, I pray thee own it; though it may not be owned in all places, and by all perſons, yet Religion is the Intereſt of them all. O Lord Remember the price
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:115260:39"/>
of Blood, that hath been ſhed for the purchaſing of the Civil and Chriſtian Liberties. And remember thy Enemies, that are not incorrigible Enemies to thy Truth and Holineſs; and give them underſtanding to ſee their Error, and to turn to thee; a heart broken, and with humiliation, that they may ſeek God with their whole heart; that they may be a Holy or Immanuel Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>A Choſen Generation, A peculiar People, zealous of good Works,</hi> careful to <hi>ſhew forth the virtue of him that hath Called them from Death to Life.</hi> The Lord call in all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the <hi>Election of Grace</hi> ſpeedily, into that Number; Let no Weapon formed againſt thy Church proſper; But Lord Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member Zion, if it be thy good pleaſure, and repair the Walls of thy Jeruſalem. O Lord, thy <hi>CAUSE</hi> lies near the hearts of thy People; And I bear thee Witneſs, that I have this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come from thee, as the Return of their Prayers; And that we are Supported to bear Witneſs for thee very chearfully and with ſatisfaction. I deſire to be found of thee in Jeſus Chriſt: I do now abhor all my ſins, and renounce my Services; and do account them all as dung. Lord thou knoweſt, I have deſired to live, that I might ſerve thee better, and love thee more; but that I may be with thy ſelf, Oh it is infinitely better; and to confirm that Teſtimony that is concerning thy glorious Will; And thy Will be done in Earth, as it is in Heaven, by me and all thine, from henceforth, and for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="documents">
            <head>Some Memorable Paſſages of <hi>Col. Adrian Scroope,</hi> after his Condemnation, and in his Impriſonment at Newgate, which (though they are but few) may diſcover the excellent chriſtian frame of his heart, and how he was born up under ſo great Sufferings.</head>
            <p>AFter his Condemnation, one of his Children hanging upon him, and weeping over him, he ſaid, Peace, Child, peace, be ſtill, not a word; thou haſt a bleſſed Portion: Who would be troubled to dye? for can any one have greater honour, than to have his Soul carried up to Heaven, upon the wings of the Prayers of ſo many Saints?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:115260:40"/>When the Jaylor called him, and Mr. <hi>Scot,</hi> Mr. <hi>Jones,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Clement,</hi> to go to the Dungeon, ſaying Gentlemen, you muſt got to the Room where Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi> was. Sayes Colonel <hi>Scroop,</hi> Muſt we all go? He repleyed, Yes. At which, laying his hand on his breaſt, and elevating his eyes, with a ſerious coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, ſaid, Bleſſed be God that we are not parted.</p>
            <p>As he ſate at Dinner he ſpoke to a Miniſter that was with them ſaying. I would ſpeak it for glory of God's Free-grace, and and comfort of you all, That my ſins are all pardoned; not one and in the ſtrength of this, will I go to Heaven.</p>
            <p>Speaking to ſome Friends that came to viſit him, ſaid, I deſire all the People of God, to look at the Lords hand in this Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, and own his Soveraignity; ſpeak well, of him, what-ever he doth; lie at his feet with their mouthes in the duſt; and live more in love and unity one with another.</p>
            <p>A tall Gentleman coming into the Dungeon to ſee Col. <hi>Scroop,</hi> the night before he dyed, ſaid to him, Uncle, I am ſorry to ſee you in this condition, and would deſire you to repent of the Fact, for which you are brought hither, and ſtand to the Kings mercy; and more words so the ſame effect. Whereupon Col. <hi>Scroop</hi> put forth his hand, and thruſt him from him, uſing theſe words, AVOID SATAN.</p>
            <p>When the time approached for his Execution, Mr. <hi>Scot</hi> and Mr. <hi>Clement</hi> were firſt carried away in the Sleds, and the ſame Sleds was afterwards to come and carry Col. <hi>Scroop,</hi> and Col. <hi>Jones;</hi> during that time, ſayes Col. <hi>Scroop,</hi> Well Brother <hi>Jones,</hi> do you ſpend your time as the Lord ſhall direct you, I intend to take a little ſteep, for I ſlept not well the laſt night; and my Countenance is not ſo freſh as I would have it. Thereupon he laid him down, and ſlept ſo ſoundly, that he ſnored very loud, and ſo continued until the Sled came for him: whereupon, being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened, he riſeth up; and a Friend taking him in his Arms, asked him how he did? he anſwers, Very well, I thank God, never better in all my life.</p>
            <p>And now, ſaith he, <hi>will I waſh mine hands in Innocency, So will I compaſſe thine Altar, O Lord:</hi> And ſo with great chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs went to Execution.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:115260:40"/>Colonel <hi>Adrian Scroop,</hi> and Colonel <hi>John Jones</hi> (two comely ancient Gentlemen) were both drawn upon that Sled which carried Mr. <hi>Scot;</hi> and being come to <hi>Charing-Croſſe,</hi> the place of Execution, Col. <hi>Scroop</hi> was firſt brought up to the Ladder, where he ſpake as followeth.</p>
            <div type="speech">
               <head>Col. <hi>Scroop's</hi> Speech at Execution, Octob. <hi>17. 1660.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOu ſee an Object here, that hath been in a better place; but howſoever the Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath ſent me to this place, that in this place I ſhould die. I have no Animoſity nor Malice againſt any man, nor ever had I; neither have I any evil will to thoſe that brought me hither, nor to the Jury that found me guilty, nor Judges that paſſed Sentence; nor to him through whoſe means I was brought here to ſuffer. I ſay, once more, the Lord forgive him, I ſhall not name him; for I come not hither to reflect upon any mans perſon.</p>
               <p>I will not tell you what my Breeding hath been, becauſe it is not good for any man (eſpecially at ſuch a time as this) to boaſt of his Linage or Breeding; But this I ſhall ſay, that I was born and bred a Gentleman.</p>
               <p>As for my Carriage, it may be ſome that looks upon me here, knows what it hath been: Howſoever the Lord knows all, and the Lord God is Judge of all, and he will judge; I ſhall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit my ſelf to his Judgment, which is a Righteous Judgment. The judgement of men may go wrong, but Gods Judgement is right, I ſhall ſubmit to his way, The Lord he is the <hi>Rock of Ages,</hi> and my Support under this great Weight that is now up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me: I look up to him alone, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt is my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour and my Redeemer; I am going into his Arms, bleſſed be his Name: I follow him, he is gone before me the ſame way: Therefore it is no reproach or ſhame to follow the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, to die in his Cauſe; for that is it which I judge I am now going to do.</p>
               <p>That which I do deſire of you (here are a great many Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors both on the right hand and on the left) is, That this day may repreſent to you, the general Day of the Judgement of Chriſt, where you muſt appear, and there every man muſt receive ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their works: And at that time it will be known; I
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:115260:41"/>
ſay, at that time it will be known and ſeen, whoſe works are righteous, and whoſe are not: Therefore I would wiſh you, and deſire you, to judge charitably of me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Col. <hi>Scroop</hi> having given a brief account of himſelf to the People, his laſt work was, to give up himſelf to God in Prayer, as follovveth.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord, thou art my Father, a preſent help in trouble; Thou art my Father, I believe in Thee: I come unto thee, Lord Jeſus, that went unto thy Father, and my Father, thy God and my God; and this is that which doth ſupport my ſpirit, and ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble me to undergo this Death with chearfulneſs and readineſs. Lord, thou knoweſt my heart and affections, and my deſires, Oh deal not with me according to my ſins, I am a miſerable wretched ſinner; <hi>If thou enter into Judgment, who is able to ſtand before thee? but there is forgiveneſs with thee, that thou mayeſt be feared.</hi> O Lord let it be known and ſeen, that there hath not been any heart in me, to do any thing with Malice or Revenge, or that might ſhew any Revenge: If there be any Revenge on the other ſide, the Lord lay it not to their charge. The Lord bleſſe thoſe in Authority, the Lord bleſſe his Majesty that he may reign prosperouſly, and that he may receive a bleſſing from the hand of the Lord. O Lord, thou ſeeſt my failings, my infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities and weakneſſes: O Lord, I beſeech thee that thou wouldſt bear with me, thou art a tender-hearted Father; Thou art my ſtrength: When my heart and my ſtrength faileth, then thou art the ſtrength of my heart, and my portion for ever. O Lord be with me in this hour of Temptation, and carry me through it; for thou art my God and my Father, into whoſe hands I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my ſpirit, for thou haſt redeemed me.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>The <hi>Copy</hi> of a Letter ſent from <hi>Col. John Jones,</hi> when Priſoner in the <hi>Tovver</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> to a Relation.</head>
            <p>I Am very much grieved, to find (by the Note I received from you) ſuch dark and ſad Apprehenſions upon your Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit concerning me: VVe are in the hands of the Lord, and what he hath appointed for us, will be our portion, and no man can
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:115260:41"/>
fruſtrate his holy purpoſe concerning us; which I queſtion not will be found to be in love, what ever appearance it may have to men. My Advice is to you and all that love me, That (in caſe I be removed from you) you do not, neither in reallity, nor outward garb, mourn for me; but rather rejoyce, that my Portion is in Heaven; and that my Diſſolution or Removal out of this earthly Tabernacle, is but in order to my Cloathing with Immortality, and poſſeſſing my Eternal Manſion; and to my being for ever with Chriſt, to behold his glory; And therefore that you do not behave your ſelf, as thoſe that have <hi>no hopes but of this life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, That you take off your mind from me, and fix it unmovably upon your eternal Relation, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; in whoſe glorious and bleſſed preſence, we ſhall meet ere long, to our Eternal Rejoycing; It is the goodneſs of the Lord to us, to remove all Creature Comforts from us, that our Souls might have no reſting-place to delight in, or to promiſe them ſafety; until we return to the Ark of his Teſtimony, the boſome of his love manifeſted and exhibited for us, in our bleſſed Lord Jeſus Chriſt. I write in haſt, therefore excuſe my abruptneſs.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in Sincere Love, JOHN JONES.</signed>
               <dateline>Tower, <date>
                     <hi>Sept.</hi> 19. 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>Let the Firſt and laſt Verſes of <hi>Pſalm</hi> 27. be conſtantly fixed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy mind.</p>
               <p>Ver. 1. <hi>The Lord is my light &amp; my ſalvation, whom ſhall I fear? The Lord is the ſtrength of my life, of whom ſhall I be afraid?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Verſ. 14. <hi>Wait on the Lord, be of good, courage, and he ſhall ſtrengthen thy heart; wait I ſay on the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <head>Some few living Sentences, that fell from a Dying Man, Col. <hi>Joh. Jones,</hi> when he was in his Chains in <hi>Newgate.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>OBſerving one of Col. <hi>Scroopes</hi> children weeping, he takes her by the hand, ſaying to her, You are weeping for your Father, but ſuppoſe your Father were to morrow to be King of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:115260:42"/>
               <hi>France,</hi> and you were to tarry a little behind, would you weep ſo? why he is going to reign with the King of Kings, in everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Glory.</p>
            <p>Speaking to a Friend, that was to have accompanied him into <hi>Ireland,</hi> Ah! dear heart (ſayes he) thee and I were in that ſtorm together, going to <hi>Ireland,</hi> and if we had gone this jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney then, we had been in Heauen to have welcomed honeſt <hi>Harriſon</hi> and <hi>Carew;</hi> but we will be content to go after them, we will go after.</p>
            <p>Speaking of thoſe that were gone beyond the Seas, (O dear hearts, ſayes he) in what a ſad condition are our dear Friends beyond Sea, where they may be hunted from place to place, and never be in ſafety, nor hear the voice of the Turtle; how much have we gotten the ſtart of them, for we are at a point, and are now going to Heaven?</p>
            <p>Speaking of the Sled in which he was to be carryed to Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; it is (ſaid he) like <hi>Elija's</hi> Fiery Charriot, only it goes through <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The time of his departure being come, this Aged Gentleman, was drawn in one Sled, with his Aged Companion, Col. <hi>Scroop,</hi> whoſe grave and graceful Countenances, accompanied with cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and chearfulneſs, cauſed great Admiration and Compaſſion in the Spectators, as they paſſed along the Streets, to <hi>Charing-Croſſe,</hi> the place of their Execution; And after the Executioner had done his part upon three others that day, he was ſo drunk with Blood, that like one ſurfeited, he grew ſick at ſtomack: and not being able himſelf, he ſet his Boy to finiſh the Tragedy upon Col. <hi>Jones;</hi> who coming up the Ladder, with the like chearfulneſs that his Brethren did before him; and being placed fit for Execution, he proceeds to ſpeak as followeth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <head>
               <hi>Col.</hi> Joh. Jones his Speech upon the Ladder, <hi>Oct. 17. 1660.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THere is two things that are neceſſary, now I am going through this narrow gate or paſſage, to the Eternal Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty; I ſay two things are neceſſary, as to the occaſion of my co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming hither, to receive my Fathers good pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Peace with God.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Peace with Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:115260:42"/>I ſhall ſpeak ſomething to each of theſe; and in the firſt place, ſpeak ſomething of the Court wherein I received the Sentence; It hath been reported, as I was told, that I confeſſed this Fact, and confeſſed that I were guilty of Murther, as under thoſe ſeveral ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions that are in the Indictment, <hi>Viz.</hi> —</p>
            <p>I deſire to clear my ſelf before the Lord, and before the world, in that particular; for ſhould I grant that I was guilty in reallity and truth of Murther and Malice, <hi>(Viz.)</hi> —</p>
            <p>I ſhould belie my own Conſcience, and draw upon me a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter weight than I could bear; But this far I do confeſſe, I was willing to make the work as ſhort as I could, And becauſe I would not ſtand ſo long, I told them I would take the firſt Jury that came; And when a Jury was called, then I did confeſs ſo much as I was convinced of, as to the matter of Fact, I deſire you will judge charitably of this that I ſpeak at this time, as in the preſence of the Lord, that it is not ſo really (<hi>viz.</hi> that I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged my ſelf guilty of Murder) I had no ſuch thing in my heart.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs I very freely quit his Majeſty, conſidering what he doth in this caſe is the part of a loving Son to a Father, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the Judges telling him that it is the Law; and I conceive that the Court did nothing, but what they to their beſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, judged right as to Law; Therefore I freely acquit the Court, though there was not enough ſaid, to ſatisfie ſuch a poor Creature as I am, in ſo great and deep a point as that was: As for all others, I do not know any man on the Earth, to whom I do bear any Malice, but I am in perfect charity with all men; and I hope the Lord is in charity with me: And therefore as I deſire to have forgiveneſs my ſelf from all thoſe that I have offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, even ſo, I do freely forgive all thoſe that have in any mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure offended me.</p>
            <p>The next thing is towards God, and it is that which ſhould be laſt upon my heart, It is not expected that I ſhould give an Account here of my ſtate and condition, for that is betwixt God and my own ſoul; And I do, through the Grace and Goodneſs of God, firmly believe, that my Redemption is wrought, and my Pardon is ſealed, and that I ſhall be immediately in my Fathers armes, and that I ſhall be tranſlated and brought to behold the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in glory, with comfort and fulneſſe of joy.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:115260:43"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Col. JONES</hi> his Prayer,</head>
            <p>BLeſſed Lord God, Thou art the great Opener, open unto my ſoul the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who will lead me into the wayes of truth and life; O God ſave me, make good all the pledges of thy love unto my ſoul; Oh make all the Promiſes which I have believed all the days of my life, make them now good unto my ſoul, giving me the full enjoyment of thy ſelf: I deſire to bleſs and praiſe thy Name for this hour that thou haſt brought me to, Oh, what am I poor worm, that thou ſhouldeſt give me this oportunity to ſuffer for thy Name, and to acknowledg thy Mercies before ſo great a Congregation at this place. Holy Father, Holy Father, Oh that thou wouldeſt now rain down Bleſſings from Heaven upon thy poor creatures, that do hear and behold this Action, this day; Oh that thou wouldeſt ſanctifie this thing to them, and let poor <hi>England</hi> be a Land of truth and happineſs, O Lord let <hi>England</hi> flouriſh: And oh that thou wouldeſt make thy Angel of Light to go before thy people: Good God we pray thee keep off thoſe great Judgments that hang over the heads of theſe Nations, becauſe they have ſinned againſt thee: Through thy Name ſanctifie us, let not thy Name be reproached. Dear Father, receive my ſoul, I am ready to come unto thee: Bleſſed Father, into thy hands I commend my Spirit: thou haſt redeemed me, bleſſed be thy Name, in that thou haſt opened the treaſures of thy love unto my poor ſoul. Thou haſt given me this hope, whereof I need not be aſhamed. Bleſſed be thy Name, my Spirit is full of joy. Oh Holy Father, holy Father, I pray thee let thy bleſſing come down upon thy poor people. Look upon me, Holy Father: Stretch out thine armes to carries me over this brook. I pray thee ſtand by me, Dear Father, I caſt my ſelf into thy hand, I commit my ſoul unto thee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then ſpeaking to the Sheriff, ſaid, Mr. Sheriff, I muſt needs return you many Thanks for your Civility.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sher. Repl. <hi>I am glad to hear ſuch an Ingenuous Confeſſion, and that you make ſuch an end, and that you have not gone into any reviling language, as ſome others have done before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>After this he committed his ſoul to God, and ſo departed.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:115260:43"/>
            <head>Something as to Mr. <hi>Gregory Clements,</hi> take as followeth.</head>
            <p>PErhaps ſome may think it ſtrange, that there is ſo little ſaid, as to Mr. <hi>Gregory Clement,</hi> who ſuffered with the reſt; Therefore this only is to be ſa<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> more, (which is known to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) That Mr. <hi>Clement</hi> was very ſilent both in the time of his Impriſonment at <hi>Newgate,</hi> and at the time and place of his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution at <hi>Charing-Croſs,</hi> only this it is ſaid, that he expreſt his trouble, (to ſome Friends in the Priſon) for yeelding ſo far to the Importunity of his Relations, as to plead guilty to the Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And though he ſpoke little at the place of Execution; yet (ſo far as could be judged by ſome deſcerning perſons that was near him) he departed this life in peace.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="documents">
            <head>Some Additional Paſſages of Col. <hi>Scroopes,</hi> Col. <hi>Jones,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Cooks;</hi> with his Letter to his Daughter.</head>
            <div type="document">
               <head>Some more Paſſages of <hi>Col. Scroope.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>COl. <hi>Scroope,</hi> when a Friend asked him at parting, the ſame day, how he did, anſwered him, Better and better I thank God every moment, my life doubles upon me, and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplies.</p>
               <p>He alſo heard him ſay, when mention was made, that there was ſome Endeavours for his Pardon, That only would prove a ſnare to him, but he was fully ſatisfied what to do, and ſhould not to ſave his Life, do any thing to prejudice his Conſcience.</p>
               <p>He alſo heard him when one was diſcourſing to him the Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of Heaven, and telling him it conſiſted in three Things, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:115260:44"/>
A perfect Communion with God; A perfect Conformty to God; And a perfect Enjoyment of God. He made this reply, Thoſe three Things you mention are but one, we are entring into it, and can tell. And that Friend asking him futher about it, he ſaid, That God was but one pure Act, and in whom there was no ſucceſſion nor diſtinction of Acts; and that Souls led forth in his Spirit, were in a manner made like to him; for their Injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was their Conformity and Communion, and one was all: In which he ſeemed to be ſwallowed up, and even then gat ſo far into Heaven, that all ſeemed to be but one Act with him.</p>
               <p>Some Friends being preſent, heard both him and Col. <hi>Jones</hi> ſay; You can ſay, God is better than all the World, and ſay it truly; but you cannot ſay it with ſo much feeling and experience, as we now can: we find he is ſo indeed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="document">
               <head>Some more Paſſages of Col. <hi>Joh. Jones</hi> in Priſon.</head>
               <p>COL. <hi>Jones,</hi> the night before he ſuffered, told a Friend he had no other Temptation upon him but this, Leſt he ſhould be too much tranſported and carryed out to neglect and ſlight his Life; ſo greatly was he ſatisfied to die in that <hi>Cauſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The day he ſuffered, he graſped a Friend in his arms, and ſaid to him with ſome expreſſions of Endearedneſs, Farewel: I could wiſh thee in the ſame condition with my ſelf, that thou mighteſt ſhare with me in my joyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="document">
               <head>Some more Paſſages of Mr <hi>Cook.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MR <hi>Cook</hi> ſpeaking to his Wife a little before his Death, ſaid, My Lamb, now I am going where I ſhall meet the Saints all of one mind, which thou knoweſt was the deſire of my heart to ſee. At another time, ſaith he, Truly, my Lamb, if I might have my choice now, I would not deſire Life; for I could not live where I might not enjoy the Liberty of my Conſcience: and when I can do nothing for God, what ſhould I live for? O welcome ſweet Death! thy ſting is out, bleſſed be God, I do imbrace thee with rejoycing: thou art a good Potter, that will ſuddenly open to
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:115260:44"/>
me the Gates of Eternity; O thoſe Everlaſting Gates will my Father ſet open to receive me. O bleſſed be God for Jeſus Chriſt the fountain of all Mercies! Lord Jeſus, I come flying to thee upon the wings of Faith; I come, Lord, full-ſail to thee, Lord Jeſus receive me. That which the world counts ſhame, ſaith he, I count it my Joy, my Crown, and my Glory.</p>
               <p>A little before he parted with his Wife, ſhe laying her head in his boſom and wept; whereat he ſaid, My dear Lamb, let us not part in a ſhower, God hath wiped away all tears from my eyes, bleſſed be the Lord.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Mr. <hi>Cook's</hi> Letter to his Daughter, <hi>Octob. 15. 1660.</hi> A little before his Death.</head>
            <head>To my dear Child, <hi>Free-love Cook:</hi> Theſe, with my moſt Fatherly endeared Love.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My dear ſweet Child,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>LEt thy Name, <hi>Free-love,</hi> put thee in mind of the free Love of God in Chriſt, in giving thee to me and thy dear Mother; and know, ſo ſoon as God gives thee any underſtanding, That thou art the Child of one whom God counted worthy to ſuffer for his ſake, and to ſeal to the Truth of his Law and Goſpel with his Blood, which will be a great Honour to thee in the judgment of all that truly love and fear God. I leave thee to the Lord, who I know will take care of thee, and be thy Portion, ſo thou ſhalt never want. Learn with all ſpeed to reade the Scriptures, and to underſtand them; and have a great care to ſerve God, and ſtudy to love Jeſus Chriſt, and be obedient to thy dear Mother, and good Grandmother, and thy loving Uncle and Aunt <hi>Maſſey.</hi> I pray thee never learn any Pride, but be humble and meek, and courteous, and wait upon Gods Ordinances: love the Word more than
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:115260:45"/>
thy appointed food. When the Lord ſhall pleaſe to alter thy Condition, be ſure to marry one that is gracious, and a man that feareth God; be ſure to prefer Grace before Wealth and Parts: for a little with the fear of God, is better than great Riches with an Ungodly man: The Lord make thee Religious; for Beauty is Vanity, and Favour is deceitful, <hi>but a Woman that feareth the Lord ſhe ſhall be praiſed.</hi> If the Lord give thee Children, be ſure to bring them up vertuouſly and religiouſly, in the Nurture, Admonition and Fear of the Lord. I charge thee never to marry without the Conſent of thy dear Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if ſhe be then living. In all thy Actions have an eye to Eternity, and never do any thing againſt the Light of thy own Conſcience. Know that thy dear Father is gone to Heaven to thy dear Brother, — and be ſure ſo to live, that by Gods Grace thou mayeſt follow after. If God give the ability, I charge thee to do good to thy Friends, and to all Gods People: And if my laſt Will may be of force, do not violate it in the leaſt. So I leave Gods Bleſſing with thee, praying for thy Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and Eternal Happineſs, and reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy dear loving Father, <hi>JOHN COOK.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Octob. 15, 1660.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="4 pages">
               <desc>〈4 pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="documents">
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:115260:45"/>
            <head>Some occaſionall Speeches, and Memorable paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of <hi>Col. Axtell</hi> and <hi>Col. Hacker,</hi> during their Impriſonment, and at their Execution.</head>
            <p>BEing asked by ſome Friends how he found himſelf ſitted to Encounter with Death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He Anſwered,</hi> I can ſay nothing until I come to dye, I dare not boaſt till I put of my Armour, but deſire your prayers until there be no more need of them.</p>
            <p>Returning from his Tryal at the Court to his Priſon with a chearful countenance, and his Wife coming to him full of Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, he ſaid, not a Tear Wife, what hurt have they done me, to ſend me ſooner to Heaven; And I bleſſe the Lord I could have freely gone from the Bar to the Gibbet. They had nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me neither by Gods law nor their own low to condemne me, was it ever known that a man ſhould dye for ſuch Words, and further ſaid, <hi>though men had Judged yet God had not Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some taking notice of his courſe lodging, he ſaid what matter is it to have a little durty way, when we have a fair Houſe to come into.</p>
            <p>Then looking upon Friends about him ſaid, if the ſight of ſo few of Gods people be ſo comfortable, what will it be to enjoy all the Saints in Heaven together.</p>
            <p>Towards the cloſe of that Evening he went to prayer (divers being preſent who admired the bleſſed frame of ſpirit that he was in) admiring God in all his appearances for his poor people, he laid all his comfort in the blood of a crucifyed Chriſt, and upon the Covenant of Free Grace; he did heartily deſire pardon for all his Judges, Jury and thoſe witneſſes that had ſworn falſely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him.</p>
            <p>Returning again from the Court when he had received his ſentence, he came into the priſon very chearfully with a Bible in his hand, ſaying, I ſhall have the uſe of this book two dayes more, and then injoy the fulneſſe of the Goſpel to all Etetnity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:115260:46"/>His Daughter coming in to him, he ſaid where haſt thou been all this while, I thought thou hadſt been aſhamed of my Chains? but they that will not bear the Croſſe, ſhall not weare the Crown.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Gentleman coming to viſit him, ſaid, ſhall I petition for your life?</hi> Col. Axtel <hi>replyed, Sir you offer me to my loſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Gentleman told him he was going for <hi>Ireland,</hi> Col. <hi>Axtell</hi> ſaid Sir pray remember my love to all Chriſtian friends there, &amp; tell them (ſaid he, ſhaking of his Chains rejoycingly) that you ſaw me in my chains; &amp; I recon all theſe links as ſo many Pearls to Adorn me, and am ſure they are ſo in Chriſts account; and tell them that for that <hi>Good Old Cauſe</hi> which we were ingaged in, under the Parliament, I am now going to be their Martyr. And as for the King, I wiſh him as well as my own ſoule. But they have meerly murthered me, and they might as well have done it at the Tower, as have brought me hither to make this busſle; I wiſh my bloud do not cry to the third and fourth Generation. But I ſhall do them more hurt in my death, then I could do in my life. They had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in Gods law nor their own to condemne me, the Court condoled me, but it was enough my name was <hi>Axtell,</hi> I wiſh that I may ſee them all in Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Friend going into Glouceſterſhire, ſaid to him, Sir what meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage will you now ſend to the good people in the Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Col. <hi>Axtell</hi> Anſwered Remember my dear love to them all, and tell them that their prayers are Anſwered. Bid them keep cloſe to Chriſt, and let them not touch with Surplis or Common prayer book; and bid them (what ever they doe) love the image of Chriſt where ever they ſee it, in <hi>Presbyterian, Independent, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed</hi> or other; And take heed of ſtriking in with any thing, that will ſtrike out any of the Offices of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Four of his fellow priſoners paſſed by his Chamber dore, as they were going forth to Execution, and being denyed ſight of them, he called them by their Names, and with a mighty fervent ſpirit ſaid, <hi>the Lord go with you, the Angell of his preſence ſtand by you</hi> (and then turning about to his Friends ſaid) <hi>Oh they are gone to Heaven before me,</hi> but we will give them up to the Lord, and ſo went to prayer and preſently after he went to prayer againe, ſaying, <hi>God hath ſaid that he will make us joyfull in the houſe of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:115260:46"/>
Prayer:</hi> and many obſerved that he did perform the duty of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Five times that day himſelfe, wherein he laid himſelf very low before the Lord, acknowledging himſelf the worſt of all the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, and that he ſhould have the leaſt to ſay for God, and would ſay to his Friends, ſay nothing of me tell you ſee me on the upermoſt round of the Ladder.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>His Daughter coming in he told her that he had left Jeſus Chriſt an Executor in truſt for her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having given an Account to ſome perſons for their ſatisfaction about his proceedings againſt the Rebels in <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſaid, I can ſay in Humility, that God did uſe me as an inſtrument in my place, for the ſuppreſſing of that boudy Enemy, and when I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered their bloudy cruelty in murthering ſo many thouſands of proteſtants and innocent ſouls, that word was much upon my heart, give her bloud to drink for ſhe is worthy; and ſometimes we neither gave nor took Quarter, though ſelf preſervation would have ſaid, give that which you may expect to have.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>One coming in told him that his fellow priſoners dyed Nobly and Chearfully,</hi> (well ſaid he, but how doe they ſtand?) <hi>Anſwer was made upon a Ladder. Bleſſed be God ſaid he, it is a Jacobs Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Sun ſhining into the room, he ſaid, if it be ſo glorious to behold the Sun, what will it be to behold the Son of Glory.</p>
            <p>Laying his hand upon (his fellow priſoner) Col. <hi>Hacker,</hi> he ſaid, <hi>come brother be not ſo ſad, by this time to morrow we ſhall be with our Father in Glory, and what hurt will they do us to bring us through the Croſſe to the Crown. Well, our God is the God of Newgate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then the Officer coming to carry them down into the Dunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he took his leave of many of his Friends then preſent, ſaying love the Lord Jeſus, love the Lord, and weep not for me, for God hath wiped away all tears.</p>
            <p>And coming to the dore of the Dungeon ſaid, I am now going to my bed of Roſes my laſt bed.</p>
            <p>Many Friends being with him, there was an Eminent Godly Miniſter of the Presbyterian way; and Col. <hi>Axtell</hi> taking him by the hand, ſaid, I have one word to ſpeak to you, it is much upon my heart, that one great cauſe why the Lord contends thus with
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:115260:47"/>
his people, is for want of their love towards them that were not of their minds; to which the Miniſter replyed, truly Sir I think ſo too, the Lord help us that wherein we ſee we have done amiſſe, we may do ſo no more. Then ſaid,</p>
            <p>Col. <hi>Axtell,</hi> I bleſſe God I have not much to charge my ſelfe with in this matter.</p>
            <p>Col. <hi>Hacker then ſaid, but I have much to complaine of in that matter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Col. <hi>Axtell,</hi> Afterwards ſitting on his bed ſide clapping his hands, ſaid, if I had a thouſand lives, I could lay them all down for the Cauſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereupon another godly Miniſter then preſent asked him what he meant by the cauſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Col. <hi>Axtell</hi> replyed, Sir I tell you I mean that cauſe which we were encouraged to, and ingaged in under the Parliament, which was for common Right and Freedome and againſt the Surplis and Common prayer book; and I tell you, that Surplis and Common prayer book ſhall not ſtand long in <hi>England</hi> for it is not of God.</p>
            <p>And afterwards thinking that he ſhould not dye that day, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired ſome retirement, but news coming that he muſt dye within an hour (though it was not ſo) he quickly made himſelf ready to go, and looking upon his Gloves, ſaid, theſe are my wedding Gloves, my mortal muſt marry immortality.</p>
            <p>Some Friends going to ſee him the night before he was Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted found him at ſupper very chearful, and many being preſent, he ſaid take heed of temporizing, &amp;c. for that hath been the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of great Evil. Then ſpeaking to an Officer there preſent, that had continued tell of late in the Army, ſaid, Brother thou haſt been greatly Guilty herein, the Lord forgive thee, thou haſt a great hand in this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To which the perſon replyed, I confeſse I have been ſo too much.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Col. <hi>Axtell</hi> anſwered, there is yet mercy for thee if the Lord give thee repentance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moreover ſaid, the Lord forgive that poor wretch</hi> Lieut. C. <hi>N. for he hath ſworn falſely in his Evidence; and now is that word made good,</hi> that brother ſhall betray brother to death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And ſpeaking of</hi> Col. T. <hi>ſaid, Ah he hath appeared Five pound lighter in Twenty then I thought him to be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:115260:47"/>
               <hi>And for</hi> Col. H. <hi>he was the uncivilleſt of all about the late King, and yet he comes in a witneſſe againſt Hacker and me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Evening many Friends being with him, he prayed with them, and in that duty the Lord by his ſpirit filled him with Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Expreſſions, to the great refreſhing of thoſe about him. And bewailing the great Diviſions amongſt Gods people, he ſaid, Lord if they will not live together in love, thou wilt make them lye together in ſufferings. Then minding their preſent condition, ſaid, Lord Death is the King of Terrors to Nature, but it is a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers choice Friend, it is thy high way to lead us into Glory.</p>
            <p>After prayer taking notice of his Daughter, he ſaid to her, <hi>get an intereſt in Chriſt and keep cloſe to him, he will be a better Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to thee then I, and ſo took his leave of her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The day of their Execution being come, ſeveral godly Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſpent ſome time with them in prayer, <hi>Viz.</hi> with Col. <hi>Axtell</hi> and Col. <hi>Hacker,</hi> and many friends coming in to pay their laſt reſpects, Col. <hi>Axtell</hi> ſeeing one of his Familiar Friends and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, ſaid, my Dear brother thou art better then I am, and yet I muſt go to heaven before thee for all that.</p>
            <p>He very chearfully ſaid to divers then with him, dear Friends Rejoyce, I am going where ye ſhall be alſo, yea where we ſhall be for ever with the Lord and never part, and be without any more change; I beſeech you follow the Lamb wherever he goeth, though he may lead you in a harſh, diſmal and difficult way; yet at laſt he will bring you into a pleaſant path, and cauſe you to lye down in green paſtures, in the land of reſt, <hi>Oh be faithful un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the death, and he will give you a Crown of life,</hi> as he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to your ſuffering Brethren.</p>
            <p>Oh! all that we have, or doe ſuffer, is but to make Chriſt and heaven more ſweet, deare and Glorious to us; all the ſad ſteps we ſhall tread on this Ladder, is but to mount us to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, for at the top are Angels ready to receive us, as was on <hi>Jacobs</hi> ladder. All the things I meet with move me not I bleſſe my God, for I am ſure to Fight a good Fight and finiſh my courſe with joy.</p>
            <p>Afterwards taking his leave of his Son, imbracing him in his Arms, he ſaid, my dear ſon fare thee well, I muſt leave thee, get an intereſt in Chriſt and love him, nothing elſe will ſtand thee in ſtead but an intereſt in him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:115260:48"/>Then calling for his Bible he hugged it, ſaying, this hath the whole Cauſe in it, and I may carry this without offence. And calling to a Friend he deſired him to remember his love to the Congregation, where he was a Member, and after took his leave of all his Friends, exhorting them with much chearfulneſſe to love the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and keep cloſe to him, and ſo with great joy addreſſed himſelf to go to his next work</p>
            <p>It will be convenient in this place to give you a brief account of Col. <hi>Francis Hacker,</hi> in regard that Col. <hi>Axtell</hi> and he were fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low priſoners and ſufferers together. He was a man of few words, and had not the gift of oratory, to deliver himſelfe as others could, yet was very ſweetly born up under his ſuffering, and had a very comfortable aſſurance that God had pardoned and accepted him in the blood of Chriſt; he had been a profeſſor of Religion many years in the Presbyterian way, and a great lover of godly Miniſters; a man of juſt and honeſt converſation amongſt men, and one that deſired to walke blameleſs in the ſight of God; his fellow priſoner did ſay he did believe that Col. <hi>Hacker</hi> had an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Col. <hi>Hacker</hi> declared to ſeverall of his own friends, a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſuffered, that the greateſt trouble he had upon his ſpirit was, <hi>that he had formerly born too great a prejudice in his heart towards the good people of God that differed from him in judgement.</hi> And then broke forth into this admiration<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>O what am I poore vile worme, that God ſhould count me worthy to ſuffer with ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſoules as theſe are, againſt whom I have been formerly ſo much prejudiced.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus theſe two gracious perſons having finiſhed their courſe, and the time of their departure being at hand, were both brought forth of priſon, the ſledge being ready for them, they took their leave of ſome friends that ſtood at the door, and Col. <hi>Axtell</hi> deſired them to be at the place of execution; and both en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring the ſledge they caſt up their eyes toward that God to whom they were comming; then with a chearfull countenance, ſetting themſelves down, they were drawn to <hi>Tyburne,</hi> the place of exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, where a cart was ſet ready, into which they both aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, their countenance not at all changed, though now the King of terror ſtared them in the face; the Ropes being then put about
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:115260:48"/>
their necks, and a burning fire kindled before their faces; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there ready to receive that ſentence which nature would have ſunk under, if grace had not ſupported, firſt Col. <hi>Axtel</hi> applies him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the Sheriffe in theſe following words:</p>
            <div type="speech">
               <head>Col. <hi>Axtels</hi> ſpeech at <hi>Tyburne,</hi> Octob. 19. 1660.</head>
               <p>Mr. Shieriffe, <hi>I am now as you ſee come to the place of execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, according to my ſentence. I deſire your leave that I may ſpeak freely and without interruption; firſt to this people, and then to God, for it is the laſt that I ſhall ſpeak in this world, and I hope it will redowne to your account.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr. Shieriffs reply.</hi> Sir, you know what the Court prohibited you to ſpeak and what was ſpoken at the barre of the Court was there deſided, therefore tis needleſs to repeat it here. I hope you will keep to the preſent buſineſſe that concerns you, and not goe out into impertinences; and becauſe you have but a little time ſpend it to your beſt advantage, and the good of the people, and then you ſhall not be interrupted. Or to the ſame effect.</p>
               <p>Col <hi>Axtel</hi> begins. <hi>I ſay the very cauſe for which I have engaged is contained in this book of God,</hi> (having the Bible in his hand) <hi>both in the civil and religious rights of it, which I leave to you</hi> (gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the book to Mr. <hi>Knowles.</hi>)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>You ſee a dead man living, and yet I hope I ſhall live to all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, through the mediation of Jeſus Chriſt, the Mediator of the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of free grace,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I muſt truly tell you, that before <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> late wars, it pleaſed the Lord to call me by his grace, through the work of the Miniſtery; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards keeping a day of humiliation in faſting and prayer, with Mr.</hi> Simeon Aſh, <hi>Mr.</hi> Love, <hi>Mr.</hi> Woodcocke, <hi>and other Miniſters, in</hi> Laurence-lane <hi>they did ſo clearly ſtate the cauſe of the Parliament, that I was fully convinced in my own conſcience of the juſtneſs of the warre, and thereupon engaged in the Parliament ſervice, (which as I did and doe believe) was the cauſe of the Lord, I ventured my life freely for it, and now die for it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then Mr. Shieriffe ſaid to this purpoſe, Sir, remember your ſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:115260:49"/>Col. <hi>Axtell</hi> proceeds, <hi>And after the work of the Lord was done in</hi> England, <hi>my lot caſt me in the ſervice of</hi> Ireland, <hi>and I thank the Lord I was ſerviceable to the Engliſh Nation in that Country, and have diſcharged my duty fully according to the truſt committed to me there.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As for the Fact for which I now ſuffer, it is for words, onely for words, and but for words, and the ſentence is already reverſed in my own conſcience, and it will be reverſed by Jeſus Chriſt by and by, I pray God from the very bottome of my ſoul to forgive all that have had any hand in my death, both Witneſſes and Jury, and the Court that paſſed ſentence; for conſidering the Doctrine of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, as he hath laid it down,</hi> Matth. 5.44. It hath been ſaid of old time, love your Neighbours and hate your Enemies, But I ſay unto you love your Enemies, and pray for them that hate and deſpitefully uſe you, that you may be the Children of your Father which is in Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I deſire according to this Doctrine from the bottome of my heart that God would give them true repentance, and not lay their ſin to their charge, nor my blood which by Gods law and mans, (I think) could not juſtly have been brought here to ſuffer. But I bleſſe God I have ſome comfortable aſſurance, that</hi> I <hi>ſhall be embraced in the Arms of Chriſt, and have cauſe to hope that his ſpirit ſhall carry my ſoul into the Fathers hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And if the Glory of this Sunſhine be ſo great (the Sun then ſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bright) how much more is the glory of the Son of God, who is the Son of righteouſneſsſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I thinke it convenient to give you ſome Account of my Faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I believe all things written in the Old and New Teſtament, as the principles and doctrine of a believers Faith, I believe the bleſſed Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Chriſt, that it is our duty to hear the word preached, to ſeek unto God in prayer, and to performe Family duties, and to walk in the Communion of Saints; and for my own part,</hi> I <hi>am a Member of a Congregation, which I judge to be the way of Chriſt, (and were it for that only</hi> I <hi>were to dye, I could witneſſe to it) which is a company of men born again by his grace, that walk in the ways of Chriſt blameleſſe and harmleſſe. I believe Jeſus Chriſt dyed for poor ſinners, of whom</hi> I <hi>am chief, as the Apoſtle Paul ſaith,</hi> this is a
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:115260:49"/>
faithfully ſaying, and worthy of all acceptation, that Chriſt Jeſus came into the world to ſave ſinners, of whom I am chiefe. <hi>And if the Apoſtle might ſay ſo, much more may I.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My friends and Countreymen,</hi> I have reaſon to bewail my own unprofitable life, having been very unfruitful unto the people of the Lord, the Lord knows I have much fault upon my heart; were it not for the blood of Chriſt that cleanſeth and waſheth me, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his promiſe, ſaying, <hi>I loved you, and waſhed away your ſins in own blood.</hi> For there is no remiſſion of ſins without the blood of Chriſt. I deſire you all to loath and caſt off ſinne; it were better to ſuffer then to ſinne, it is beter to die then to ſinne; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could grive our Saviour but ſinne, and therefore have a care of that you and I muſt meet one day at the bar of Chriſt &amp; the Son of God ſhal be our Judge, for God hath committed all judgement to the Son, <hi>that all men ſhould honour the Son as they honour the Father.</hi> This day is a reſemblance of that day, therefore be ſerious beg as much good to your immortal ſouls as I expect to enjoy by and by. I beſeech you beg of God that he would ſave your ſoules, and omit no opportunity through the ſtrength of the Lord to believe, and put your truſt in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; be ſure to labour after aſſurance of your intereſt in him, or elſe you wil be of all men moſt miſerable; for I of all men were moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable if I had not believed to <hi>ſee the goodneſſe of the Lord in the land of the living.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Bleſſed be the Lord that brings me into this ſtate, let the way or means be what it wil; it is Gods ſoveraignty who made theſe creatures ſo to diſpoſe of them how he pleaſeth and God hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined this death for me, from all eternity. The Lord Chriſt often prayed <hi>thy will be done,</hi> this is the Lords wil. He hath numbred my daies, and my times are in his hand. Many ſeek the Rulers favor, but every ons judgement is from the Lord. When <hi>Pilat</hi> ſaid unto Chriſt, <hi>Knoweſt thou not that I have power to crucifie thee,</hi> Chriſt anſwered him, <hi>thou couldeſt have no power againſt me, except it were given thee from aboue.</hi> Therefore I acknowledge the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous hand of God, he is righteous but I am ſinful, <hi>Therefore will I beare Gods indignation, becauſe</hi> I <hi>have ſinned againſt him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is ſaid of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>that for the joy ſet before him he endured the croſs, and deſpiſed the ſhame, and is ſet down at the right hand
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:115260:50"/>
of God,</hi> where I hope to ſee him by and by, in glory and Majeſty, and to ſee his Angels and believers worſhipping of him, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I deſpiſe the ſhame. Our Saviour died upon the croſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinne, I am a ſinful creature, a wretched ſinner, and ſhall I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect better then he that was my maſter? he who was holy, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had a ſinful thought in all his life; and died not for himſelfe, but for us, that we might live through his death; that through his poverty we might to made rich. And Chriſt having done this for his people, it ſhould not be in their eyes thought a deſpicable thing that we ſhould ſuffer for him, having been engaged in the work of God. But Chriſt muſt prevail in righteouſneſs, and he wil prevaile.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now Mr. Sheriffe, I thank you for your civillity, and for this leave.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After this Col. <hi>Hacker</hi> ſpoke ſomething privately to him, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Col. <hi>Axtel</hi> ſaid, Mr. Shieriffe, muſt we both die together?</p>
               <p>Mr. Shieriffe anſwered, Yes.</p>
               <p>Then Col. <hi>Hacker</hi> read a paper which he had in his hand, a coppy whereof followeth:</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="letter">
                           <p>FRiends &amp; Country-men, all that have known me in my beſt eſtate, have not known me to have been a man of Oratory, and that God hath not given me the gift of utterance, as to others, therefore I have onely this briefly to ſay unto you that are ſpectators: As the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſtated the war, I did out of judgment and conſcience joyn with them, in the common cauſe, and have through grace been faithfull to it according to my meaſure. And as for that which now I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for, I do freely forgive both Judges, Jury, and Witneſſes, and all others; And I thank the Lord, to whom <hi>I</hi> am now going, at whoſe tribunall <hi>I</hi> muſt render an account, I have nothing lies upon my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeience as guilt whereof I am now condemned; and doe not doubt but to have the ſentence reverſt. <hi>I</hi> doe now apply my ſelfe unto God by prayer, and doe deſire the hearty prayers of all that fear God, that I may have a ſweet paſsage from this mortall life, to that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal life which God hath prepared for all that are in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Francis Hacker.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>After the reading of this he deſired that Col. <hi>Axtell</hi> would be both their mouths to God in prayer.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:115260:50"/>And then Col. <hi>Axtell</hi> ſaid, I deſire all that fear the Lord to hear me with patience, and to lift up their hearts to ſeek the Lord with me, that we may have his ſtrength, and the preſence of his ſpirit from this world to everlaſting life.</p>
               <p>And with a wonderful compoſed frame of ſpirit, and with an audible voice entred upon the following duty, wherein the Lord helped him with excellent expreſſions ſuitable to both their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The prayer followeth.</head>
               <p>OH! bleſſed Lord, the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt who art the great God of heaven and earth, heaven is thy throne, and the earth thy foolſtool, thou upholdeſt all things with and by the word of thy power. The iſſues of life and death are in thy hand, oh God. Bleſſed Lord, we pray thee let us have communion with thy ſelfe, and the glory of thy face, let the ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning rayes of Chriſt ſhine continually upon our ſouls. Lord, let there be no interruption between the brightneſs of thy glory and our ſouls, til we come into the fulneſs of the poſſeſſion of it. Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lord, we deſire to take ſhame before thee and this multitude, for all our iniquities and tranſgreſſions; we were born and came great ſinners into the world, the root of bitterneſs was in us, that flowed from that bitter fountain <hi>Adam:</hi> but thou, O Lord, haſt been pleaſed to ſend the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> that <hi>as by the ſinne of one man death entred into the world, ſo by the obedience and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of one Jeſus Chriſt many ſhould be made righteous.</hi> Bleſſed Lord, thou knoweſt all our original guilt, all upon our hearts, and upon our conſciences, all our perſonal defilements and tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; we pray thee Lord, waſh them all away in the blood of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. Lord we have nothing of our own to rely upon, but a Chriſt; for all our goodneſs and righteouſneſs is but as polluted rags and menſtruous cloaths. Therefore, O Lord, thou haſt ſaid by the workes of the Law no man ſhall be juſtified, but by the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt Jeſus. Therefore, oh Lord hold out the covenant of grace to poor believers, and make Jeſus Chriſt the Mediator of the covenant, to perform Gods part to us, and our part towards God. Oh lord, in thee are all our ſpring, thou art the fountain of all grace, let us have mercy and pardon from thee. Lord it is by grace that any here are ſaved. Thou ſhouldſt be a
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:115260:51"/>
righteous God if thou ſhouldeſt not only ſuffer us to lye under the condemnation of man, but to exclude us from heaven and glory for ever.</p>
               <p>But Lord if thou ſhouldſt be ſtrict to mark iniquity, who ſhould ſtand in thy preſence? but there is mercy with thee that thou mayſt be feared. Lord thou haſt ſaid, <hi>Who is a God like unto thee, pardoning iniquity, and paſſing by the tranſgreſſions of the remnant of thy people, for thine own names ſake.</hi> Lord, it is thy covenant, that thou wilt put thy ſpirit into our hearts, and erect thy law in our inward parts, and our ſins and tranſgreſſions thou wilt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member no more. Bleſſed be the Lord for the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: for had it not been for a Chriſt we were undone forever. Bleſſed be our Lord, that hath written our names in heaven, and given us a portion in Chriſt, in whom we have believed and truſted. We humbly beg of thee the pardon of all our perſonal and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly guilt; the ſins of our publique imployments, which thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt we have not willingly committed, though it may be through infirmity and temptation, and the ſins of our nature. Lord, we humbly pray thee, let us ſee our ſelves juſtified in the blood of our Lord Jeſus that we may ſay with the Apoſtle, Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods elect. It is God that juſtifieth us, it is Chriſt that died, yea rather that is riſen again for our juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. He is riſen that he might be our advocate, interceſſor, and mediator. He is filled with all the fulneſs of the Godhead, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute to us according to our need. Thou haſt promiſed by the Apoſtle, that God ſhall ſupply all our wants according to the riches of his own grace. Lord thou wilt have the paſſover eaten with ſowre hearbs, and Lord we are contented: but Lord thou haſt provided ſweet Wine for us, and haſt thou not kept the beſt Wine, and the beſt of thy divine comforts until now? til now? to carry us over this bridge, and paſſage from earth to heaven; ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie this our paſſage, for it is beſt to have the croſſe with the crown, they goe together, and are inſeparable: therefore ſaith our Lord they that wil ſuffer with me, ſhal alſo raign with me.</p>
               <p>Deare Lord, we pray thee give us a full experience, and let thy holy Spirit witneſs to our ſouls that we are the children of God, and reconciled to thee in the covenant; and that we ſhal through thy Son be glorified with thee. Strengthen our faith, that we may
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:115260:51"/>
be purged, waſhed and cleanſed, and for our juſtification, ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and acceptation with the Father.</p>
               <p>Glorious lord, we deſire to leave our requeſts with thee on the behalfe of this poor people, as the laſt requeſt we have to beg of thee on this ſide heaven; if there be any here not belonging to Chriſt, and not friends to him, Lord convert them; and ſhew them their own undone and miſerable eſtate, and give them the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of a dying Saviour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (thy poor ſervants would not part with a Chriſt for ten thouſand lives.) Lord make Chriſt precious to their immortal ſouls, Lord convince them of the evil of their ſins, and the evil of their own ways, and break them off from them; and cauſe them to cloſe with Jeſus Chriſt. Thou haſt promiſed that thoſe that come unto him thou wilt not caſt off. Remember all thy people and help them to perſevere in thy grace and love, and make them able to hold faſt the truth till thou come, and to quit themſelves like men, to ſtand faſt in the faith.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed Lord, we humbly pray thee to have mercy upon that great City, the place from whence we came. When thou reſolvedſt to deſtroy <hi>Sodom,</hi> thy ſervant <hi>Abraham</hi> expoſtulated with thee, and thou ſaidſt, <hi>if there were but ten righteous thou wouldſt ſave it:</hi> but Lord there are many tens of righteous ones in that City. It hath been a place where thou haſt been glorified, and where ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny godly Miniſters have been encouraged. O Lord, let it goe wel therefore with that great City, and let thy Goſpel have free paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage in the publique worſhip of it. Bleſs the government and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours thereof, and make them inſtruments to thy glorious praiſe. We pray thee have reſpect to the chief Magiſtrates that are come here by command to ſee execution done. Oh Lord we beg mercy for their ſoules. O that Chriſt would evidence himſelf more to their ſoules, and that we might meet in Heaven together, and be imbraced in the arms of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. And him that ſhal be the Executioner, &amp; muſt now waſh his hands in our blood, doe thou waſh his ſoul in the blood of Jeſus Chriſt; O lord, we pray thee that thou wouldeſt have pitty upon his ſoul, and let him know what it is to be waſhed in the blood of Chriſt, that fountain ſet open for him, and for uncleanneſs.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed Lord, help us thy poor creatures with ſtrength, for we have no ſtrength of our own. Thy word ſaith, that death is the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:115260:52"/>
King of terrours; but bleſſed be thy Name, thou haſt taken the ſting out of it, and the poyſon from it; and therefore as faith the Apoſtle, <hi>Oh death then, where is thy ſting? oh grave, where is thy victory? Thanks be to God, through Jeſus Chriſt, that hath given us the victory.</hi> Thou haſt ſaid by the Apoſtle, <hi>We have the ſentence of death in our ſelves, and therefore ſhould not truſt in our ſelves, but believe in Chriſt that raiſeth the dead.</hi> Lord, we will not truſt in our ſelves, but in the living God— Oh my God, that art the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and of <hi>Jacob,</hi> ſtrengthen and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port our poor ſouls. <hi>Stephen</hi> when he was ſtoned to death, ſaw the Heavens opened and the glory of the Father and of his throne; Shall we but ſee the Face of Jeſus Chriſt, bearing up our hearts under all, and we ſhall go through. Thou haſt promiſed that thou wilt never, never, never leave us nor forſake us. Thou haſt ſaid, <hi>Who can ſeparate us from the love of God in Chriſt Jeſus?</hi> Come life, come death, or what can ſeparate a believer from Jeſus Chriſt, let thy Angels come downe, we are perſwaded that the Angels are ready to receive our ſoules, and to carry them into thy boſome, and into the company of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and of the bleſſed Apoſtles and Martyrs, and witneſſes of Jeſus, and juſt men made perfect in thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Bleſſed lord, thou art our ſupport and comfort, ſupport us with the cordials of thy love.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed lord, before we make an end of praying, O thou father of mercies, and God of all conſolation, we beg one requeſt for the chief Magiſtrate of this Nation, That thou wouldeſt give him a glorious Chriſt into his poor ſoul, and magnifie thy grace towards him, that he may become a friend unto Chriſt, and a friend to the people of Chriſt, and raigne in righteouſneſſe; and may be a terrour to evill doers, and a praiſe to them that doe wel; that he may caſt away iniquity with his eye, &amp; rule for God, before whom he and all others muſt render an account in the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Lord hear us for him. And bleſſed lord doe the like for all that had any uncharitableneſs towards us, we would have none towards them, but we beg their ſouls might live in thy preſence; make them to ſee their ſins, and let them receive their pardon, that we might embrace one another through the grace of God, in Jeſus Chriſt, one day in Heaven. Dear Father, we pray thee for
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:115260:52"/>
them, as we would beg for our ſelves.</p>
               <p>We now deſire to reſign up our ſelves into thy boſome as it is thy Command; thou haſt ſaid, <hi>Ye are bought with a price not with ſilver or gold, but with the precious bloud of Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> and we offer up our bodies and ſouls unto Chriſt, which is but a reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſervice, that thou ſhouldeſt have all when thou calleſt for them, our eſtates and lives themſelves. The Earth is the Lords, and the fulneſſe thereof, and we are all his works: It is God's ſoveraignty to command whatſoever he pleaſeth. Bleſſed Lord, we deſire with our Lord Jeſus, when he offered up himſelf upon the Croſſe, he ſaid unto thee, <hi>O Father, into thy hands I commend my ſpirit;</hi> and with <hi>Stephen</hi> when he was put to death, <hi>Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus receive my ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So ſay we Lord Jeſus receive our ſpirits, pity us, love us, and accept us, in thy Son upon whom we reſt for life and ſalvation. Lord let us know that death is a paſſage into Glory; it is appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for all men once to dye, and after death to Judgement. This is a decree and ſtatute law of Heaven, that all muſt dye, and this is ſome comfort in our death, that from this time forward, we ſhall ſinne no more, grieve Chriſt no more, diſhonour God no more, nor offend any elſe no more; ſet thy love upon our ſoules and let our prayers be diſſolved into praiſes, where we may em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace thee, and thou embrace us.</p>
               <p>We humbly intreate thee do more abundantly for us and all them we have prayed for, then we are able to ask or think, in the name, and for the ſake, of our Lord Jeſus, who is the interceſſour with the Father, who hath promiſed that he will pray the Father for us; he is the Mediator of the new Covenant, betwixt God and us, our fulneſſe, our ſtrength, our comfort and our ſupport, our all, in his name we ask all our requeſts; to whom with thy ſelf and thy holy ſpirit we deſire to give all Honour and Glory and Praiſe for ever more, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After he had ended his prayer, he gave the Sheriffe thanks a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain for his civility, and then turning to Col. <hi>Hacker,</hi> they ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and embraced each other in their Armes, and ſaid, the lord ſweeten our paſſage and give us a happy meeting with himſelf in Glory.</p>
               <p>Then pulling his Cap over his Eyes, expecting as is ſuppoſed
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:115260:53"/>
that the Cart ſhould be drawn away, with his hands lifted up, he uttered theſe words with a loud and Audible voyce, Lord Jeſus receive my ſpirit; but the Cart ſtaying a little longer, he lift up his hands the ſecond time, and with the like audible and loud voyce ſaid, into thy hands Oh Father I commend my ſpirit; and yet in regard there was no man found to put forward the horſe to draw away the Cart until the common Hang-man came down out of the Cart himſelf to do it. The Carman as many witneſſes affirm, ſaying, he would loaſe his Cart and Horſe before he would have a hand in hanging ſuch a man; by this means he had op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to lift up his hands and utter the like words the third time alſo.</p>
               <p>One thing more is very remarkable, that when Col. <hi>Axtell</hi> and Col. <hi>Hacker</hi> were taken out of the ſledge into the cart; the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators being in great numbers there, behaved themſelves very civilly, only two perſons among them as ſoon as the Ropes were put about their Necks, cryed out very earneſtly, hang them, hang them Rogues, Traytors, Murtherers, Hang-man draw away the cart; whereupon a man that ſtood by them, deſired them to be civil, and ſaid, Gentlemen, this is not civil, for the Sheriff know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth what he hath to doe; and thereupon they were ſilent and gave attention to Col. <hi>Axtell</hi>'s ſpeech and prayer; but before he had done, thoſe very perſons were ſo affected, that they could not refrain from pouring out many Tears upon the place, and went aſide to a place a little more retired to weep, and that man that before deſired them to be civil, went after them and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held them, to his great admiration, as himſelf hath Narrated.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115260:53"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> In regard that the Preſſe could not conveniently be attended, there are many faults committed in this Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſome Sentences left out, and others miſplaced, which doth much alter the ſence; therefore thou art earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, before the reading of this book, to take thy Pen and Correct theſe following Errours, and for others which are leſſe conſiderable, it's hoped thy ingenuity will help thee to Correct them.</head>
            <div type="errata">
               <head>ERRATA.</head>
               <p>PAge 14. Line 11. for but the enemy, read <hi>but for the enemy.</hi> P. 15. l. 19 <hi>Allured us.</hi> p. 21. l. 22. by, r. <hi>be.</hi> p. 23. l, 28. own, r. <hi>one.</hi> p. 26. l. 28. love, r. <hi>Job.</hi> p. 28. l. 21. take the, r. <hi>take your.</hi> p. 33. l. 9. and all, r. <hi>for all.</hi> p. 33. l. 18. therein I have done, r. <hi>I have done therein</hi> p. 33. l. 26. Galliaſſes, r. <hi>Galliſlaves.</hi> p. 33. l. 35. the faith, r. <hi>your faith.</hi> p. 36. l. 9. and if, r. <hi>but if.</hi> p. 37. l. 22. they ſhould, r. <hi>they may.</hi> p. 38. l. 26. wittingly, r. <hi>willingly.</hi> P. 39. l. 20. any, r. <hi>my.</hi> p. 41. l. 15. teahes thence, r. <hi>netles them.</hi> p. 41. l. 34. in mercy, r. <hi>through mercy.</hi> p. 43. l. 31. our, r. <hi>one.</hi> p, 44. l. 5. moſt, r. <hi>muſt.</hi> p. 44. l. 9. Father, r. <hi>Author.</hi> p. 45. l. 13 dulcimum, r. <hi>dulciſſimum.</hi> p. 45. l. 32. them, r. <hi>theirs.</hi> p. 47. l. 7. in, r <hi>to.</hi> p 47. l. 21. Heronian, r. <hi>Neronian.</hi> P. 48. l. 23. leaſt, r. <hi>beſt.</hi> p. 49. l. 28. while, r. <hi>which.</hi> p. 50. l. 8. Know, r. <hi>Knew.</hi> p. 52. l. 37. ſolid &amp; zeal, r. ſolid comfort &amp; — p. 58. l. 23. the Mans, r. <hi>Hemans.</hi> p. 62. l 6. dele <hi>the ſame.</hi> p. 62. l. 7. that glorious, r. <hi>that that glorious.</hi> p. 62. l. 10. in it. Thou, r. <hi>in it thou</hi> (without the full point.) p 62. l. 15. <hi>through or,</hi> that muſt be left out. p. 64. l. 5. the Lord r. <hi>O Lord.</hi> p. 71. l. 8. truth of r. <hi>truth guilty of.</hi> p. 85. l. 8. redoune r. <hi>redound.</hi> p. 89. l 6. much faith r. <hi>much filth.</hi> p. 89 l. 8. I loved r. <hi>I have loved.</hi> p. 89. l. 15. honour the Father r. <hi>honour the Son as they honour the Father.</hi> p. 89. l. 26. theſe r. <hi>his.</hi> p 89. l. 27. <hi>leave out</hi> (ſo) p. 90. l. 9. their r. <hi>your.</hi> p. 91. l. 17. interruption r. <hi>interpoſition.</hi> p. 92. l. 9. erect r. <hi>write.</hi> p. 92. l 35. experience r. <hi>evidence.</hi> p. 92. l. 38. that we may r. <hi>that we may lay hold upon a naked Chriſt that by his blood we may,</hi> &amp;c. p. 93. l. 34. upon his ſoul, r. <hi>upon his ſoul, and remember him in his low eſtate.</hi> p. 93. l. 36. for him r. <hi>for ſinne.</hi> p. 94. l. 16. come life come r. <hi>can life can death.</hi> p. 94. l. 23. of thy love, r. <hi>of thy love, O thou Father of mercy and God of all conſolation.</hi> And leave that ſentence out in the next line.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
